<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <title>The Generation Z Blog</title>
    <link href="https://blog.thegenz.org/feed.xml" rel="self" />
    <link href="https://blog.thegenz.org" />
    <updated>2021-03-05T21:45:09-05:00</updated>
    <author>
        <name>Ishan Vepa</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://blog.thegenz.org</id>

    <entry>
        <title>Why are we Going to Mars?</title>
        <author>
            <name>Ishan Vepa</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://blog.thegenz.org/why-are-we-going-to-mars.html"/>
        <id>https://blog.thegenz.org/why-are-we-going-to-mars.html</id>

        <updated>2021-03-05T21:43:43-05:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://blog.thegenz.org/media/posts/66/maxresdefault-Rohan-Thapliyal.jpg" alt="Graphic of Space Craft Launching." />
                    In the last few decades, the human race has progressed substantially and exponentially. We have created supercomputers that can fit in the palm of your hand, manned rockets to enter space, and, eventually, will be able to create colonies in other planets. Of course, progress&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <img src="https://blog.thegenz.org/media/posts/66/maxresdefault-Rohan-Thapliyal.jpg" alt="Graphic of Space Craft Launching." />
                <p><span style="font-weight: 400;">In the last few decades, the human race has progressed substantially and exponentially. We have created supercomputers that can fit in the palm of your hand, manned rockets to enter space, and, eventually, will be able to create colonies in other planets. Of course, progress is only made when we need a solution to a problem, and the problem that we are solving by colonizing Mars is the ongoing issue of our planet slowly dying. Dying due to our man-made pollution, our seemingly never-ending issue of deforestation, and our lapse in judgement in believing these to be non-issues. </span></p>
<p class="msg msg--highlight "><em><strong>Our race to Mars may be our last hope of our species’ survival.</strong></em></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;"> </span><span style="font-weight: 400;">To stray away from the existential crisis that is the human races’ mortality, our trials leading up to where we are today in space travel have been very successful. We are on the verge of being able to take a portion of our population to a different planet and have a fresh start free from the Earth’s problems. In fact, there are multiple ways we could be going about starting these colonies, from creating buildings with aerogel insulation, to fully terraforming planets, starting the growth of a habitable atmosphere as well as new life. Of course, these are a far cry from where we are today in technology and “on the verge” may actually mean “on the first few steps towards”.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;"> </span><span style="font-weight: 400;">So, why are we spending so much time trying to go to Mars if it’s a project that may not even be completed in our lifetimes? Why are we spending all this time looking for a way off of this planet instead of looking for a way to save it? Well, while Elon Musk, the owner of SpaceX, is trying to find ways to get to Mars, he also owns a company that’s actively trying to stop global warming. Tesla has made major leaps in the past decade, at first creating expensive electric cars that people saw as gimmicks, but then improving the cars while making them more affordable for a larger consumer base. Though it may seem to be all in the pursuit of cash, it may also be a way for a large portion of our population to stop using gas powered vehicles and a way to start a new generation of cars, free from air pollution. Elon Musk has even gone on record saying this was the very reason he started Tesla, though I wouldn’t give him too much credit. He is a multi-billionaire after all.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;"> </span><span style="font-weight: 400;">While it’s easy to say “Why even try to save Earth if we have other planets to fall back on,” you must remember that even the billionaires trying to colonize other planets are trying to save it at the same time. We cannot just watch idle waiting for some genius to find the easy way out of our situation. Earth is dying, and we’ll have to take the right steps to try and save it before it comes to us having to abandon ship. </span></p>
<p class="post__lead"><strong>What you can do to help.</strong></p>
<ul>
<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"><span style="font-weight: 400;">Save electricity- try to turn off lights when they aren’t needed</span></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"><span style="font-weight: 400;">Try to limit use of your own car- use public transportation, bikes, or walk when you can</span></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"><span style="font-weight: 400;">Invest in clean energy for your house- (if you can) try to buy solar panels or look into getting energy for your house from clean energy plants</span></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"><span style="font-weight: 400;">Vote- (if your old enough) vote for a candidate that addresses climate change and plans to help prevent it from continuing</span></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"><span style="font-weight: 400;">Speak up- talk to your friends and family to spread the word: without change, our planet will die</span></li>
</ul>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Voting Options</title>
        <author>
            <name>Ishan Vepa</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://blog.thegenz.org/voting-options.html"/>
        <id>https://blog.thegenz.org/voting-options.html</id>
            <category term="#vote"/>
            <category term="#political"/>
            <category term="#infrastructure"/>

        <updated>2021-03-05T21:45:09-05:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://blog.thegenz.org/media/posts/65/1A73AF6D-B26E-4D0C-88EE-8C8EBD324139-Ryan-Shankar.jpeg" alt="Voting Ballots being Organized " />
                    This year has been very abnormal and many aspects of people lives have been affected. Now voting for the next president will be too. The pandemic is raging and has shown no signs of slowing down, therefore in person voting will not be possible because&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <img src="https://blog.thegenz.org/media/posts/65/1A73AF6D-B26E-4D0C-88EE-8C8EBD324139-Ryan-Shankar.jpeg" alt="Voting Ballots being Organized " />
                <p><span style="font-weight: 400;">This year has been very abnormal and many aspects of people lives have been affected. Now voting for the next president will be too. The pandemic is raging and has shown no signs of slowing down, therefore in person voting will not be possible because of the coronavirus. It seems like mail in voting will be one of the primary options for voting this year. Many oppose mail in voting for a plethora of reasons. The main argument against it, has been voter fraud which is a very valid argument. At the other end of the spectrum, voters say it allows them to stay safe and vote from home. If mail in voting isn’t allowed, voters options are in person voting or online voting, the problem with online voting is how easily it can be tampered with as we saw during the last election. In person voting us unsafe for most people.</span><span style="font-weight: 400;"> </span></p>
<p class="msg msg--highlight "><strong><i>What are the risks and benefits of voting by mail?</i></strong></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">There are many pros of voting by mail. The major one is, that voters will be able to vote safely from the comfort of their home. There is very large percentage of people who don’t vote. They say its because voting is a major hassle, because they have to wait in long lines and many would rather spend their time doing other things. With mail in voting, it is convenient for most of the people who find in person voting tedious. This is a very good thing, as voter turnout will greatly increase but this plays into voter fraud. Increased voter turnout leads to many questioning the integrity of the votes, because of how easy it is to fake votes with the mail system. A large amount of money would have to be given to USPS, which is already being discussed by the House of Representatives. If this bill which would give a substantial amount of money to the USPS doesn’t pass it will make mail in voting extremely difficult and slow. Mail in voting is very important, but it has to be done right or else it could very easily be disregarded and pushed to the side.</span></p>
<p class="msg msg--highlight "><strong><i>What other ways can I vote?</i></strong></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">In person voting is still allowed in some states such as Montana. But other states only have online voting like Texas and Tennessee, these states political affiliations do play a part in this. Voting by mail is not allowed in all states. Voting by mail in states which don't allow it, is known as absentee voting, and depending on the state require a excuse/reason. </span></p>
<p class="msg msg--highlight "><strong><i>Pros and Cons of Online Voting </i></strong></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Online voting is a very controversial topic and is being debated currently. In 2016 online voting was used, and some hints of Russian meddling was found in the election. This is obviously a major problem, and if someone can hack into the voting system it will create a massive problem because of how it changes the democracy which the U.S prides itself on. But not all aspects of online voting is negative. Online voting is very convenient for many and is arguably easier than mail in voting but has more potential for fraud.</span></p>
<p class="align-center"><strong><i>Conclusion</i> </strong></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Mail in voting is good and is very beneficial for many people, because of how easy it is. But that also allows it to be very easily manipulated. While online voting has the same appeal as mail in voting if not more of an appeal to many, if tampered with online voting would have a more continuous results with more long term implications. Because of the pandemic I do not recommend in person voting but the choice is yours. Voting is a way to let your voice be heard and is a large part of the United States and it's foundation as a democracy. If you can vote let your voice be heard.</span></p>
<hr>
<p class="align-center"><em>Citations</em></p>
<p><a href="https://www.cnn.com/2020/08/19/politics/mail-in-vs-absentee-voting-2020-election/index.html"><span style="font-weight: 400;">https://www.cnn.com/2020/08/19/politics/mail-in-vs-absentee-voting-2020-election/index.html</span></a></p>
<p><a href="https://www.brennancenter.org/our-work/research-reports/why-vote-mail-option-necessary"><span style="font-weight: 400;">https://www.brennancenter.org/our-work/research-reports/why-vote-mail-option-necessary</span></a></p>
<p><a href="https://my.lwv.org/illinois/chicago/article/pros-cons-mail-voting"><span style="font-weight: 400;">https://my.lwv.org/illinois/chicago/article/pros-cons-mail-voting</span></a></p>
<p><a href="https://www.axios.com/how-to-vote-by-state-2020-307c3d17-ee57-4a1b-8bad-182ca1cdb752.html"><span style="font-weight: 400;">https://www.axios.com/how-to-vote-by-state-2020-307c3d17-ee57-4a1b-8bad-182ca1cdb752.html</span></a></p>
<p> </p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Progress in the fight against Covid-19</title>
        <author>
            <name>Ishan Vepa</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://blog.thegenz.org/progress-in-the-fight-against-covid-19.html"/>
        <id>https://blog.thegenz.org/progress-in-the-fight-against-covid-19.html</id>
            <category term="#globalconflict"/>
            <category term="#covid19"/>
            <category term="#coronavirus"/>

        <updated>2021-03-05T17:54:45-05:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://blog.thegenz.org/media/posts/64/EBT-L-FRIPROTEST-0606-7.jpg" alt="Covid Protest " />
                    This was written in Late 2020. Covid-19 has been devastating. It has impacted billions of people in one way or the other because of its infectivity and the quarantine measures put into place to stop the spread. Covid-19 is believed to have originated from a&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <img src="https://blog.thegenz.org/media/posts/64/EBT-L-FRIPROTEST-0606-7.jpg" alt="Covid Protest " />
                <p class="msg msg--info"><em><strong>This was written in Late 2020.</strong></em></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Covid-19 has been devastating. It has impacted billions of people in one way or the other because of its infectivity and the quarantine measures put into place to stop the spread. Covid-19 is believed to have originated from a Chinese wet market where a bat or pangolin transmitted the disease to humans. According to LiveScience, the first Covid-19 case was recorded in November of 2019. In August 19 2020, there were approximately 22.2 million cases confirmed worldwide and 783,000 deaths. This is an incredibly large amount of cases and deaths in less than a year. Countries have taken many precautions like limiting travel, testing for the virus, and requiring wearing masks in order to slow the spread. </span></p>
<p><strong>Quarantine: </strong></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;"> </span><span style="font-weight: 400;">Quarantine is perhaps the most important weapon against Covid-19 while a reliable vaccine is being made. Staying home and staying away from others is a better way to stay safe than wearing masks in public. Though masks are definitely a must if one goes to a public space, quarantine is a guaranteed way to not contract Covid. According to the CDC, people should quarantine if they think they have been close to someone with Covid-19 or you have recovered from symptoms. Research has shown that the virus can stay in the body for up to 3 months after recovery. So quarantine is the best way to play it safe and not risk the lives of others.</span></p>
<p><strong>Testing:</strong></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;"> </span><span style="font-weight: 400;">Getting tested for Covid-19 is another example of progress being made to control the virus. According to the CDC there are currently two types of tests: </span><a href="https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/testing/diagnostic-testing.html"><span style="font-weight: 400;">viral tests</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;"> and </span><a href="https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/testing/serology-overview.html"><span style="font-weight: 400;">antibody tests</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;">. A viral test tells you if you are currently infected. An antibody test tells you if you have been infected in the past. Getting tested is completely safe and helps stop the spread of the virus by identifying people that are currently infected so that they can take the necessary measures to keep others safe.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;"><strong>Vaccine:</strong> </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Currently, there is no reliable vaccine being produced to cure Covid. However, Russia recently approved the world’s first vaccine named Sputnik 5. The virus is completely safe according to Vladimir Putin, the President of Russia but many others including scientists are skeptical of its safety. There hasn’t been any evidence regarding the safety of the vaccine and large scale production has not begun </span><span style="font-weight: 400;"> </span><span style="font-weight: 400;">so we have yet to see where Russia’s vaccine will go. Meanwhile, most research efforts in other parts of the world are also focused on creating a vaccine for the virus. A main player in the vaccine race is Moderna, a U.S. biotech company who made one 1 of 3 vaccines that were cleared for Phase 3 of testing by the U.S. government. Other two are European companies from England and Germany.</span></p>
<hr>
<p class="align-center"><em>Citations</em></p>
<p><a href="https://www.raps.org/news-and-articles/news-articles/2020/3/covid-19-vaccine-tracker"><span style="font-weight: 400;">https://www.raps.org/news-and-articles/news-articles/2020/3/covid-19-vaccine-tracker</span></a></p>
<p><a href="https://www.livescience.com/first-case-coronavirus-found.html"><span style="font-weight: 400;">https://www.livescience.com/first-case-coronavirus-found.html</span></a></p>
<p><a href="https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/if-you-are-sick/quarantine.html"><span style="font-weight: 400;">https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/if-you-are-sick/quarantine.html</span></a></p>
<p><a href="https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/symptoms-testing/testing.html"><span style="font-weight: 400;">https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/symptoms-testing/testing.html</span></a></p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>The AAVE Dialect: It&#x27;s Not Broken English</title>
        <author>
            <name>Ishan Vepa</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://blog.thegenz.org/the-aave-dialect-its-not-broken-english.html"/>
        <id>https://blog.thegenz.org/the-aave-dialect-its-not-broken-english.html</id>
            <category term="#society"/>
            <category term="#oped"/>
            <category term="#inequality"/>
            <category term="#generations"/>
            <category term="#education"/>
            <category term="#community"/>
            <category term="#class"/>
            <category term="#BLM"/>

        <updated>2021-03-02T09:00:25-05:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://blog.thegenz.org/media/posts/63/AAVE-Awol9.jpg" alt="Using Black Vernacular English (BVE) as a Non-Black Person Isn&#x27;t ‘Woke’ If You Don&#x27;t Understand the History." />
                    America has a vast diversity of different races of foreign immigrants and visitors. These people allow Americans to notice and appreciate fascinating foreign culture including traditions, language, accent, and more. However, there are some aspects of culture American citizens perceive as inappropriate--possibly even thugs or&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <img src="https://blog.thegenz.org/media/posts/63/AAVE-Awol9.jpg" alt="Using Black Vernacular English (BVE) as a Non-Black Person Isn&#x27;t ‘Woke’ If You Don&#x27;t Understand the History." />
                <p><span style="font-weight: 400;">America has a vast diversity of different races of foreign immigrants and visitors. These people allow Americans to notice and appreciate fascinating foreign culture including traditions, language, accent, and more. However, there are some aspects of culture American citizens perceive as inappropriate--possibly even thugs or criminals; for other cultures, the same may be true the other way around. One of the most important examples is African American Vernacular English (AAVE), a dialect of English used mainly by African Americans in the southern US. America’s diversity makes the topic of AAVE an issue since it is often associated as a broken form of English by most people. This is the most obvious conclusion people come to after hearing others speak it. </span></p>
<p class="msg msg--highlight "><em><strong>But based on the history of African Americans living in slavery and segregation, this dialect is a part of culture and not a depiction of a lack of education, which is something everybody must understand.</strong></em></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">AAVE arose after slaves were brought from Africa to the Caribbean over two centuries ago, who came into contact with English-speaking slave masters and indentured servants from Europe. Unlike other Caribbean creoles (languages developed as a result of contact between two languages from an earlier “pidgin” state), AAVE has been nearly identical to Standard English, which was possibly due to the slaves learning English from the less educated and less proficient indentured servants (who still technically spoke English). As these slaves were shipped from the Caribbean to the US, the dialect developed further with other idioms and expressions--some that may come as a surprise to people who use these idioms without knowing about their origin. </span></p>
<p class="msg msg--highlight "><strong><em>So the fact that this dialect originated from enslaved ancestors not being able to have a proper education is important to understand.</em></strong></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">One of the most widely used idioms in AAVE, “to give props”, is actually used very often in Standard English as “Props to him for figuring it out!”. The word “ain’t” originated from AAVE and is also used casually in certain dialects of English. However, there are features of AAVE that are almost always considered to be grammatical errors in Standard English: double negatives, using the same verb for singular and plural subjects, and using “be” instead of “is” and “are”. For example, “Ain’t nobody got time for that”, “We was workin’”, and “They be hittin’ the door” are examples of what a Standard English speaker would falsely perceive as incorrect English.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">One important thing people should understand is that they must create habits where they only speak AAVE in acceptable scenarios, not </span><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">all </span></i><span style="font-weight: 400;">scenarios. That being said, if you still doubt the fact that AAVE is a separate dialect from Standard English, just understand that when you hear people speaking it in public, it does not mean they are uneducated or thugs. They simply happen to be speaking an informal dialect that is perfectly acceptable in informal situations, like with friends and family. Hopefully you now have a better understanding about how we must accept the cultures and lifestyles of other people in America.</span></p>
<hr>
<p class="align-center"><em><span style="font-weight: 400;">Citations</span></em></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;"> AAVE - African American Vernacular English, by Paul from the Langfocus YouTube Channel: https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=UZpCdI6ZKU4</span></p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Genetic Engineering: Creating Our Future or Our Demise?</title>
        <author>
            <name>Ishan Vepa</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://blog.thegenz.org/genetic-engineering-creating-our-future-or-our-demise.html"/>
        <id>https://blog.thegenz.org/genetic-engineering-creating-our-future-or-our-demise.html</id>
            <category term="#science"/>
            <category term="#engineering"/>

        <updated>2021-03-02T08:56:00-05:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://blog.thegenz.org/media/posts/62/Genetic-Engineering-Article-Photo-Alyson-Torino.jpg" alt="Genetic Engineering Graphic" />
                    Everybody has heard the phrase “when pigs fly” at some point in their lives, usually as a response when asking for permission to do something. Well, that retort is no longer useful because with the help of genetic engineering, in theory, we could modify pigs&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <img src="https://blog.thegenz.org/media/posts/62/Genetic-Engineering-Article-Photo-Alyson-Torino.jpg" alt="Genetic Engineering Graphic" />
                <p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Everybody has heard the phrase “when pigs fly” at some point in their lives, usually as a response when asking for permission to do something. Well, that retort is no longer useful because with the help of genetic engineering, in theory, we could modify pigs to be able to fly. To my knowledge, that hasn’t happened yet, but it very well could if someone put their mind to it. Humans have been genetically modifying organisms indirectly, with techniques like selective breeding, for hundreds of years, and only recently have scientists figured out how to do this directly. Specifically, the first recorded instance of direct genetic modification was in 1973 by Herbert Boyer and Stanley Cohen, when they combined the DNA of two different viruses. </span></p>
<p class="msg msg--highlight "><em><strong>Since then, genetic engineering has improved immensely, which, as with most new scientific discoveries, has its positive and negative effects. </strong></em></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Let’s begin with the positives. Among one of the most useful things genetic engineering can do is create medicine. One of the most common of these is insulin for patients with diabetes. Scientists have altered the DNA of bacteria, for example yeast and E. coli, to produce insulin similar to the insulin humans produce. The gene in human DNA that codes for insulin production is removed from a human cell and then placed into the bacteria. When the bacteria cells divide, insulin is produced. After the insulin undergoes a purification process, it is packaged and ready to be used by those who need it. Genetic engineering can also be used to enhance crops. This means that we can make them grow faster, grow larger, and to be resistant to bacteria. Some crops have also been modified to be able to grow with less nutrients available. The first genetically modified foods began being sold around 1994. The entirety of generation z has been eating genetically modified foods since the day we were born, so what exactly are the negative effects of genetic engineering?</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">At the surface, genetic engineering seems like it’s harmless, but once you take a deeper look at the modified organism, you can see that not everything is exactly as it should be. In genetically modified crops, the nutrients inside of them are significantly less than those that are not modified. Chicken is also a fantastic example of this. In genetically modified chickens, the amount of fat increases by over 220%, as well as a significant decrease in the amount of protein. Genetic engineering can make a crop resistant to certain pathogens, but pathogens are organisms too that undergo evolution. Pathogens can evolve to overcome any resistance that we modified crops to have, strengthening the pathogen and making it harder to stop. It has also been observed in plants modified to grow well in a drought that they are more sensitive to sunlight, meaning too much sunlight could be harmful to them. Genetic engineering also has environmental consequences. Eventually, the modified organisms will make their way into the wild. With their modifications, they will likely survive easier than non-modified organisms, which will decrease diversity and harm the ecology of that environment. Allergens have also been seen passing to different organisms when modified. While knowing the pros and cons of genetic engineering are important, they aren’t the most important thing to discuss when debating whether or not it’s a good idea. The most important thing to consider is if it is <em>ethical.</em></span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">I won’t go into this side of the issue too deeply, but this is where most of the debate over genetic engineering happens. Usually people are either all for it or all against it. People can debate over whether or not we should use it on plants and animals, and people too, but when it comes to bacteria and viruses, most people don’t care and even encourage it. However, as we are unfortunately well aware of at this time, microorganisms can be extremely harmful. If a mistake is made when working with bacteria or a virus, the aftermath could be catastrophic. There are already many antibiotic resistant bacteria (like mycobacterium tuberculosis, a strain of tuberculosis resistant to multiple types of antibiotics), and a mishap when trying to modify something can result in stronger diseases. While this is simply speculation on my part, it is still likely that this can occur.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Here’s the thing. When it comes to genetic engineering, the wide reach it has over various aspects of our lives, and the amount of knowledge we have about its effects on us and the environment, the equation seems unbalanced. In the grand scheme of things, it’s only been around for a short amount of time, so we can still learn about it and make changes that need to be made. The only piece of advice I have to give is to look for items in the grocery store marked non-GMO. If it doesn’t have that label, most likely, it has been modified in some way. Take what you will from this article, and I urge you to do more research for yourself, but who am I kidding? The next time someone takes a warning from an article like this will be when pigs fly.</span></p>
<hr>
<p class="align-center"><em><span style="font-weight: 400;">Citations</span></em></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Gaille, Louise. “13 Advantages and Disadvantages of Genetic Engineering.” </span><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">Vittana.org</span></i><span style="font-weight: 400;">, 16 Dec. 2019, vittana.org/13-advantages-and-disadvantages-of-genetic-engineering.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">“Genetic Engineering.” </span><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">Genome.gov</span></i><span style="font-weight: 400;">, www.genome.gov/genetics-glossary/Genetic-Engineering.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Patra, Satyajit, and Araromi Adewale Andrew. “Human, Social, and Environmental Impacts of Human Genetic Engineering.” </span><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">Journal of Biomedical Sciences</span></i><span style="font-weight: 400;">, IMedPub, 29 Oct. 2015, www.jbiomeds.com/biomedical-sciences/human-social-and-environmental-impacts-of-human-genetic-engineering.php?aid=7264.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">“What Is Genetic Engineering?” </span><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">Facts</span></i><span style="font-weight: 400;">, The Public Engagement Team at the Wellcome Genome Campus, 17 Feb. 2017, www.yourgenome.org/facts/what-is-genetic-engineering.</span></p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Systemic Racism Still Exists in Connecticut</title>
        <author>
            <name>Ishan Vepa</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://blog.thegenz.org/systemic-racism-still-exists-in-connecticut.html"/>
        <id>https://blog.thegenz.org/systemic-racism-still-exists-in-connecticut.html</id>
            <category term="#society"/>
            <category term="#lifestyle"/>
            <category term="#inequality"/>
            <category term="#blacklivesmatter"/>
            <category term="#advocacy"/>
            <category term="#BLM"/>

        <updated>2021-02-25T21:49:57-05:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://blog.thegenz.org/media/posts/60/ct_systematicRacism.jpg" alt="Connecticut Juneteenth Protest" />
                    Article Title: “Connecticut towns are declaring racism a public health crisis. Advocates want the state to follow” Author: Jenna Carlesso from the CT Mirror Summary: Activists want CT to declare racism a public health crisis because systemic racism in CT needs drastic measures to be&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <img src="https://blog.thegenz.org/media/posts/60/ct_systematicRacism.jpg" alt="Connecticut Juneteenth Protest" />
                <p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Article Title</span><span style="font-weight: 400;">: “<strong>Connecticut towns are declaring racism a public health crisis. Advocates want the state to follow</strong>”</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Author</span><span style="font-weight: 400;">: Jenna Carlesso from the CT Mirror</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Summary</span><span style="font-weight: 400;">:  Activists want CT to declare racism a public health crisis because systemic racism in CT needs drastic measures to be addressed and changed. Plus, racism also causes health issues for minorities such as black people. In addition, systemic racism in CT has caused black people to have less access to health care. By making a public health crisis declaration pertaining to racism, people will see how big of an issue it really is, and it will shed light on the racism that still exists in CT. The declaration will also bring more attention to the issue, allowing for more possible reforms and changes in the right direction.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Important Quotes From the Article</span><span style="font-weight: 400;">:</span></p>
<ul>
<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"><span style="font-weight: 400;">“The COVID-19 pandemic has brought Connecticut’s racial inequities into sharp focus. Black residents here are 2 ½ times more likely to die from a coronavirus infection than whites.”</span></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"><span style="font-weight: 400;">“People of color here are also more likely to work in high-risk, ‘essential’ jobs, such as those in nursing homes, grocery stores and retail, to live in densely populated communities, and to have higher rates of pre-existing conditions like diabetes and asthma that are caused or worsened by systemic racism.”</span></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"><span style="font-weight: 400;">“During the pandemic, residents in low income, predominantly minority neighborhoods have faced larger barriers to testing and other services. Until May, two-thirds of the state’s testing sites required a doctor’s note, and many people living in these communities have no insurance or primary care doctor to refer them.”</span></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"><span style="font-weight: 400;">“A study by the Connecticut Health Foundation in January highlighted links between discrimination and ‘negative physical and mental health consequences’ including depression, anxiety, hypertension, breast cancer, and giving birth preterm or having a low-birthweight baby. ‘Research suggests that one way discrimination could lead to poorer health is through repeated activation of the body’s stress response system, which can have negative long-term physiological and psychological effects,’ the foundation noted.”</span></li>
</ul>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Link to the Full Article</span><span style="font-weight: 400;">: </span><a href="https://ctmirror.org/2020/06/24/connecticut-towns-are-declaring-racism-a-public-health-crisis-advocates-want-the-state-to-follow/"><span style="font-weight: 400;">https://ctmirror.org/2020/06/24/connecticut-towns-are-declaring-racism-a-public-health-crisis-advocates-want-the-state-to-follow/</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;"> </span></p>
<hr>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Article Title</span><span style="font-weight: 400;">: “<strong>Racism in Connecticut’s education system must be exposed and corrected</strong>”</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Author</span><span style="font-weight: 400;">: Anita Samuels from the CT Mirror</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Summary</span><span style="font-weight: 400;">: There is still a lot of systemic racism in CT’s education system. Most of the educators making decisions about hiring other educators, and promoting other educators, are white. Black educators have to work harder than white educators in order to get hired or be recognized for a promotion. “Black educators in Connecticut, with the appropriate credentials, have found job attainment difficult in any district.” Connecticut’s attempts to increase minority teachers and school staff have failed. Black people often get interviews, but are not hired. There should not be a qualified black educator that is jobless. How are we supposed to get black people to go into education, when there’s a large possibility they may get rejected? There should be systematic monitoring of districts to see how many minority educators apply, how many are interviewed, how many are hired and how many are promoted.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Important Quotes From the Article</span><span style="font-weight: 400;">:</span></p>
<ul>
<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"><span style="font-weight: 400;">“The majority of educators, approximately 90%, making decisions on who gets hired, promoted in a district and even at the state level, are white.”</span></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"><span style="font-weight: 400;">“The study found that all black participants (certified educators) experienced and perceived unconscious bias and racial discrimination during the hiring process.”</span></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"><span style="font-weight: 400;">“In fact, in 2019, some districts in Connecticut had no minorities on staff; affluent districts employ few educators of color or none at all.For example, among Greenwich district’s 978 teachers, 2% were black; Darien district had 1% among 544; Westport and Wilton had fewer than 1%; and Weston district had none.”</span></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"><span style="font-weight: 400;">“According to the State’s Diversifying the Educator Workforce office, between 2013 and 2017, 739 qualified minority educators had not attained positions in Connecticut’s education system; approximately 300 black, and 350 Hispanic...According to Connecticut’s Department of Labor Statistics, there were approximately 651 teacher positions available, yearly, between 2013 and 2017; a total of 2,604. Not hiring 300 black educators total in that same time span is not acceptable.”</span></li>
</ul>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Link to the Full Article</span><span style="font-weight: 400;">: </span><a href="https://ctmirror.org/category/ct-viewpoints/racism-in-connecticuts-education-system-must-be-exposed-and-corrected/"><span style="font-weight: 400;">https://ctmirror.org/category/ct-viewpoints/racism-in-connecticuts-education-system-must-be-exposed-and-corrected/</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;"> </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">**At the bottom of the article you can actually look for how many minority students attend your school district in CT versus how many minority educators there are in your school district.</span></p>
<hr>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Article Title</span><span style="font-weight: 400;">: “<strong>Whites-only rules still surface in CT property records</strong>”</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Author</span><span style="font-weight: 400;">: Ken Dixon from the Middletown Press</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Summary</span><span style="font-weight: 400;">: When a couple was going to buy a small cottage near a lake, their lawyer found this in the contract: “No portion of this said premises shall be conveyed or leased to any other than the Caucasian Race.” Whites only rules were common in neighborhoods or areas of CT, even after the US Supreme Court case, Shelley v. Kraemer, outlawed restrictive housing in 1948. There are other racially restrictive contracts found in historic property documents throughout CT. These contracts have no legal effect, but they show the racism that still lingers in CT’s mostly white suburbs, and mostly minority populated cities. Property owners are able to take out the racist parts of the housing contracts, yet whites only rules still surface now. Other states have made it possible for homeowners to get rid of the racist part of their contracts, but keep the original wording on record in order to not whitewash history. Although racist housing contracts are not enforceable, there is still racial discrimination in CT’s housing today.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Important Quotes From the Article</span><span style="font-weight: 400;">:</span></p>
<ul>
<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"><span style="font-weight: 400;">“David K. Ware, a retired corporate lawyer and candidate for a master of laws degree at the University of Connecticut School of Law recently published a study that uncovered about 250 properties in three neighborhoods in the city of Manchester that had racially restrictive covenants.”</span></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"><span style="font-weight: 400;">“These covenants have not been legally enforceable since 1948, but housing discrimination is alive and well today. Discrimination is not always explicit. Thinly-veiled discrimination is at work today including exclusionary zoning ordinances, redlining, and source-of-income discrimination. Where we live affects every aspect of our lives—our health, safety, education, transportation, access to jobs, and more. This was true pre-1948, and is still true today.”</span></li>
</ul>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Link to the Full Article</span><span style="font-weight: 400;">:</span></p>
<p><a href="https://www.middletownpress.com/news/article/Whites-only-rules-still-surface-in-CT-property-15096547.php#photo-19114529"><span style="font-weight: 400;">https://www.middletownpress.com/news/article/Whites-only-rules-still-surface-in-CT-property-15096547.php#photo-19114529</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;"> </span></p>
<p> </p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Why Should I Have to Wear a Mask?</title>
        <author>
            <name>Ishan Vepa</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://blog.thegenz.org/why-should-i-have-to-wear-a-mask.html"/>
        <id>https://blog.thegenz.org/why-should-i-have-to-wear-a-mask.html</id>
            <category term="#society"/>
            <category term="#socialdistancing"/>
            <category term="#covid19"/>
            <category term="#coronavirus"/>

        <updated>2021-02-25T21:23:44-05:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://blog.thegenz.org/media/posts/59/Face-Masks-Abigail-Mullins.jpg" alt="" />
                    Keys? Check. Wallet? Check. For most of the world today, there is one more essential item they need before going out: a mask. However, the issue of wearing a mask has led to some conflict, especially in the United States. Although there are many reasons&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <img src="https://blog.thegenz.org/media/posts/59/Face-Masks-Abigail-Mullins.jpg" alt="" />
                <p>Keys? Check. Wallet? Check. For most of the world today, there is one more essential item they need before going out: a mask. However, the issue of wearing a mask has led to some conflict, especially in the United States.</p>
<p class="msg msg--highlight "><strong><em>Although there are many reasons as to why a person should wear a mask, there are still people asking “Why should I?”</em></strong></p>
<p>For some, the confusion in the beginning may have deterred them from wearing masks. Initially, the CDC sent out conflicting guidelines, saying mask wearing was not necessary. They changed this message on April 3, when they said that it was important to wear a mask. These two different messages may have made people confused, and damaged the credibility of the guidelines. However, there are two reasons for these conflicting messages. One, the CDC wanted to preserve masks for those who really needed it- medical workers. At the start of the pandemic there was a shortage of masks and the CDC wanted to make sure that medical workers were able to get them. Now, more companies are producing masks in order to supply for the demand, and buying reusable masks means that you won’t need to buy any more. The danger of not having enough masks is much less than it was at the start, so the CDC didn’t need to worry about that anymore. The second reason is because of a lack of testing. The less testing there is, the less positive tests for COVID-19. The less positive tests, the lower the count is for the infected. Once testing was able to pick up, the CDC saw that there were more cases than they initially had found. With masks more readily available and a spike in cases, the CDC chose to change their guidelines. As of early August, the CDC has not changed their mind. Masks are important in preventing the spread. With no major change in 4 months, the public should be assured that wearing masks is an important part of keeping COVID-19 at bay and that the CDC is firm in their decision.</p>
<p>Others may be avid followers of influencers, celebrities, and leaders to the point where they follow what they do religiously. Some of these well known people may not believe in wearing masks, or even promote themselves not wearing one. It is important to realize that a vast majority of these people are not health professionals and do not always make the right decision in terms of health. Do research yourself and don’t always follow someone else’s example. It is important to be well informed and make decisions based on what <em>you</em> believe and have researched and not solely on what a single person says or does.</p>
<p>In the end, the most important thing to consider is <em>why</em> you should wear a mask. COVID-19, like any virus, multiplies in your body. This causes the virus to become suspended in body fluids in the lungs, mouth and nose. When a person coughs, they spew droplets containing the virus, and a single cough could produce 3,000 droplets. Even when talking you’re sending out droplets. So what? Maybe you’re not in the same room at the same time as a person and can avoid those droplets, right? Wrong. Larger droplets can collect on surfaces and smaller droplets can stay suspended in the air, with the virus surviving for 3 hours, perhaps longer if the conditions are right. By wearing a mask, you limit the amount of droplets you breathe in and therefore limit your chances of catching the virus.</p>
<p>You might be thinking, <em>I’ll never catch the virus. I don’t have any medical problems, and I’m in the age group that doesn’t get affected. Even if I do get sick, I won’t have it bad.</em> You could be right. You could also be wrong. Many young, healthy individuals are hit hard with the virus. Even if you don’t get sick, the problem is the people you interact with. You may be asymptomatic, and while being unaware of having the virus, you may pass it on to someone who is at a higher risk for it. Your parents, grandparents, even younger people who have a medical issue that you’re unaware of. You may be the reason why they get sick. And that’s what’s so dangerous about this virus. It can be hard to be sure who’s sick and who’s not sick. That’s why wearing a mask is so important. It limits your chances of passing the virus on to others, and others of passing the virus to you.</p>
<p>Many anti mask wearers believe that they have the freedom to not wear a mask. That’s technically true. However, in that same respect, a business has that same right to not allow a person into their store. You have the freedom to not wear a mask, a business has the freedom to not let you in. You cannot have it all, especially when your choice affects the safety of other people.</p>
<p>You don’t have to wear a mask for yourself. But you need to wear it for other people. Why do I, a teenage girl with no underlying health problems, wear a mask? So I can protect my family and friends from getting the virus. If you can’t do it for you, do it for them. Wear a mask.</p>
<hr>
<p class="align-center"><em><span style="color: var(--text-editor-body-color); font-family: var(--font-base); font-size: inherit; font-weight: var(--font-weight-normal);">Citations</span></em></p>
<p><span style="color: var(--text-editor-body-color); font-family: var(--font-base); font-size: inherit; font-weight: var(--font-weight-normal);">Bai, Nina. “Still Confused About Masks? Here's the Science Behind How Face Masks Prevent Coronavirus.” </span><em style="color: var(--text-editor-body-color); font-family: var(--font-base); font-size: inherit; font-weight: var(--font-weight-normal);">Still Confused About Masks? Here's the Science Behind How Face Masks Prevent Coronavirus | UC San Francisco</em><span style="color: var(--text-editor-body-color); font-family: var(--font-base); font-size: inherit; font-weight: var(--font-weight-normal);">, 26 June 2020, <a href="http://www.ucsf.edu/news/2020/06/417906/still-confused-about-masks-heres-science-behind-how-face-masks-prevent">www.ucsf.edu/news/2020/06/417906/still-confused-about-masks-heres-science-behind-how-face-masks-prevent</a>.</span></p>
<p>Buchwald, Elisabeth. “Why Do So Many Americans Refuse to Wear Face Masks? Politics Is Part of It - but Only Part.” <em>MarketWatch</em>, MarketWatch, 28 June 2020, <a href="http://www.marketwatch.com/story/why-do-so-many-americans-refuse-to-wear-face-masks-it-may-have-nothing-to-do-with-politics-2020-06-16">www.marketwatch.com/story/why-do-so-many-americans-refuse-to-wear-face-masks-it-may-have-nothing-to-do-with-politics-2020-06-16</a>.</p>
<p>Cairomoon. “Face Masks.” <em>Pixabay</em>, 28 May 2020, <a href="http://www.pixabay.com/photos/face-masks-face-coverings-colorful-5228731/">www.pixabay.com/photos/face-masks-face-coverings-colorful-5228731/</a>.</p>
<p>Gillespie, Claire. “People Are Being Shamed on Social Media for Not Wearing a Face Mask in Public-But Why Won't They?” <em>Health.com</em>, 1 July 2020, <a href="http://www.health.com/condition/infectious-diseases/coronavirus/face-mask-refuse-to-wear-one-but-why">www.health.com/condition/infectious-diseases/coronavirus/face-mask-refuse-to-wear-one-but-why</a>.</p>
<p>Gray, Richard. “Why We Should All Be Wearing Face Masks.” <em>BBC Future</em>, BBC, 1 July 2020, <a href="http://www.bbc.com/future/article/20200504-coronavirus-what-is-the-best-kind-of-face-mask">www.bbc.com/future/article/20200504-coronavirus-what-is-the-best-kind-of-face-mask</a>.</p>
<p> </p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Hispanics Can Also Be Racist - Here&#x27;s Why</title>
        <author>
            <name>Ishan Vepa</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://blog.thegenz.org/hispanics-can-also-be-racist-heres-why.html"/>
        <id>https://blog.thegenz.org/hispanics-can-also-be-racist-heres-why.html</id>
            <category term="#society"/>
            <category term="#generations"/>
            <category term="#culture"/>
            <category term="#community"/>
            <category term="#advocacy"/>

        <updated>2021-02-23T09:21:24-05:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://blog.thegenz.org/media/posts/58/Landing_of_Columbus_.jpg" alt="Landing of Columbus" />
                    This summer has seen a lot more political and economic tension than ever before in most of our lifetimes. Racism has always been a point of discussion in the United States, especially in a post-Civil Rights Movement era. However, growing up in South Florida has&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <img src="https://blog.thegenz.org/media/posts/58/Landing_of_Columbus_.jpg" alt="Landing of Columbus" />
                <p><span style="font-weight: 400;">This summer has seen a lot more political and economic tension than ever before in most of our lifetimes. Racism has always been a point of discussion in the United States, especially in a post-Civil Rights Movement era. </span></p>
<p class="msg msg--highlight "><em><strong>However, growing up in South Florida has always gotten me to wonder how racism is handled in other parts of the world, specifically in Latin America.</strong></em></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Perhaps we should start with some history for context. In the early 16th century, the conquistadors landed in the Americas, following Columbus. Their expeditions were pure conquest -- finding land and resources for Spain. Their foreign germs murdered 90% of the native populations and what was left were either chased off, converted to Christianity, enslaved by the Spanish, or a combination of any of these. This could be where racism in Latin America truly started, but there is a key difference: the Spanish conquered for the sake of conquering. The argument could be made that there was hardly real racial motivation for colonizing the Americas, but the argument can be made for the opposite. However, by 1502, African slaves were already in the Caribbean. </span></p>
<p class="msg msg--highlight "><em><strong>This is, arguably, where the true racism began in colonial Latin America.</strong></em></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">While indigenous people were enslaved due to conquest, African slaves were a part of the Trans-Atlantic trade system -- also famously called the Colombian Exchange -- and so now the conquistadors found themselves with a question: What will the social hierarchy be? You have ethnocentric Europeans with two different kinds of enslaved peoples. The </span><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">casta </span></i><span style="font-weight: 400;">system that the Spanish developed was as follows, roughly: with the </span><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">peninsulares </span></i><span style="font-weight: 400;">at the top (white Europeans from the Iberian peninsula), </span><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">creoles</span></i><span style="font-weight: 400;"> just under (white Europeans born in the Americas), mestizos and mulattos, followed by indigenous people, and then black slaves all the way at the bottom -- because to the white conquistador, enslaved Africans were lesser than everyone. This was due to a combination of the notion of blood purity and racial segregation. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">This system of both political, economic, and social hierarchy is most probably the reason for modern-day racism in Latin America. Unlike in the United States, racism in Latin America is based on social and economic class. This may sound similar to racism in the U.S., but in Latin America: if you’re poor, then you’re black. In the United States, racism is often the opposite: if you’re black, then you must be poor. According to an article from the American Quarterly, “</span><span style="font-weight: 400;">As early as 1944, Alejandro Lipschutz, a Chilean anthropologist, coined the idea of Latin America as a ‘pigmentocracy’ -- where the region’s social hierarchies are ethnic or color-based. However, that idea was largely ignored until recently, when research using new census data on racial identification began to document racial inequalities. These studies generally show that Afro-descendant and Indigenous people occupy the lowest rungs on the income, educational and occupational ladders across Latin America.”</span><span style="font-weight: 400;"> But because Latin America as a whole is not the wealthiest of continents, funding and money are often pushed towards other projects. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The social aspect of it is also a factor because while in the United States, “negro” is compared to the n-word, but in Latin America, it is used a fond version of “homie” for people with darker skin. To us in the U.S., this appears to be racist. But in Latin America, oftentimes it’s not used as such. Its connotations depend entirely on the context. “Negrita(/o)” is used as a fond pet name for friends or family with dark skin, even if they’re not black. At the same time, it can be used as a slur as bad as the n-word when thrown around with hate behind it. </span></p>
<p class="msg msg--highlight "><em><strong>Because of all of this, racism is often overlooked. </strong></em></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">However, now this poses the question: how does this racism manifest itself in immigrants who come to the United States? It’s quite an interesting phenomena because here, Hispanics are no longer the majority; they’re the minority. Here in the U.S., they are often greeted with racism towards them, so why are some Hispanics still racist towards other minorities? By all logic, they shouldn’t. </span></p>
<p class="msg msg--highlight "><em><strong>They’re on the same level as them; they’re all facing the same racism and oppression. So, why?  </strong></em></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The answer is very complicated. For one, there is the notion of a sort of “protection.” Latinos are often encouraged to either marry people who are lighter skin than them or marry white people. Marrying lighter skin people has the connotations that you marry rich and that you’re gaining more “protection” from racism. It’s a practice of erasing culture and heritage for the sake of wanting -- what some would call -- a better life. This is the same reason why some Hispanics parents refuse to teach Spanish to their kids -- so that those kids don’t get picked on or have to experience racism like their parents did. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">There is also, however, a paradoxical feeling of superiority that leads to racism towards other minorities. This is mainly rooted in stereotypes portrayed in the United States that Hispanics families sometimes believe, such as how black people are called “thugs.” This reinforces the classist racism of Latin America, so the line between “poor therefore black” and “black therefore poor” is extremely blurred.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">So hopefully this has provided some insight on how racism manifests itself in different parts of the world, but also how it manifests itself when it is in the United States. </span></p>
<hr>
<p class="align-center"><em>Citations</em></p>
<p><a href="https://www.encyclopedia.com/science/encyclopedias-almanacs-transcripts-and-maps/impact-european-diseases-native-americans"><span style="font-weight: 400;">https://www.encyclopedia.com/science/encyclopedias-almanacs-transcripts-and-maps/impact-european-diseases-native-americans</span></a></p>
<p><a href="https://study.com/academy/lesson/the-spanish-casta-system-definition-significance.html"><span style="font-weight: 400;">https://study.com/academy/lesson/the-spanish-casta-system-definition-significance.html</span></a></p>
<p><a href="https://nativeheritageproject.com/2013/06/15/las-castas-spanish-racial-classifications/"><span style="font-weight: 400;">https://nativeheritageproject.com/2013/06/15/las-castas-spanish-racial-classifications/</span></a></p>
<p><a href="https://www.americasquarterly.org/article/the-effects-of-skin-color-in-the-americas/"><span style="font-weight: 400;">https://www.americasquarterly.org/article/the-effects-of-skin-color-in-the-americas/</span></a></p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Why should We Care About Space?</title>
        <author>
            <name>Ishan Vepa</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://blog.thegenz.org/why-should-we-care-about-space.html"/>
        <id>https://blog.thegenz.org/why-should-we-care-about-space.html</id>
            <category term="#space"/>
            <category term="#science"/>
            <category term="#oped"/>
            <category term="#community"/>
            <category term="#class"/>

        <updated>2020-12-27T11:07:14-05:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://blog.thegenz.org/media/posts/57/satellite.jpeg" alt="Satellite Graphic" />
                    Space is a wondrous place where we can unlock so many secrets of this reality we live in. Many people think that space travel isn’t important or that the rich are the only ones trying to figure out how to travel since they’ve destroyed Earth&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <img src="https://blog.thegenz.org/media/posts/57/satellite.jpeg" alt="Satellite Graphic" />
                <p class="msg msg--highlight "><span style="font-weight: 400;"><strong><em>Space is a wondrous place where we can unlock so many secrets of this reality we live in. </em></strong></span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Many people think that space travel isn’t important or that the rich are the only ones trying to figure out how to travel since they’ve destroyed Earth so much and don’t want to live in the future filth and I think both those ideas are absurd. First of all, with many different types of discoveries in space, we’ve learned that there are many planets out there that could be habitable and we’ve learned so much about the matter and how anti-matter works. Also, if the rich really wanted to get off of Earth and/or cared about the destruction of this planet, they would’ve funded space exploration a lot more.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Even though the Cold War was a horrible thing, it led to more activity in searching space, we now have satellites, have space stations, have sent someone to the moon, and have done many more things. With things like satellites and telescopes, we’re able to learn more about other planets, and how to either not become like them or to become more like them. Another thing satellites and space stations are useful for is tracking natural disasters, helping our internet, getting information about certain things whether it’s dangerous or not to the people, and helping us predict what will happen in the future.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Space is so much more than just a big empty area that is close and far away from Earth. It’s an area filled with amazing stars, galaxies, planets, and other things. It shows us how we most likely aren’t alone in this universe and how we’re really insignificant compared to everything else. Don’t get me wrong, everyone is still a valued human being, but to accept our insignificance and to look beyond the stars is such an amazing thing and something we could learn from. We could possibly also find alien life in the future whether it’s intelligent or not. Hopefully, it doesn’t find us first though, because as Stephen Hawking said “If aliens visit us, the outcome will be much as when Columbus landed in America, which didn’t turn out well for the Natives”.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">If more funding is put into space, and more people are interested in learning about it, many more secrets about the universe we live in could be unlocked, the way time and possible time travel works could also be discovered more in-depth. Even if scientists don’t put a lot of funding towards discovering space, they could use things like satellites and better stations to learn more about the Earth and unlock the secrets about our planet and the system.</span></p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>One Song at a Time: Music for Social Change</title>
        <author>
            <name>Ishan Vepa</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://blog.thegenz.org/one-song-at-a-time-music-for-social-change.html"/>
        <id>https://blog.thegenz.org/one-song-at-a-time-music-for-social-change.html</id>
            <category term="#society"/>
            <category term="#popculture"/>
            <category term="#music"/>
            <category term="#culture"/>

        <updated>2020-11-21T17:09:31-05:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://blog.thegenz.org/media/posts/56/66A37754-08E5-461F-BA17-31642CFCEA72-maddie-_3.jpeg" alt="&quot;The Stax Museum&quot;" />
                    People around the world love to listen to and create music. Music has always been a way for people to dance, to celebrate, and to live happy lives. However, music can be more than just a hobby or small enjoyment. Music can help us to&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <img src="https://blog.thegenz.org/media/posts/56/66A37754-08E5-461F-BA17-31642CFCEA72-maddie-_3.jpeg" alt="&quot;The Stax Museum&quot;" />
                <p><span style="font-weight: 400;">People around the world love to listen to and create music. Music has always been a way for people to dance, to celebrate, and to live happy lives. However, music can be more than just a hobby or small enjoyment. Music can help us to change the world. This change has occurred multiple times in the past; now our generation can look at those examples and find ways to utilize our music for <em>change.</em></span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">An extremely important example of music inspiring social change is the American Civil Rights Movement. During the 1950s and 60s, many successful musicians, both black and white, used their platforms and music to contribute to the movement. White singers such as Bob Dylan and Joan Baez wrote many songs about the social injustices occurring at the time and devoted large parts of their careers to civil rights. Freedom songs became very popular, especially in the 60s, and they were inspired by black church music. The Staple Singers, originally a gospel group, rose to fame at the height of the civil rights movement. They were signed to Stax Records, a producing company that embodied the collaboration of many different races at a time of social pandemonium. The co-owner of Stax, Jim Stewart, said, “</span><span style="font-weight: 400;">If we've done nothing more, we've shown the world that people of different colors, origins, and convictions can be as one, working together towards the same goal. Because we've learned how to live and work together at Stax Records, we've reaped many material benefits. But, most of all, we've acquired peace of mind. When hate and resentment break out all over the nation, we pull our blinds and display a sign that reads 'Look What We've Done—TOGETHER.'”. </span><span style="font-weight: 400;">All of the music that was created, performed, and shared during this time helped immensely in the movement. It inspired people to stand up for what they believed in and provided a sense of courage for those who were hesitant to take part. Music played a huge role in uniting a divided population to fight together for one of the most central movements in American history.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The idea of using music to inspire social change is still relevant today. A global producing company, Community Media for Development (CMFD) Productions, records both music and radio sessions for exactly this purpose. One of their projects, Musicians Against Xenophobia, united musicians from South Africa, Zimbabwe, and Mozambique to produce a small album centered around the social issue of discrimination. Other CMFD projects include multiple songs about HIV awareness, a radio program titled “Hungry City” that discusses the poor state of food security in South African countries, and a radio series about floods in Mozambique in 2013. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Because music is such an important part of popular culture today, it is a perfect platform to raise awareness about social issues. Artists can address their beliefs in person at concerts, reaching hundreds of people at the same time. Songs on the radio are repeated over and over, which drills important messages into people’s minds. When someone learns and sings along to a song, they can then spread the message to others as well as have more understanding for what the song is truly about. Music is not just a form of entertainment. It contains the messages and ideas of artists who are truly passionate about what they believe in. These messages can often be overlooked by the audience. As a generation, it is important for us to stop and listen to what people are trying to say. If we think about what the artists are trying to tell us, we can create a united generation of people who are courageous and inspired enough to bring about social change. We can change the world for the better, one song at a time. </span></p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
</feed>
