<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <title>The Generation Z Blog</title>
    <link href="https://blog.thegenz.org/feed.xml" rel="self" />
    <link href="https://blog.thegenz.org" />
    <updated>1969-12-31T19:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <author>
        <name>Ishan Vepa</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://blog.thegenz.org</id>

    <entry>
        <title>America&#x27;s Problem with Race: An In-depth Look at Racism and the Civil Rights Movement in America</title>
        <author>
            <name>Ishan Vepa</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://blog.thegenz.org/americas-problem-with-race-an-in-depth-look-at-racism-and-the-civil-rights-movement-in-america.html"/>
        <id>https://blog.thegenz.org/americas-problem-with-race-an-in-depth-look-at-racism-and-the-civil-rights-movement-in-america.html</id>
            <category term="#society"/>
            <category term="#oped"/>
            <category term="#generations"/>
            <category term="#community"/>
            <category term="#blacklivesmatter"/>
            <category term="#advocacy"/>
            <category term="#BLM"/>

        <updated>2020-08-11T10:27:01-04:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://blog.thegenz.org/media/posts/35/ooop-Sebastian-Maniac-Sanchez.jpg" alt="Black Lives Matter Campaign, Confederate Flag" />
                    This took a long time to write. I wanted this article to be as unbiased as possible and to appropriately and correctly explain and represent the views of the groups involved in the recent events. “On Memorial Day, the police in Minneapolis killed George Floyd,&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <img src="https://blog.thegenz.org/media/posts/35/ooop-Sebastian-Maniac-Sanchez.jpg" alt="Black Lives Matter Campaign, Confederate Flag" />
                <p class="msg msg--highlight  align-center msg--info"><em><strong>This took a long time to write. I wanted this article to be as unbiased as possible and to appropriately and correctly explain and represent the views of the groups involved in the recent events.</strong></em></p>
<p> </p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">“On Memorial Day, the police in Minneapolis killed George Floyd, a 46-year-old black man.” writes the New York Times. “The killing has...prompted renewed calls to address brutality, racial disparities and impunity in American policing....”. But the story doesn’t begin there. And it certainly doesn’t end there either.  Calls for social and political change have prompted a push for reform and overhaul of law enforcement.  However, it is impossible to discuss proper reform of policing and law enforcement in the United States as a whole without properly discussing the prominent issues surrounding the discussion. Some believe that the response from activist groups such as Black Lives Matter and their ever-increasing following are disproportionate to recent events. Others believe that prominent supporters of the Black Lives Matter movement aren’t going far enough. But where does all this tension come from? And how will all this affect us in the future?</span></p>
<p class="msg msg--highlight  align-center"><strong><em>What is Systemic Racism?</em></strong></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The United States has had a long and terrible history with racism and racial inequality. In his book, “Racist America: Roots, Current Realities, and Future Reparations” sociologist Joe Feagin states that systemic racism is a popular way of explaining, within the social sciences and humanities, the significance of race and racism both historically and in today's world. Feagin claims that the United States was founded in racism since the Constitution classified black people as the property of whites. Feagin illustrates that the legal recognition of racialized slavery is a cornerstone of a racist social system in which resources and rights were and are unjustly given to white people and unjustly denied to people of color. In summation, the theory of systemic racism accounts for individual, institutional, and structural forms of racism.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">  </span></p>
<p class="align-center msg msg--highlight "><em><strong>The History of Black Lives Matter and The Civil Rights Movement </strong></em></p>
<p> </p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Today, Black Lives Matter is a phrase that no longer simply refers to the activist organization, but is used to refer to the greater civil rights movement as a whole. Because of recent events, people conjoin the two as simply “The Black Lives Matter Movement”.  However, it is also important to consider that Black Lives Matter (the organization) and the greater Civil Rights movement have separate histories. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The Civil Rights Movement began in the 1940s after the World War II, with the National Association for the Advancement of Colored People (NAACP) began by fighting against segregation, discrimination in public recreational facilities, and restrictive covenants in transportation and housing. In 1954, the US Supreme Court made a historic ruling, outlawing segregation in the public school system. This caused backlash from racist groups of white Southern citizens, who used economic pressure, legal maneuvers and violence to strike against the Civil Rights Movement. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">It would be impossible to discuss the Civil Rights Movement without mentioning Martin Luther King Jr… He organized the 1955-1956 bus boycott in Montgomery, Alabama. It was a peaceful protest brought on by Rosa Parks’ arrest after she refused to give up her seat to a white passenger on a segregated bus. In 1956, the Supreme Court ruled segregation of public transport unconstitutional. King would later go on to leave several successful sit-ins and marches in Birmingham, Alabama, and Washington, D.C. He won the Nobel Peace Prize in 1964 at the age of 35 and gave all his prize money to the Civil Rights Movement. The activist Malcolm X founded the Organization of Afro-American Unity in the early 1960s, pushing a less than peaceful message of  Black Power. He was assassinated in 1965. Just three years later, Martin Luther King Jr. would die in the same way. Even after their deaths, their message continues to resonate with people around the world, and this inspired many to form their own organizations to fight injustice wherever it may occur. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The Black Lives Matter Foundation was formed by Alicia Garza, Patrisse Cullors, and Opal Tometi in response to the killing of 17-year old Trayvon Martin. According to the organization’s website, their mission is to “eradicate white supremacy and build local power to intervene in violence inflicted on Black communities by the state and vigilantes.” Black Lives Matter also actively advocates for Black innovation and pushes for greater amounts of Black representation in politics and culture. Their focus also includes women and a portion of the LGBTQ+ community, who may not have organizations available to represent them. The Black Lives Matter Foundation does not have a central structure of a hierarchy and instead works through local chapters with individual leadership. The organizations regularly organize protests to speak out against issues such as  inequality, racial profiling, police brutality, and the killing of blacks. It is also important to note that Black Lives Matter activists tend to fall on the more radical side of social change. For example, One of Black Lives Matter’s staple chants is “no justice, no peace”, and after the acquittal and total exoneration of police officer Darren Wilson, 300 Black Lives Matter activists were arrested after protests turned violent and multiple fires broke out in the city of  Ferguson, Missouri. In 2015, A radio host that was affiliated with Black Lives Matter agreed with an anonymous caller suggesting that black people should murder whites people, quoting that they should “hang them from a tree, take pictures of it and send it to mother f*ckers.” In November 2015, Black Lives Matter members at the University of Missouri demanded a “blacks only healing space” where white “allies” and sympathizers of their cause were kicked out. This form of segregation was  in response to perceived “racial injustices” and “white privilege” at the college. In 2016, at a Black Lives Matter Protest in Portland, Oregon protesters began advocating the killing of cops, quoting “You pull out your pistol and you bust them”. In response to the death of Eric Garner at the hands of Daniel Pantaleo, a New York City Police Officer,  Black Lives Matter protesters chanted “What do we want? Dead cops. When do we want them? Now!”. In July 2016, members of Black Lives Matter refused to sell a white supporter a Black Lives Matter because the t-shirts were reserved for blacks only. Despite these moments of controversy, Black Lives Matter still claims that its overall mission has not changed, a claim which is supported by their success in spreading awareness about the issues that black people face. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">On May 25, 2020, 46-year-old George Floyd, a black man, was killed by  Minneapolis police officer Derek Chauvin, who pressed his knee into the neck of the complacent and handcuffed George Floyd, killing him, but not before Floyd cried out several times that he was unable to breathe. The tragedy resulted in several protests breaking out across the world. While the majority of the protests were peaceful, many turned into riots, causing violence, arson, and widespread looting. As a response, US cities implemented curfews, and certain cities even called in the National Guard. Of course, these riots are not without casualty. On June 2, a Las Vegas police officer was shot. On the same day, a 77-year-old retired St. Louis police captain was killed by looters at a pawn shop. In Indianapolis, 2 people were killed during the riots, one of which was former Indiana University lineman Chris Beaty.  A 21-year-old man died in Detroit after shooting began during a riot.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Overall, these events have provoked multiple instances of protests and calls for action all over the world. The Black Lives Matter Foundation has taken this opportunity to pursue a new goal, which is a nation-wide defunding of the police. </span></p>
<p> </p>
<p><em><span style="font-weight: 400;">But what exactly does it mean to ‘“defund the police?"</span></em></p>
<p> </p>
<p class="msg msg--highlight align-center"><strong><em>Defund the Police?</em></strong></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">To begin with, there are many misconceptions about the widespread call to “Defund the Police”. Some believe that it calls for total removal of the police force in certain cities and districts. Politicians such as Alexandra Ocasio Cortez have explained that ”Defund the Police” only entails the shifting of funding away from police and instead investing it in poorer communities and towns who were victims of racist practices in the past (more on that later). “Defund the police” may be the most popular solution to police brutality, but it certainly isn't the only one. Less radical political groups and figures have shown support for increased police training and harsher punishments for police officers who violate police code. Doing so would result in increased accountability and awareness about police misconduct on the line of duty. Rep. Jim Clyburn, Democrat  from South Carolina explained that despite calls defunding the police, it would not happen. Instead, he called on his fellow members of Congress to work with him on a “reimagining” of the police system. “I would simply say, as I have always said, nobody is going to defund the police,” Clyburn said on CNN’s “State of the Union.” “We can restructure the police forces, restructure, reimagine policing,” Clyburn said. “That is what we are going to do. The fact of the matter is, the police have a role to play. What we have got to do is make sure that their role is one that meets the times, one that responds to these communities that they operate in.” Clybrun’s words are in line with what the rest of Congress is planning to do, which is reforming police without defunding it. That being said, just why is “Defund the Police” so hotly debated?</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The issue at hand is that police represent such an integral part of society. The responsibilities of the average police officer go far beyond catching criminals. When someone suggests defunding them, it’s easy to assume that the police will become less capable of fulfilling their responsibilities. Defunding the police is not a simple matter and requires careful planning and implementation, that when done correctly could result in impactful support and social change for people who were victims of institutionalized racism. However, every city in the United States is different, and each local government handles its budget differently. People who support the Black Lives Matter movement tend to advocate for defunding the police, but do not consider the fact that not all police departments are “overfunded” and that all poorer neighborhoods who may need financial support are the direct result of institutionalized racism. Lastly, it can not be overstated that not all cops contribute to police brutality. Many cops have stood in solidarity with the Black Lives Matter movement, giving support to the calls for reform. Despite all this, there are still those who deny that radical change demanded organizations like the Black Lives Matter Foundation is needed. </span></p>
<p class="msg msg--highlight  align-center"><strong><em>All Lives Matter</em></strong></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">While the Black Lives Matter Foundation was created with a specific goal in mind as an activist organization, the same cannot be said for  #AllLivesMatter. The hashtag began appearing as soon as the popularity of Black Lives Matter began to skyrocket in response to the death of George Floyd. It was used as a sort of response to people spreading #BlackLivesMatter all over the internet. #AllLivesMatter stems from a misconception- that the statement ‘Black Lives Matter’ means that ONLY black lives matter. When in reality, that is not what the statement entails. The statement is meant to highlight the injustice and mistreatment faced by black people throughout history and campaign for social and political change that will help put an end to racism once and for all.</span></p>
<p class="msg msg--highlight  align-center"><strong><em>Social Media and Activism</em></strong></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">A positive side of the recent events is that many celebrities, politicians, and ordinary people young and old alike have taken to social media as a method of activism. Thanks to the rise of the internet, it is now easier than ever to spread the word about petitions and rallies to foment change in our communities. With silence being frowned upon by all sides, calls for people to express their views are louder than ever, resulting in large instances of messages being shared and debated online. However, the question still remains as to whether these messages plastered all over social media can be considered activism. Former President Barack Obama spoke about social media and activism, saying “there is this sense that 'the way of me making change is to be as judgmental as possible about other people and that's enough.... That's not activism. That's not bringing about change. If all you're doing is casting stones, you're probably not going to get that far. That's easy to do.”</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Anyone with an Instagram account can post a five-second story with the hashtag: </span><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">BlackLivesMatter</span></i><span style="font-weight: 400;">. But how many have gone out of their way to organize a protest, or a letter writing campaign? Ever since the rise of social media, the way that our society deals with current events has changed. Apps like Twitter and YouTube have ‘trending’ sections. Much of what people see and interact with has to do with whether it is trending. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">That being said, social media is still a potent method of spreading awareness about a topic. Controversy is one of the most common ways that something can go viral, especially considering the heated political climate of the United States. </span></p>
<p class="msg msg--highlight  align-center"><strong><em>The Politics of  Racism</em></strong></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Though many would argue that the issues raised by Black Lives Matter and other such institutions do not necessarily need to be political and should instead be regarded as societal, it is also important to consider that much of the changes demanded by organizations like Black Lives Matter and Antifa are analogous with that of political change, and require political support to be turned into law. The most important discrepancy occurs when considering the issues on the racism of the past, and how it may still have an impact today. Many conservatives argue that systemic racism is not an issue. They use statistics to show that police are more likely to shoot white people than black people and that police are also less likely to shoot unarmed black suspects than unarmed suspects.  According to American Free Press’s Peter Papaherakles, “For every black killed by a white police officer in the U.S. every year, there are about 71 blacks killed by other blacks.” This data was backed up by FBI data from 2007-2012 as well as the </span><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">Wall Street Journal</span></i><span style="font-weight: 400;">. Many attribute the leftist claims about systemic racism to the practice of “redlining”. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Redlining is a process in which institutions such as banks will refuse to offer mortgages or offer worse rates to customers in certain predetermined neighborhoods selected on the basis of their racial and ethnic composition. This is clearly an example of institutionalized racism in the United States. However, this practice was outlawed in 1968. Despite this, some argue that black people today still feel the effects of Redlining, pointing to the lack of government resources and support in order to make up for the utter lack of basic health and services like banking, healthcare, transportation and job opportunities. Conservatives address these claims by saying that government vouchers exist to help those in need, while liberals insist on a more widespread solution, calling for the government to spend more on neighborhoods that may have been affected by red-lining. Such arguments can be traced back to the differences between party platforms concerning the role of government as a whole. Many hoped that the United States would pull together to put an end to the numerous crises that the country is facing, but if anything, we are more divided than ever. </span></p>
<p class="align-center msg msg--highlight "><em><strong>The Future: What’s Next for America</strong></em></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">This is a difficult time for all of us. All around the world, the loss of stability, security, and human life, seems to affect every single community. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Everyone wants to return to their normal lifestyle, but analysts assure us that things won’t ever be the same. What exactly do they mean?</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">While this is  a time of great instability, it is also a time in need of great reform. It is easy to see that we are far from the “status quo”, but we must come to terms with the fact that the “status quo” is at least partially, responsible for our dire situation. Things cannot go back to the way they were. The Constitution of the United States was written as a living document for a reason. It was Abraham Lincoln who said “A house divided against itself cannot stand.” Now more than ever, that is true. If we continue to politicize every single issue and become outraged at everything we disagree with, our nation will continue to be divided. We can attain a prosperous future only through cooperation and compromise. For this reason, I urge that we forget our party affiliations, that for just a moment, we forget our rage and our hate, that for just a moment we can negotiate and find a solution that will work for us. We must stop seeing what makes us different and start looking for solutions, because this is more than a fight against injustice or a pandemic. This is a fight for America, and if we lose, we have only ourselves to blame.</span></p>
<hr>
<p class="align-center"><em><span style="font-weight: 400;">Citations</span></em></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Bazelon, Emily. “Police Reform Is Necessary. But How Do We Do It?” The New York Times, The New York Times, 13 June 2020, </span><a href="http://www.nytimes.com/interactive/2020/06/13/magazine/police-reform.html"><span style="font-weight: 400;">www.nytimes.com/interactive/2020/06/13/magazine/police-reform.html</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;">.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Mitchell, Alissa Zhu and Justin. “They Love the Rebel Flag and Are Protesting at Ole Miss. Who Is Confederate 901?” Ledger, Mississippi Clarion Ledger, 19 Feb. 2019, </span><a href="http://www.clarionledger.com/story/news/2019/02/19/who-confederate-901-pro-confederate-groups-protest-ole-miss-rebel-flag-hiwaymen/2919957002/"><span style="font-weight: 400;">www.clarionledger.com/story/news/2019/02/19/who-confederate-901-pro-confederate-groups-protest-ole-miss-rebel-flag-hiwaymen/2919957002/</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;">.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Nicki Lisa Cole, Ph.D. “Understanding Systemic Racism.” ThoughtCo, </span><a href="http://www.thoughtco.com/systemic-racism-3026565"><span style="font-weight: 400;">www.thoughtco.com/systemic-racism-3026565</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;">.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Kershner, Ellen. “What Is The Black Lives Matter Movement?” WorldAtlas, WorldAtlas, 4 June 2020, </span><a href="http://www.worldatlas.com/articles/what-is-the-black-lives-matter-movement.html"><span style="font-weight: 400;">www.worldatlas.com/articles/what-is-the-black-lives-matter-movement.html</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;">.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">O'Reilly, Andrew. “Clyburn Says 'Nobody Is Going to Defund the Police,' Calls for 'Reimagining' of Law Enforcement.” Fox News, FOX News Network, 14 June 2020, </span><a href="http://www.foxnews.com/politics/clyburn-nobody-defund-police-george-floyd"><span style="font-weight: 400;">www.foxnews.com/politics/clyburn-nobody-defund-police-george-floyd</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;">.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Bandler, Aaron. “7 Statistics That Show That 'Systemic Racism' Doesn't Exist In Policing.” The Daily Wire, The Daily Wire, 11 July 2016, </span><a href="http://www.dailywire.com/news/7-statistics-show-systemic-racism-doesnt-exist-aaron-bandler"><span style="font-weight: 400;">www.dailywire.com/news/7-statistics-show-systemic-racism-doesnt-exist-aaron-bandler</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;">.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Prestigiacomo, Amanda. “5 Things You Need To Know About Black Lives Matter.” The Daily Wire, The Daily Wire, 11 July 2016, </span><a href="http://www.dailywire.com/news/5-things-you-need-know-about-black-lives-matter-amanda-prestigiacomo"><span style="font-weight: 400;">www.dailywire.com/news/5-things-you-need-know-about-black-lives-matter-amanda-prestigiacomo</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;">.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">“324,000 U.S. Blacks Killed by Blacks In Only 35 Years.” American Free Press, americanfreepress.net/in-just-35-years-232000-u-s-blacks-killed-by-other-blacks/.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Lockwood, Beatrix. “The US Government Used These Maps to Keep Neighborhoods Segregated.” ThoughtCo, </span><a href="http://www.thoughtco.com/redlining-definition-4157858"><span style="font-weight: 400;">www.thoughtco.com/redlining-definition-4157858</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;">.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Stuart, Tessa. “A Practical Guide to Defunding the Police.” Rolling Stone, Rolling Stone, 10 June 2020, </span><a href="http://www.rollingstone.com/politics/politics-news/defund-the-police-1007254/"><span style="font-weight: 400;">www.rollingstone.com/politics/politics-news/defund-the-police-1007254/</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;">.</span></p>
<p><br><br></p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>The Importance of a Bubble</title>
        <author>
            <name>Ishan Vepa</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://blog.thegenz.org/the-importance-of-a-bubble.html"/>
        <id>https://blog.thegenz.org/the-importance-of-a-bubble.html</id>
            <category term="#sportsnow"/>
            <category term="#sports"/>
            <category term="#global"/>
            <category term="#covid19"/>
            <category term="#coronavirus"/>

        <updated>2020-08-11T10:27:01-04:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://blog.thegenz.org/media/posts/34/Web-Sports-COVID-19.jpg" alt="" />
                    Sports are beginning to make a comeback. The way they are doing it differs by sport, but is a bubble necessary? After the coronavirus forced many sports to shut down, they are now beginning to start back up. The NBA is resuming its season with&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <img src="https://blog.thegenz.org/media/posts/34/Web-Sports-COVID-19.jpg" alt="" />
                <p class="msg msg--highlight  align-center"><strong><i>Sports are beginning to make a comeback. The way they are doing it differs by sport, but is a bubble necessary?</i></strong></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">After the coronavirus forced many sports to shut down, they are now beginning to start back up. The NBA is resuming its season with a bubble at the Walt Disney World Complex in Orlando, Florida. Twenty two out of thirty total teams have been invited to play “seeding” games in order to determine playoff standings. Then, the NBA postseason will begin. The NBA is very determined to keep the integrity of the bubble. Players and staff are constantly tested for covid-19 and are required to wear masks. Anyone entering the bubble must quarantine themselves before joining their team, and anyone leaving the bubble must let the NBA know. Since NBA teams have been arriving to the bubble in early July, the integrity of the bubble has kept up, and there have been no reported cases. Additionally, other leagues, such as the NWSL, MLS, and the WNBA, all have returned by instituting a bubble. In all of these leagues, there was not a single reported case of covid-19 after the initial quarantine stage. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The MLB has also begun their season. They too have instituted new rules to keep players and staff safe, such as shortening the season, playing games without fans, testing personnel, and even banning spitting on the field. However, unlike the NBA, they are playing without a bubble. Teams still have to travel back and forth, and players do not have to be in isolation. Perhaps due to the lack of a bubble, there was a major coronavirus outbreak. Less than a week into the MLB season, seventeen people on the Miami Marlins tested positive for coronavirus. For now, the next six games for the Marlins have been canceled, and there is a sense of uncertainty of whether the Marlins’s season, or even the league’s season, will have to be canceled. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Two major sports have yet to begin their season, football and hockey. The NHL is planning to restart its season with two bubble cities, one in Edmonton and another in Toronto. On the other hand, the NFL plans to begin its season with no bubble in place. The recent outbreak in the MLB, as well as the close physical contact between players that football entails, many are worried about the NFL season. Many different leagues have shown that a bubble works, while the MLB showed why a bubble is necessary. As sports look to continue during a pandemic, a bubble seems to be the only way to do it safely.</span></p>
<hr>
<p class="align-center"><em>Citations</em></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Colin Ward-Henninger  &amp; . “NBA Disney World Rules: Details of How the Bubble Will Work as League Plans to Resume Play in Orlando.” </span><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">CBSSports.com</span></i><span style="font-weight: 400;">, 17 July 2020, www.cbssports.com/nba/news/nba-disney-world-rules-details-of-how-the-bubble-will-work-as-league-plans-to-resume-play-in-orlando/.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Macaya, Melissa, et al. “Here's How MLB Will Conduct Its Upcoming Season.” </span><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">CNN</span></i><span style="font-weight: 400;">, Cable News Network, 30 June 2020, www.cnn.com/world/live-news/coronavirus-pandemic-06-29-20-intl/h_4b0a40baa65fcec05a2527769149a0cd.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Radnofsky, Louise, et al. “The Sports Bubbles Are Working, So Far.” </span><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">The Wall Street Journal</span></i><span style="font-weight: 400;">, Dow Jones &amp; Company, 23 July 2020, www.wsj.com/articles/the-sports-bubbles-are-working-so-far-11595502000.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Sanchez, Ray, and David Close. “Miami Marlins Coronavirus Outbreak Grows with Four More Players Testing Positive.” </span><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">CNN</span></i><span style="font-weight: 400;">, Cable News Network, 28 July 2020, www.cnn.com/2020/07/28/us/mlb-miami-marlins-coronavirus-spt-trnd/index.html.</span></p>
<p> </p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>One Way to Protect Ourselves from COVID-19</title>
        <author>
            <name>Ishan Vepa</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://blog.thegenz.org/one-way-to-protect-ourselves-from-covid-19.html"/>
        <id>https://blog.thegenz.org/one-way-to-protect-ourselves-from-covid-19.html</id>
            <category term="#socialdistancing"/>
            <category term="#healthcare"/>
            <category term="#health"/>
            <category term="#covid19"/>
            <category term="#coronavirus"/>

        <updated>2020-08-11T10:27:01-04:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://blog.thegenz.org/media/posts/33/mask_cover.jpg" alt="A standard mask." />
                    In this time where the number of COVID-19 cases are growing at an exponential rate we must find ways to protect ourselves so that we don’t get sick and in turn make everyone around us sick. One of the best ways to do that right&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <img src="https://blog.thegenz.org/media/posts/33/mask_cover.jpg" alt="A standard mask." />
                <p class="msg msg--highlight "><em><strong>In this time where the number of COVID-19 cases are growing at an exponential rate we must find ways to protect ourselves so that we don’t get sick and in turn make everyone around us sick. One of the best ways to do that right now is using a mask or face shield. </strong></em></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Face masks are essential as not only do they protect you from the virus, they also help protect others by reducing exposure to saliva and other respiratory secretions released by the mask wearer. Masks basically kill two birds with one stone as not only are you protected, but so are others around you. As the Mayo Clinic states, masks function by “protecting the wearer’s nose and mouth from contact with droplets, splashes and sprays that may contain germs.” Additionally they filter out large particles in the air further keeping the user protected from the virus. As outlined by the Mayo Clinic, a few pointers for putting on and taking of your maks are:</span></p>
<ul>
<li style="font-weight: 400;"><span style="font-weight: 400;">Placing your mask around both your mouth and nose. If even one of them is exposed then you are at risk of contracting the virus.</span></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400;"><span style="font-weight: 400;">Not touching your mask while you are wearing it.</span></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400;"><span style="font-weight: 400;">If you touch your mask, wash or sanitize your hands immediately.</span></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400;"><span style="font-weight: 400;">Washing your hands immediately after taking off your mask.</span></li>
</ul>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">If one simply follows all of these guidelines then they can significantly reduce their chances of getting infected. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">According to the Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America (PNAS), masks significantly reduce the spread of the virus and that other countermeasures such as social distancing are not nearly as effective as masks are. A study by PNAS showed that simply wearing face masks prevented over 78,000 infections in Italy between April 6 and May 9 and over 66,000 infections in New York City between April 17 and May 9. As the statistics show, wearing a mask can drastically decrease the rising number of cases with little to no effort on our part. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">While many states have taken the initiative and made masks mandatory, I believe that all states should implement this to make sure that the number of cases can finally start going back down again. No one is completely immune to the virus and to prevent any more casualties from occurring we must prevent the virus from spreading any further. Above all we must learn to have patience in these troubling times. If we had been a little more patient then the number of cases wouldn’t be rising at such a fast rate again. I get that it can be annoying to be stuck at home for so many months but it will ensure that we are not stuck at home longer than we need too. After all, the faster people start following all the precautions, the faster the number of cases will go down, and eventually leading the country to reopen faster.</span></p>
<hr>
<p class="align-center"><em><span style="font-weight: 400;">Citations</span></em></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">“Can Face Masks Protect against the Coronavirus?” </span><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">Mayo Clinic</span></i><span style="font-weight: 400;">, Mayo Foundation for Medical Education and Research, 17 July 2020, www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/coronavirus/in-depth/coronavirus-mask/art-20485449.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Kim, Allen, et al. “These Are the States Requiring People to Wear Masks When out in Public.” </span><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">CNN</span></i><span style="font-weight: 400;">, Cable News Network, 17 July 2020, www.cnn.com/2020/06/19/us/states-face-mask-coronavirus-trnd/index.html.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Kim, Allen. “Best Way to Reduce Coronavirus Transmission Is by Wearing a Face Mask, Study Finds.” </span><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">CNN</span></i><span style="font-weight: 400;">, Cable News Network, 12 June 2020, www.cnn.com/2020/06/12/health/coronavirus-mask-wellness-trnd/index.html.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Zhang, Renyi, et al. “Identifying Airborne Transmission as the Dominant Route for the Spread of COVID-19.” </span><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">PNAS</span></i><span style="font-weight: 400;">, National Academy of Sciences, 30 June 2020, www.pnas.org/content/117/26/14857.</span></p>
<p> </p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Why Do Some People Not Believe In Global Warming?</title>
        <author>
            <name>Ishan Vepa</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://blog.thegenz.org/why-do-some-people-not-believe-in-global-warming.html"/>
        <id>https://blog.thegenz.org/why-do-some-people-not-believe-in-global-warming.html</id>
            <category term="#science"/>
            <category term="#global"/>
            <category term="#environment"/>
            <category term="#energy"/>
            <category term="#climatechange"/>
            <category term="#climate"/>

        <updated>2020-08-11T10:27:01-04:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://blog.thegenz.org/media/posts/32/pexels-valdemaras-d-1670845.jpg" alt="Polar icecaps melting due to climate change." />
                    What is Global Warming? The World has experienced colossal changes in the last century. One of the biggest changes is global warming. The basic definition of global warming is that in the last 50 years years, the average global temperature has been increasing rapidly. This&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <img src="https://blog.thegenz.org/media/posts/32/pexels-valdemaras-d-1670845.jpg" alt="Polar icecaps melting due to climate change." />
                <p class="align-left"><strong>What is Global Warming?</strong></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The World has experienced colossal changes in the last century. One of the biggest changes is global warming. The basic definition of global warming is that in the last 50 years years, the average global temperature has been increasing rapidly. This is mainly due to the burning of fossil fuels and deforestation. Yes, the very thing that is found in 96% of the items we used regularly is the main cause of global warming. Deforestation is also another main cause of global warming. Trees play an important role in regulating the amount of carbon dioxide, a common greenhouse gas, present in the air. The Amazon rainforest is the most threatened forest in the world. The WWF estimates that 27% of the amazon biome would be without trees by 2030 due to deforestation.</span></p>
<p class="align-left"><strong>Why is it important?</strong></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">One of the biggest problems that are caused by global warming is the melting of glaciers. The world has seen an increase in sea levels due to this. The evidence for this is everywhere. For example, the Glacier National Park in Montana had 150 glaciers in 1910 but now the number has decreased to 30. If we let the glaciers melt at the rate they are right now, the consequences would be devastating. It is estimated that if all the glaciers in the world melt, the sea level would rise by 70 meters or higher. The melting of glaciers poses a great threat to all the coastal cities like New York, Tokyo, Shanghai, Los Angeles etc. Another problem caused by global warming is the decrease of ozone levels in the atmosphere. The ozone layer protects us from the harmful UV rays from the sun. Ozone depletion would result in variou skin related diseases and also cancer. </span></p>
<p class="msg msg--highlight  align-center"><em><strong>Why do some people not believe in global warming?</strong></em></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">But of course, there are still a lot of people who do not believe in global warming despite having seen the evidence presented by scientists around the world. So why do some people not believe in global warming? I think that it boils down to people vs. science. People have been denying science for centuries, religion being one of the main reasons. Flat-Earthers, anti-vaxxers, anti-NASA etc. are all products of people vs. science. Another reason why people do not believe in global warming is that they simply can't feel the temperature increase for themselves as global warming is not an immediate change. It is a change that occurs and is occurring over a long period of time. People have to understand that these claims are being made by professional scientists who have spent most of their lives studying about the environment. They have to put more trust into these people than they do in conspiracy theories. Countries should start converting to renewable sources of energy. Practicing the 3 R’s (Reduce, Reuse, Recycle) also helps to battle climate change.</span></p>
<hr>
<p class="align-center"><em><span style="font-weight: 400;">Citations</span></em></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">MacMillan , Amanda. </span><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">Global Warming 101</span></i><span style="font-weight: 400;">, 2016, </span><a href="http://www.nrdc.org/stories/global-warming-101#warming"><span style="font-weight: 400;">www.nrdc.org/stories/global-warming-101#warming</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;">.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">“Importance of Fossil Fuels.” </span><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">International Association of Geophysical Contractors | Houston, TX, 77008</span></i><span style="font-weight: 400;">, </span><a href="http://www.iagc.org/importance-of-fossil-fuels.html#:~:text=Fossil%20fuels%20are%20found%20in,gas%20used%20to%20generate%20electricity"><span style="font-weight: 400;">www.iagc.org/importance-of-fossil-fuels.html#:~:text=Fossil%20fuels%20are%20found%20in,gas%20used%20to%20generate%20electricity</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;">.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Glick, Daniel. </span><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">Global Climate Change, Melting Glaciers</span></i><span style="font-weight: 400;">, 18 Jan. 2017, </span><a href="http://www.nationalgeographic.com/environment/global-warming/big-thaw/#:~:text=When%20temperatures%20rise%20and%20ice,warms%20and%20expands%20in%20volume"><span style="font-weight: 400;">www.nationalgeographic.com/environment/global-warming/big-thaw/#:~:text=When%20temperatures%20rise%20and%20ice,warms%20and%20expands%20in%20volume</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;">.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">“Will the World Ever Be All under Water?: AMNH.” </span><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">American Museum of Natural History</span></i><span style="font-weight: 400;">, </span><a href="http://www.amnh.org/explore/ology/earth/ask-a-scientist-about-our-environment/will-the-world-ever-be-all-under-water#:~:text=If%20all%20the%20ice%20covering,such%20as%20Denver%2C%20would%20survive."><span style="font-weight: 400;">www.amnh.org/explore/ology/earth/ask-a-scientist-about-our-environment/will-the-world-ever-be-all-under-water#:~:text=If%20all%20the%20ice%20covering,such%20as%20Denver%2C%20would%20survive.</span></a></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">“Deforestation in the Amazon.” </span><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">WWF</span></i><span style="font-weight: 400;">, </span><a href="https://wwf.panda.org/our_work/our_focus/forests_practice/deforestation_fronts2/deforestation_in_the_amazon/"><span style="font-weight: 400;">wwf.panda.org/our_work/our_focus/forests_practice/deforestation_fronts2/deforestation_in_the_amazon/#:~:text=Amazon%20is%20the%20biggest%20deforestation,current%20rate%20of%20deforestation%20continues.</span></a></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Butler, Rhett A. “Amazon Destruction.” </span><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">Mongabay</span></i><span style="font-weight: 400;">, Mongabay, 4 Feb. 2020, </span><a href="https://rainforests.mongabay.com/amazon/amazon_destruction.html"><span style="font-weight: 400;">rainforests.mongabay.com/amazon/amazon_destruction.html.</span></a></p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Why Do We Procrastinate?</title>
        <author>
            <name>Ishan Vepa</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://blog.thegenz.org/why-do-we-procrastinate.html"/>
        <id>https://blog.thegenz.org/why-do-we-procrastinate.html</id>
            <category term="#youth"/>
            <category term="#society"/>
            <category term="#mentalhealth"/>
            <category term="#education"/>

        <updated>2020-08-11T10:27:01-04:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://blog.thegenz.org/media/posts/31/Procrastination-Article-Picture-Alyson-Torino.jpg" alt="Chalk board with inscription." />
                    According to Psycom, a resource for mental health, nearly 20% of men and women in the US are chronic procrastinators, and that procrastination is an issue humanity has faced for centuries. It is the last thing that we want to do, but somehow it ends&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <img src="https://blog.thegenz.org/media/posts/31/Procrastination-Article-Picture-Alyson-Torino.jpg" alt="Chalk board with inscription." />
                <p><span style="font-weight: 400;">According to Psycom, a resource for mental health, nearly 20% of men and women in the US are chronic procrastinators, and that procrastination is an issue humanity has faced for centuries. It is the last thing that we want to do, but somehow it ends up happening anyways. From a young age, we are taught to manage our time properly in order to complete all of our responsibilities on time, but people can’t control when they procrastinate. We rely on self control and motivation to get tasks done, but it's when those two things aren’t present that procrastination occurs. It is a vicious cycle that is difficult to escape, but the first step in doing so is figuring out the reason behind your procrastination. </span></p>
<p class="align-center msg msg--highlight "><em><strong>Lack of motivation </strong></em><span style="font-weight: 400;"><em>is one possible reason someone may procrastinate.</em> </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">As I stated before, motivation is what drives us to complete a task, so lack thereof would lead to the task not being completed. The cause behind lack of motivation is extrinsic motivation, meaning coming from an outside source. This is common among students in the form of teachers and parents. If the student themself does not want to complete their work, the motivation for them would come from their parents and teachers, which is not enough for them to complete their task.</span></p>
<p class="msg msg--highlight  align-center"><em><strong>Fear of failure and perfectionism </strong></em><span style="font-weight: 400;"><em>is another cause to procrastination.</em> </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">These examples go hand in hand since they are very similar in their root cause, which is a person’s work not being good enough. If someone is afraid of failing, then they will not be driven to complete their work since they don’t want it to be seen as mediocre. Similarly, if someone is a perfectionist, then they will want their work to be flawless. This will either cause the person to never start their task, or to never finish it, since it has to be perfect. </span></p>
<p class="msg msg--highlight  align-center"><em><strong>Negative emotions</strong><span style="font-weight: 400;"> are a large cause of procrastination, such as being overwhelmed or anxious about a task. </span></em></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">One becomes overwhelmed by a task when they think it is much too large, or when multiple smaller tasks pile up. This will cause a person to avoid their tasks and procrastinate them. Anxiety about a task is difficult to overcome because it creates a loop. Once a person becomes anxious about a task, they will avoid it, which will only amplify their anxiety about it, since it is not being completed. </span></p>
<p class="msg msg--highlight  align-center"><em><strong>Optimism</strong></em><span style="font-weight: 400;"><em>, however strange it sounds, contributes to procrastination as well.</em> </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Positive thinking, in terms of procrastination, refers to either the amount of time someone thinks a task will take, or one’s ability to complete it. This will lead them to believe that they won’t need to put much work into the task, which means they will wait to complete it. Because of this, when they actually do the task, it will become stressful when they realize they have not allowed themself enough time to do it well.</span></p>
<p class="msg msg--highlight align-center"><em><strong>Disconnect from the future self</strong><span style="font-weight: 400;">, or temporal disjunction, is another cause of procrastination, and also happens to be mine. </span></em></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">It is when one sees their future self as a completely different person. This leads them to think that the task they have at hand is not their problem, but one for their future self to take care of. It becomes a way for them to deflect their responsibilities onto “someone else” and not worry about completing them. Speaking from personal experience, this ends up being a large problem when the due date for a task comes around and there is little to no work shown for it.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">These are just a few of many causes of procrastination, and once you have identified why you procrastinate, you can then figure out how to stop. Here are some tips to help you get started:</span></p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Just start working. </strong><span style="font-weight: 400;">The hardest part of any task is getting started, and once you get that out of the way, you have a good foundation for quality work.</span></li>
</ul>
<ul>
<li><strong>Break it down. </strong><span style="font-weight: 400;">The larger a task is, the less you will want to do it. Breaking a larger task into smaller ones will be a big help in staying productive.</span></li>
</ul>
<ul>
<li><strong>Put aside possible distractions. </strong><span style="font-weight: 400;">Find yourself a quiet workspace where you can focus on your task. It’s not possible to eliminate every single distraction there may be, but putting away the ones you know will cause a problem will allow you to concentrate.</span></li>
</ul>
<ul>
<li><strong>Stay positive!</strong><span style="font-weight: 400;"> If you approach a task with a negative attitude, your work will not be at its best, and it will be harder for you to focus. If you stay positive while working, it will be much more enjoyable and the quality of your work will be better.</span></li>
</ul>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Procrastination is one of the biggest obstacles preventing us from reaching our full potential. Don’t let yourself be the one to stop you from making the world a better place.</span></p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>The Yemeni Crisis</title>
        <author>
            <name>Ishan Vepa</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://blog.thegenz.org/the-yemeni-crisis.html"/>
        <id>https://blog.thegenz.org/the-yemeni-crisis.html</id>
            <category term="#society"/>
            <category term="#globalconflict"/>
            <category term="#global"/>
            <category term="#environment"/>
            <category term="#crisis"/>
            <category term="#community"/>

        <updated>2020-08-11T10:27:01-04:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://blog.thegenz.org/media/posts/30/yemen_war.jpg" alt="Aftermath of Yemen Conflict" />
                    Yemen is currently caught in the worst humanitarian crisis of the 21st century with 24 million people or 80% of the population in need of humanitarian aid. The issue: The country is going through its second civil war which started in 2015 and over 100,000&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <img src="https://blog.thegenz.org/media/posts/30/yemen_war.jpg" alt="Aftermath of Yemen Conflict" />
                <p class="msg msg--highlight  align-center"><strong><em>Yemen is currently caught in the worst humanitarian crisis of the 21st century with 24 million people or 80% of the population in need of humanitarian aid. </em></strong></p>
<p><strong><i>The issue:</i></strong></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The country is going through its second civil war which started in 2015 and over 100,000 people have been killed by the conflict. The situation only gets worse every day. According to UNICEF, more than half of those in need of humanitarian aid are children and around 2 million children under the age of 5 are malnourished. Civilians are suffering the most due to the lack of essential items. Roads and buildings required for delivering food and water have been destroyed or taken over resulting in the price of food skyrocketing. Most cannot afford enough food for their families and have had to flee their homes to get away from conflict. Houthi rebels who are fighting the government have been accused of confiscating food, water, and other essential items from civilians.</span></p>
<p><em><strong>American involvement in Yemen: </strong></em></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Ever since the start of the war, the United States supported its ally Saudi Arabia who is fighting against Yemeni forces. The U.S has sold over 110 billion in arms to Saudi since 2009. Many have been critical of America’s involvement and claim that the conflict will end if the U.S. pulls out. However, the U.S. continues to show support of Saudi and sells arms to them. Saudi forces use weapons without consideration of civilian lives which the U.S. knows but does nothing. Saudi Arabia targets Yemeni infrastructure as a strategy to cripple Yemen from the inside by causing civil unrest and to weaken enemy forces but the conflict has been stretched for years and thousands of civilian lives have been taken. </span></p>
<p><strong><i>Covid-19 in Yemen:</i></strong></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The coronavirus has made things much worse than it already is in Yemen. Cases are spiking and most don’t have access to affordable healthcare which is crucial to stopping the spread of the virus. Most health workers are not receiving pay and basic sanitation supplies which is putting them at risk of getting the virus. They also get threatened and killed for doing their work causing many to flee in fear. Over 4 million people have been displaced and many of them live in areas with a high population density which further increases the danger of the situation. Many children could not afford school before the virus but now that schools have closed, 7.8 million children do not have access to education. There is a short supply of ventilators and test kits. Many are not aware of the dangers of the virus and its high contagiousness. The situation is getting worse every day and the UN has gone as far as airlifting testing kits to Yemen in hopes of slowing the spread.</span></p>
<p><strong><i>How you can help: </i></strong></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">One of the best ways you can help other than donating is to spread awareness about the issue. Not many people know about this and it doesn’t get much media attention even though millions of people are starving. Spreading awareness about this issue will allow it get more media attention and garner more donors. Another way to help is to sign petitions that demand change. For example, a petition on Change.org already has over 2.7 million signatures. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Here are some useful links to help :</span></p>
<ul>
<li style="font-weight: 400;">
<div class="js-petition-content">
<div class="sm-txt-c mtxxl xs-mtm xs-phs">
<p class="mtl mbxxxl xs-mts xs-mbxs type-break-word petition-title"><a href="https://tinyurl.com/y2olzqqk" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Stop the war and end the famine in Yemen, Change.org</a></p>
</div>
</div>
</li>
<li style="font-weight: 400;"><a href="https://tinyurl.com/yxotc3sg" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Send support to fight medical crisis in Yemin, Islamic Relief USA</a></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400;"><a href="https://tinyurl.com/y2p9ckpj" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Help save children in Yemen, savethechildren.org</a></li>
<li class="align-left" style="font-weight: 400;"><a href="https://tinyurl.com/y3d2gte3" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Donate to help save Yemeni lives, Doctors Without Borders</a></li>
</ul>
<hr>
<p class="align-center"><em>Citations</em></p>
<p>“What's Happening in Yemen? .” <i>BBC News</i>, BBC, 28 Mar. 2918, <a href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/newsround/38317367" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">www.bbc.co.uk/newsround/38317367</a>.</p>
<p>UNICEF. “Yemen Crisis.” <i>UNICEF</i>, 22 July 2020, <a href="http://www.unicef.org/emergencies/yemen-crisis" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">www.unicef.org/emergencies/yemen-crisis</a>.</p>
<p>Bazzi, Mohamad. “America Is Likely Complicit in War Crimes in Yemen. It's Time to Hold the US to Account | Mohamad Bazzi.” <i>The Guardian</i>, Guardian News and Media, 3 Oct. 2019, <a href="http://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/2019/oct/03/yemen-airstrikes-saudi-arabia-mbs-us" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/2019/oct/03/yemen-airstrikes-saudi-arabia-mbs-us</a>.</p>
<p>“Yemen: Displaced at Heightened Covid-19 Risk.” <i>Human Rights Watch</i>, 22 May 2020, <a href="http://www.hrw.org/news/2020/05/22/yemen-displaced-heightened-covid-19-risk" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">www.hrw.org/news/2020/05/22/yemen-displaced-heightened-covid-19-risk</a>.</p>
<p><br><br><br><br><br><br></p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Hedy Lamarr: More Than Just a Pretty Face</title>
        <author>
            <name>Ishan Vepa</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://blog.thegenz.org/hedy-lamarr-more-than-just-a-pretty-face.html"/>
        <id>https://blog.thegenz.org/hedy-lamarr-more-than-just-a-pretty-face.html</id>
            <category term="#womensrights"/>
            <category term="#womeninstem"/>
            <category term="#society"/>
            <category term="#science"/>
            <category term="#inequality"/>
            <category term="#community"/>

        <updated>2020-08-11T10:27:01-04:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://blog.thegenz.org/media/posts/29/Hedy-Lamarr-Science-Abigail-Mullins.jpg" alt="Hedy Lamar working on scientific experimentation." />
                    Can a woman be both smart and beautiful? The obvious answer is well, yes. Of course she can. However, society tends to split women between being smart and beautiful. There are women who are seen as beautiful, and there are women who are smart, although&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <img src="https://blog.thegenz.org/media/posts/29/Hedy-Lamarr-Science-Abigail-Mullins.jpg" alt="Hedy Lamar working on scientific experimentation." />
                <p class="msg msg--highlight align-center"><span style="font-weight: 400;"><strong><em>Can a woman be both smart and beautiful? The obvious answer is well, yes. Of course she can. However, society tends to split women between being smart and beautiful.</em></strong></span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">There are women who are seen as beautiful, and there are women who are smart, although in the past a lot less was seen of the latter. Take Hedy Lamarr. It is a name that evokes old Hollywood and great beauty. She was the most beautiful woman and a famous actress. She was also an inventor. Somehow, history tends to forget this last part.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Lamarr had from a young age had had a love of science, which had been influenced by her father. He talked to her about the inner workings of machines to the point that Lamarr at the age of 5 was able to take apart and reassemble a music box. Guided by her mother, Lamarr took on roles in movies and eventually married a munitions manufacturer, who often had guests over. Lamarr would listen in on their conversations regarding wartimes weapons. In 1937, she left her unhappy marriage with a husband who didn’t see her beyond a pretty doll and eventually ended up in London. Unfortunately, this would not be her first experience with being seen only as pretty.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">In London, she met the co-founder of MGM studios which eventually led to a career in Hollywood. Despite her newfound fame, Lamarr still found time for her inventive mind. In her trailer, she continued working on various projects. Howard Hughes encouraged her inventive mind, and would take her to airplane factories. She even designed airplane wings by taking inspiration from nature. She combined the design of the fastest fish’s fins and the fastest birds’ wings into one set of speedy airplane wings. “Genius” Hughes called her.  Her inventive side, though, was somewhat hidden from the public, and not because she didn’t want people to know.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Lamarr shared her passion of inventing with George Antheil, a pianist. Both were concerned by the looming war and wanted to contribute ideas to help. In order to help torpedoes resist interference from the enemy, they created a frequency-hopping system that prevented the signal from being jammed. The transmitter and receiver would jump frequencies together and the enemy would not be able to intercept the message with the signal constantly moving across frequencies. In August 1942, they received a patent and donated it to the US Navy. However, the US Navy rejected it, saying it was too cumbersome. Unfazed, Lamarr continued to show her support for the war and used her celebrity status to raise money for war bonds. She even became a US citizen in 1953.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">When Hedy Lamarr starred in a new movie, there were headlines raving about how beautiful she was and how greatly she performed. Her new invention? No big headline. Nothing. It is interesting to see what parts of her that society valued. Her beauty, definitely. Her acting, yes. Her scientific side? Nope. It was brushed aside. Why must society pick and choose which parts of people, especially women, to present to the world? Even today actresses are asked about what they wear or their makeup routine. Anything else is irrelevant.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">In the mid 1950s, the Navy did use her and Antheil’s concept on a buoy that was able to detect submarines and even used it during the Cuban Missile Crisis of 1962. With the patent expiring in 1958, neither Lamarr or Antheil ever received any money from their invention.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">As for Lamarr herself, she continued working as an actress until 1958, and even worked as a producer in 2 films. While her great beauty was praised by many, Lamarr did not find her outward appearance as the most important thing. “Any girl can look glamorous. All you have to do is look stupid,” she once said. Lamarr was aware of how society valued her beauty. In the 40s, her profile was most requested by plastic surgery patients. Could the same awe be said of her science side? No. Lamarr was in a way forced to hide that aspect about her because she couldn’t be recognized for being smart. Society only really valued beauty in women anyway. Even if she was smart, that wasn’t really important. It is unfortunate that society was, and still is, like that. Society should realize that beauty isn’t always about looking good. It is also about creativeness, kindness, what we can do for others, and so much more beyond physical attributes. Hedy Lamarr created the frequency-hopping system not for herself, but to help our country win the war.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">As the years went on, Lamarr never really spoke of her inventive nature. Why? Perhaps because she felt she wouldn’t have been taken seriously. After all, the reason she left her first husband was because he never treated her like an equal. It is unfortunate that she felt that she had to conform to society’s ideals and couldn’t share her inventive side. Society’s idea of her was that she was pretty and that was it. Even today women have to deal with society only thinking of them as being pretty or smart, never both. To the public, Hedy Lamarr was only beautiful, and some probably thought that because she was beautiful, she was dumb as well. If she was smart, she would’ve been ugly. Which is completely untrue.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">As time went on, society’s ideas of women lessened a bit. Women could get recognition for their brains even while being pretty. Long lost tapes from the 1990s tapes reveal a different side to Lamarr than the public had originally seen. She talked about her inventions, and said “The brains of people are more interesting than looks, I think.” She was beginning to be comfortable talking about her science side and know that she wouldn’t get ridiculed for it. Finally, in 1997, she began to receive credit for the work she had done. She was the first woman to receive the Invention Convention’s Bulbie Gnass Spirit of Achievement Award, which is the equivalent of an Oscar in the inventing world. The Electronic Frontier Foundation honored her and Antheil with the Pioneer Award. It took 50 years for her and Anthiel’s achievement to be recognized. Why did it have to take so long? Did society simply not want to recognize her efforts? We have to realize that people are more than just what they look like. The things they do, how they treat others are more important factors that define a person. Physical characteristics mean nothing and do not contribute to who a person is overall.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Lamarr passed away in 2000. However, her frequency-hopping system continues to live on. In fact, you most certainly have used it before, maybe even right now. Today, this technology is used in WiFi and Bluetooth communications. In 2014, she and Antheil were posthumously inducted into the Inventor’s Hall of Fame for their work.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">It is interesting how history has chosen what pieces of someone to remember. For Hedy Lamarr, history chose her beauty. Not her work as an inventor, which was ignored for years. It wasn’t until 50 years later after the invention of her and Antheil’s frequency-hopping system were they recognized for their work. Why was it forgotten? Perhaps because society values physical beauty more than anything else, especially concerning women. A woman cannot be both smart and pretty. But Hedy Lamarr defies that role. She was a brilliant inventor and a genius who also happened to look good. Her inventive mind is perhaps the most beautiful part about her.</span></p>
<hr>
<p class="align-center"><em><span style="font-weight: 400;">Citations</span></em></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Brancaccio, David, and Paulina Velasco. “The Story of Hedy Lamarr, the Hollywood Beauty Whose Invention Helped Enable Wi-Fi, GPS and Bluetooth.” </span><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">Marketplace</span></i><span style="font-weight: 400;">, 29 Apr. 2019, </span><a href="http://www.marketplace.org/2017/11/21/inventor-changed-our-world-and-also-happened-be-famous-hollywood-star/"><span style="font-weight: 400;">www.marketplace.org/2017/11/21/inventor-changed-our-world-and-also-happened-be-famous-hollywood-star/</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;">.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Cheslak, Colleen. “Hedy Lamarr.” </span><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">Hedy Lamarr</span></i><span style="font-weight: 400;">, National Women's History Museum, 30 Aug. 2018, </span><a href="http://www.womenshistory.org/students-and-educators/biographies/hedy-lamarr"><span style="font-weight: 400;">www.womenshistory.org/students-and-educators/biographies/hedy-lamarr</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;">.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Desta, Yohana. “How Inventive ‘Genius’ Hedy Lamarr Became a Hollywood Tragedy.” </span><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">Vanity Fair</span></i><span style="font-weight: 400;">, Vanity Fair, 25 May 2017, </span><a href="http://www.vanityfair.com/hollywood/2017/04/hedy-lamarr-documentary-clip"><span style="font-weight: 400;">www.vanityfair.com/hollywood/2017/04/hedy-lamarr-documentary-clip</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;">.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Field, Shivaune. “Hedy Lamarr: The Incredible Mind Behind Secure WiFi, GPS And Bluetooth.” </span><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">Forbes</span></i><span style="font-weight: 400;">, Forbes Magazine, 8 Mar. 2018, </span><a href="http://www.forbes.com/sites/shivaunefield/2018/02/28/hedy-lamarr-the-incredible-mind-behind-secure-wi-fi-gps-bluetooth/#66f66fba41b7"><span style="font-weight: 400;">www.forbes.com/sites/shivaunefield/2018/02/28/hedy-lamarr-the-incredible-mind-behind-secure-wi-fi-gps-bluetooth/#66f66fba41b7</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;">.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">George, Alice. “Thank This World War II-Era Film Star for Your Wi-Fi.” </span><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">Smithsonian.com</span></i><span style="font-weight: 400;">, Smithsonian Institution, 4 Apr. 2019, <a href="http://www.smithsonianmag.com/smithsonian-institution/thank-world-war-ii-era-film-star-your-wi-fi-180971584/">www.smithsonianmag.com/smithsonian-institution/thank-world-war-ii-era-film-star-your-wi-fi-180971584/</a>.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Long, Emily. “HEDY LAMARR, MARCH 2017 LAMP LUMINARY.” </span><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">The Lamp</span></i><span style="font-weight: 400;">, 14 </span><span style="font-weight: 400;">Mar. 2017, <a href="http://www.thelamp.org/hedy-lamarr/">www.thelamp.org/hedy-lamarr/</a>.</span></p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Lowering the Voting Age</title>
        <author>
            <name>Ishan Vepa</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://blog.thegenz.org/lowering-the-voting-age.html"/>
        <id>https://blog.thegenz.org/lowering-the-voting-age.html</id>
            <category term="#vote"/>
            <category term="#society"/>
            <category term="#rights"/>
            <category term="#generations"/>
            <category term="#community"/>

        <updated>2020-08-11T10:27:01-04:00</updated>
            <summary></summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <img src="https://blog.thegenz.org/media/posts/28/1242731F-441C-41B7-8866-A44110881168-Ryan-Shankar.png" alt="Voting rights depiction." />
                
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Voting age is a very controversial topic. History has seen the minimum age for voting change, from 21 to 18 during 1969. When 18 year-olds were being drafted into the military, but could not vote. Now something similar has occurred, with climate change and gun control. Now more than ever, guns are killing more students. In 46 weeks there has been over 45 school shootings killing at least one student. Still gun laws aren’t changing and many believe it's because students, the ones actually being affected by the shootings aren’t represented in politics. People are starting comparing this to when 18-year-olds couldn’t vote for the president that was drafting them into the military. Climate change is a problem that is not going to affect the current generation but the generation born after the 2000’s, so it doesn’t get much attention and priority from current voters. Because of 16 year-olds participation and involvement in these problems, national voting age should be reduced to 16.</span></p>
<p><strong><i>What Are Ages of Current Voters?</i></strong></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Currently the U.S has the lowest voter turnout of any developed nation. This greatly affects the U.S.A and can be seen in their voter demographics, most of the voters in the U.S are age 65 plus white, data provided from the U.S Census. The main problem with this demographic is that they don’t know much about current issues, such as climate change and gun violence because it won’t affect them as much as it affects minorities or people of younger ages. The current issue many have is that. Why should the kids of this generation stand on the side and watch while their future is being destroyed right in front of them, with the world's lack to address climate change? Many teens around the world, especially in the U.S are stepping up and organizing protests and coming together to try to stop this, like the Juliana Plaintiffs and the recent worldwide teen protest about climate change. The only thing is no leaders are listening because they don’t have to worry about teen voters, all they have to do is satisfy the older population who is clearly not worried about climate change. As seen from the recent election of leaders around the world who have been ignoring this issue. But one highly debated topic has been gun control. The countless protests that teens have done trying to stricten gun control laws have seemed to be ineffective. This goes back and relates to the fact that politicians don't have to address teens issues and concerns, because it won't affect their chances of being elected. They are better off not addressing gun control because the people who vote are not as concerned about guns or climate change. This is why U.S.A has to change its voting age, because for a country that boasts about having a democracy, clearly do not as not everyone's issues are being heard and attended to. </span></p>
<p><strong><i>Why Isn’t the Voting Age Being Changed?</i></strong></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;"> People believe that 16 year-olds are not mature enough to vote, or not involved as much as older people. People argue that 16 year-olds don’t care enough about politics. These were the same arguments people used when trying to justify why African Americans shouldn’t and women shouldn’t vote. They said that African Americans and women were not relevant and weren’t as smart as the current voter population, but when you look at it now it seems ridiculous. The same should be done with 16 year-olds, now more than ever. Because with technology they are more exposed current affairs and politics. This can be seen when you look at mock elections and voting events teens are participating more in these elections because they care about current affairs. Ayanna Pressley who presented a bill to lower voting age to the House said </span><span style="font-weight: 400;">“Some have questioned the maturity of our youth. I don’t,” the congresswoman told the House”, she went on to say “A sixteen-year-old in 2019 possesses a wisdom and a maturity that comes from 2019 challenges, hardships, and threats”. The bill she presented did not pass but did get the support of 125 House members. </span><span style="font-weight: 400;">Teen activism is rising, recently there have been many protests against the way the world is being run and this has been proving Pressley’s point of why teens should be allowed to vote. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The national voting age of the United States should be lowered to 16 because it allows a larger voting population of people who are interested in their future. Opening up voting to 16 will allow the country to have more creative solutions and gives the youth a chance to be heard. Many say that lowering the voting age will be unfavorable to the country but they are also the ones who make key decisions in the lives of the younger people and so far their decisions have negatively impacted the youth. The youth can't argue because their voice is not heard and lowering the voting age will allow them to be heard.</span></p>
<hr>
<p class="align-center"><em>Citations</em></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">“ACLU Letter Opposing H.R. 1 (For the People Act of 2019).” </span><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">American Civil Liberties Union</span></i><span style="font-weight: 400;">, https://www.aclu.org/aclu-letter-opposing-hr-1-people-act-2019.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Astor, Maggie. “16-Year-Olds Want a Vote. Fifty Years Ago, So Did 18-Year-Olds.” </span><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">The  New York Times</span></i><span style="font-weight: 400;">, The New York Times, 19 May 2019, https://www.nytimes.com/2019/05/19/us/politics/voting-age.html.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Cilluffo, Anthony, and Richard Fry. “Gen Z, Millennials and Gen X Outvoted Older Generations in 2018 Midterms.” </span><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">Pew Research Center</span></i><span style="font-weight: 400;">, Pew Research Center, 29 May 2019, https://www.pewresearch.org/fact-tank/2019/05/29/gen-z-millennials-and-gen-x-outvoted-older-generations-in-2018-midterms/.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Costly, Andrew. “Race and Voting - Constitutional Rights Foundation.” </span><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">Race and Voting - Constitutional Rights Foundation</span></i><span style="font-weight: 400;">, https://www.crf-usa.org/brown-v-board-50th-anniversary/race-and-voting.html.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">DeSilver, Drew. “U.S. Voter Turnout Trails Most Developed Countries.” </span><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">Pew Research Center</span></i><span style="font-weight: 400;">, Pew Research Center, 21 May 2018, https://www.pewresearch.org/fact-tank/2018/05/21/u-s-voter-turnout-trails-most-developed-countries/.</span></p>
<p><br><br></p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Should Children Play Video Games?</title>
        <author>
            <name>Ishan Vepa</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://blog.thegenz.org/should-children-play-video-games.html"/>
        <id>https://blog.thegenz.org/should-children-play-video-games.html</id>
            <category term="#youth"/>
            <category term="#videogames"/>
            <category term="#mentalhealth"/>

        <updated>2020-08-11T10:27:01-04:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://blog.thegenz.org/media/posts/27/video-game-game-controller-genz-Lauren-Scarpa.jpg" alt="White Xbox and Sony PS4 Controllers on Brown Surface, Video Game." />
                    Should children play video games? “They argue that violent video games may provide a safe outlet for angry feelings. This may actually reduce crime”(Newsela). Many experts claim that video games aren’t proven to lead to violent crimes in the future. They also have many studies&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <img src="https://blog.thegenz.org/media/posts/27/video-game-game-controller-genz-Lauren-Scarpa.jpg" alt="White Xbox and Sony PS4 Controllers on Brown Surface, Video Game." />
                <p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Should children play video games? “They argue that violent video games may provide a safe outlet for angry feelings.  This may actually reduce crime”(Newsela).  Many experts claim that video games aren’t proven to lead to violent crimes in the future.  They also have many studies showing that when video game sales increased the crime rate decreased.  Children should play video games, because they lower crime rates, they do not lead to violent crimes, and they help with their physical and mental health.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">There is no question that video games are proven to lower crime rates. In the article, “Shooters in the Dark”</span><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">, </span></i><span style="font-weight: 400;">“‘We found that higher rates of violent video game sales related to a decrease in crimes, and especially violent crimes’, said Dr. Ward, whose co-authors were A. Scott Cunningham of Baylor University and Benjamin Engelstätter of the Center for European Economic Research in Mannheim, Germany”(Benedict).  This shows that when more video games are sold, there is a decrease in crimes. But, is there much of a decrease in crimes?  Yes, actually.  One of the most significant pieces of evidence that supports this is,  “Issue Overview: Do Video Games Cause Violence?” by Newsela, “From 1994 to 2014, game sales increased by more than 200 percent.  During those same ten years, murders by youth acting on their own fell 76 percent and violent crime rates dropped 37 percent.” When the video games sales increased by 200 percent the violent crime rates dropped.</span><span style="font-weight: 400;">  </span><span style="font-weight: 400;">This further displays the fact that more video games sales leads to significantly less murders and violent crimes, especially on the youth’s behalf.  If violent video games lead to violent crimes, why exactly would crime rates lower, as more people bought video games?</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">It seems that video games are not proven to lead to violent crimes.  According to “Issue Overview: Do Video Games Cause Violence?”</span> <span style="font-weight: 400;">by Newsela, “Courts have said there is no clear link between video game violence and real-world violence.”  This reveals that even courts have found that video game violence is not linked to real world violence.  Another relevant piece of evidence that supports that video games do not lead to violent crimes is from the article “Do Games Like 'Grand Theft Auto V' Cause Real-World Violence?”</span> <span style="font-weight: 400;">by Erik Kain, “If there is a truly direct, causal link between games like Grand Theft Auto V and violent shootings, we will soon have 18 to 20 million killers on our hands, not to mention the countless millions who have been playing violent video games for years”.  This implies that there is no possible way that video games can lead to violence, because then we would have countless more criminals and violent people in the world.  The world is violent, but not violent enough to be because of video games.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">In general, video games help with the physical and mental health of children.  For instance, the article, “Game on! New Study Says Video Games Could Be Good for You?”</span> <span style="font-weight: 400;">by Newsela, states, “Gaming might burn more calories than just watching TV.  She believes it also may be that kids holding a controller are not as likely to pick a snack or a soda.”  This demonstrates that children who play video games have more physical health benefits than children who don’t.  When children are playing video games they are burning off more calories than just sitting in front of the TV, and these children are also less likely to eat a fattening snack or drink a soda full of sugar, because they won’t be eating for “fun”.  Video games do not only help children with their health physically, but also mentally.  As stated earlier, children who play video games are able to release some of their anger in a safe environment, which ultimately helps their mental health, plus video games also help children with decision making.  In the same article it also talks about this positive mental health factor.  It says that video games are an important tool for teaching children to make the right decision.  This affirms that video games can also help with the decision making part of mental health.  All in all, video games help children physically and mentally in more than one area.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Although some people believe that video games lead to more violence and violent crimes, this is not the case.  According to “Shooters in the Dark”</span> <span style="font-weight: 400;">by Carey Benedict, “The proliferation of violent video games has not coincided with spikes in youth violent crime. The number of violent youth offenders fell by more than half between 1994 and 2010, to 224 per 100,000 population, according to government statistics, while video game sales have more than doubled since 1996.”  If video games lead to violence, like some people argue, then when more video games were sold, certainly, more people would be committing crimes. The previous evidence clearly explains that this is simply not how it works.  Others also claim that when children play violent video games, they are more hostile and violent, nevertheless, “They argue that violent video games may provide a safe outlet for angry feelings</span><span style="font-weight: 400;">.” </span><span style="font-weight: 400;">(Newsela).  As you can see, video games actually cause children to be </span><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">less</span></i><span style="font-weight: 400;"> violent, since they are able to release some of their anger while playing these video games.  Not only are they able to release their anger, but it’s also in a safe way, where they are not hurting themselves or others.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Let’s come to an agreement, video games should be played by children  because they do not lead to violent crimes and they help with the physical and mental health of children.  When children play violent video games they burn more calories than just watching TV, and they can release some of their rage and hostility. But, most importantly, video games lead to significantly high percentages of less vicious crimes.  Without a doubt, the world could use less violence and hostility, and video games will help with that.  What can you do to help spread this message?  </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;"><em>Voice your position to professionals, such as child psychiatrists, on how beneficial video games are.</em></span></p>
<hr>
<p class="align-center"><em><span style="font-weight: 400;">Citations</span></em></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Carey, Benedict. “Shooting in the Dark.” </span><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">The New York Times</span></i><span style="font-weight: 400;">, The New York Times, 11 Feb. 2013, </span><a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2013/02/12/science/studying-the-ef"><span style="font-weight: 400;">www.nytimes.com/2013/02/12/science/studying-the-ef</span></a></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">“Essential Facts About Games and Violence.” </span><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">The Entertainment Software Association</span></i><span style="font-weight: 400;">,   </span><span style="font-weight: 400;">Entertainment Software Association, 20016, </span><a href="http://www.theesa.com/article/essential-facts-about-games-and-violence/."><span style="font-weight: 400;">www.theesa.com/article/essential-facts-about-games-and-violence/.</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;">  </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">“ Game on! New Study Says Video Games Could Be Good for You?” </span><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">Newsela- Game on! New </span></i><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">Study Says Video Games Could Be Good for You</span></i><span style="font-weight: 400;">, By Chicago Tribune, Adapted by Newsela Staff, 2 Apr. 20 ADAD, <a href="http://www.newsela.com/read/videogames-health/id/7123/">www.newsela.com/read/videogames-health/id/7123/</a>.</span><span style="font-weight: 400;">  </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">“Issue Overview: Do Video Games Cause Violence?” Newsela | Issue Overview: Do Video Games Cause </span><span style="font-weight: 400;">Violence?, Newsela, 27 Nov.  2016. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Kain, Erik. “Do Games Like 'Grand Theft Auto V' Cause Real-World Violence?” </span><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">Do Games Like </span></i><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">'Grand Theft Auto V' Cause Real-World Violence?</span></i><span style="font-weight: 400;">, Forbes Magazine, 18 Sept. 2013, 01:30PM, <a href="http://www.forbes.com/sites/erikkain/2013/09/18/do-games-like-grand-theft-auto-v-cause-real-world-violence/">www.forbes.com/sites/erikkain/2013/09/18/do-games-like-grand-theft-auto-v-cause-real-world-violence/</a>.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Mohammadi, Dara. “How Online Gamers Are Solving Science's Biggest Problems.” </span><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">How </span></i><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">Online Gamers Are Solving Science's Biggest Problems</span></i><span style="font-weight: 400;">, Guardian News and Media, 25 Jan. 2014, 14:05.</span></p>
<p> </p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;"> </span></p>
<p><br><br><br><br><br><br></p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>How Apple&#x27;s Strange Decisions will Ultimately Benefit the Environment</title>
        <author>
            <name>Ishan Vepa</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://blog.thegenz.org/how-apples-strange-decisions-will-ultimately-benefit-the-environment.html"/>
        <id>https://blog.thegenz.org/how-apples-strange-decisions-will-ultimately-benefit-the-environment.html</id>
            <category term="#tech"/>
            <category term="#infrastructure"/>
            <category term="#environment"/>
            <category term="#energy"/>

        <updated>2020-08-11T10:27:01-04:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://blog.thegenz.org/media/posts/26/Electronic_waste_at_Agbogbloshie_Ghana-Ahvan-Misra.jpg" alt="PCB and Electronic components in waste." />
                    It’s not surprising for Apple to remove certain features from their devices or charge a ridiculous price for their products. But in late June, 2020, Apple leaks have confirmed the upcoming iPhone 12 will not ship with a charging adapter or EarPods. This isn’t like&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <img src="https://blog.thegenz.org/media/posts/26/Electronic_waste_at_Agbogbloshie_Ghana-Ahvan-Misra.jpg" alt="PCB and Electronic components in waste." />
                <p class="align-center msg msg--highlight "><em><strong>It’s not surprising for Apple to remove certain features from their devices or charge a ridiculous price for their products. But in late June, 2020, Apple leaks have confirmed the upcoming iPhone 12 will not ship with a charging adapter or EarPods.</strong></em></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;"> This isn’t like the removal of the headphone jack from Apple devices in 2016--this is more controversial than that. Ultimately, this will provide a huge benefit for the environment, and there are reasons to support why this was the right decision.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Of course, coming from Apple, this decision was expected to happen sooner rather than later, as Apple have been striving to create a portless iPhone sometime in the future. This was just one step they needed to take in order to get closer to their goal, albeit controversial. The headphone jack wasn’t a big feature on their smartphones, so its removal from the iPhone 7 and all future iPhones became less of an issue when people were able to get an adapter to use their EarPods and/or get Apple’s AirPods for wireless Bluetooth connection. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">This time, Apple is removing a </span><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">necessary</span></i><span style="font-weight: 400;"> component of their smartphones. It is nearly impossible to consistently use and charge an iPhone with just a Lightning cable on a day-to-day basis (though USB-C is likely going to be on the iPhone 12), unless one has a USB wall outlet at home. That still doesn’t solve any problems, since those are a hassle to install manually.</span></p>
<p><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">So, the question is, why did Apple decide to remove a major accessory people are essentially required to use?</span></i></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Currently, with no speculation from Apple, the answer to this question is not certain. (The information was leaked by Ming-Chi Kuo, one of the most reliable and accurate sources for information about Apple’s future plans.) Essentially, with less accessories being produced and sold alongside the upcoming iPhones, there will be much less e-waste. According to Arun Maini from the YouTube channel “Mrwhosetheboss”, Apple has about 66% of all profits with only 20% of people in the world using iPhones. So, if only a small percentage of the human population are going to buy one of the new 2020 iPhones, is the reduction in e-waste worth the annoyance of having to find an older charging adapter or buy one separately?</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">On paper, it doesn’t look like a worthy trade-off. However, one thing needs to be considered: In the tech industry, specifically smartphones, Android manufacturers see Apple as a role model, and usually implement Apple’s “odd” decisions into their own devices. There are several examples of this, most notably the headphone jack’s removal from nearly every Android flagship. So, Android smartphone manufacturers like Samsung, OnePlus, Oppo, etc. are likely to follow Apple’s footsteps and remove the charging adapter from their smartphone boxes sometime in the future, thus reducing even more e-waste.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">On the other hand, people say the removal of these accessories from smartphone purchases will not have a worthy impact on the amount of e-waste, because most people don’t throw their chargers away in the first place. They also say Apple is being greedy and are only doing this to save money, as they likely will still charge full price for their upcoming iPhones even though it doesn’t have accessories. Tech reviewer Marques Brownlee released a YouTube video about the removal of these accessories and why Apple’s decisions were justified (and not an excuse for them to gain an even bigger profit). In the video, he said people who want/need the charger should be able to order the charger at a discount with their phone, since the charger Apple sells is a very basic 5 watt charger and people who already have a charger don’t need another, especially if it’s inferior to the one they already have. He also refers back to the CEO of Anker’s words by saying it will still save a significant amount of e-waste, at least enough that it will be a huge benefit for the environment. Brownlee’s ideas have a possibility of being implemented by Apple simply due to how beneficial it is for everyone buying a 2020 iPhone.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">After reading all of this, you may be wondering: </span><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">Why should I care? Why do I need to know about Apple’s decisions? </span></i><span style="font-weight: 400;">Well, you need to understand this: Apple’s decisions are going to affect </span><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">you</span></i><span style="font-weight: 400;">. You </span><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">will</span></i><span style="font-weight: 400;"> be affected by these decisions in the future because you are going to purchase a new smartphone. You may have to deal with the annoyance of using your old and worn out charging adapter, or simply not having any earbuds if you don’t already have a pair. But most importantly, you will understand how the decrease in e-waste throughout the world will be absolutely worth it.</span></p>
<hr>
<p class="align-center"><em>Citations</em></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Bohn, Dieter. “Apple Might Not Include a Charger with the iPhone 12. Good.” </span><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">The Verge</span></i><span style="font-weight: 400;">, The Verge, 30 June 2020, www.theverge.com/2020/6/30/21307463/apple-iphone-12-power-adapter-charger-rumor-usb-c.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Mayo, Benjamin. “Kuo: Apple Will Not Include Earbuds or Charger in iPhone 12 Box.” </span><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">9to5Mac</span></i><span style="font-weight: 400;">, 29 June 2020, 9to5mac.com/2020/06/28/iphone-12-no-earbuds-power-adapter/.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">“On the iPhone 12 With No Charger…” YouTube, uploaded by Marques Brownlee, 1 July 2020, https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=8IB7JcKJEeI</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">“The Apple Master Plan.” YouTube, uploaded by Mrwhosetheboss, 11 July 2020, https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=aYPaso1zHow</span></p>
<p><br><br></p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
</feed>
