<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <title>The Generation Z Blog</title>
    <link href="https://blog.thegenz.org/feed.xml" rel="self" />
    <link href="https://blog.thegenz.org" />
    <updated>1969-12-31T19:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <author>
        <name>Ishan Vepa</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://blog.thegenz.org</id>

    <entry>
        <title>Why Do We Procrastinate?</title>
        <author>
            <name>Ishan Vepa</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://blog.thegenz.org/why-do-we-procrastinate.html"/>
        <id>https://blog.thegenz.org/why-do-we-procrastinate.html</id>
            <category term="#youth"/>
            <category term="#society"/>
            <category term="#mentalhealth"/>
            <category term="#education"/>

        <updated>2020-07-30T18:19:22-04:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://blog.thegenz.org/media/posts/31/Procrastination-Article-Picture-Alyson-Torino.jpg" alt="Chalk board with inscription." />
                    According to Psycom, a resource for mental health, nearly 20% of men and women in the US are chronic procrastinators, and that procrastination is an issue humanity has faced for centuries. It is the last thing that we want to do, but somehow it ends&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <img src="https://blog.thegenz.org/media/posts/31/Procrastination-Article-Picture-Alyson-Torino.jpg" alt="Chalk board with inscription." />
                <p><span style="font-weight: 400;">According to Psycom, a resource for mental health, nearly 20% of men and women in the US are chronic procrastinators, and that procrastination is an issue humanity has faced for centuries. It is the last thing that we want to do, but somehow it ends up happening anyways. From a young age, we are taught to manage our time properly in order to complete all of our responsibilities on time, but people can’t control when they procrastinate. We rely on self control and motivation to get tasks done, but it's when those two things aren’t present that procrastination occurs. It is a vicious cycle that is difficult to escape, but the first step in doing so is figuring out the reason behind your procrastination. </span></p>
<p class="align-center msg msg--highlight "><em><strong>Lack of motivation </strong></em><span style="font-weight: 400;"><em>is one possible reason someone may procrastinate.</em> </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">As I stated before, motivation is what drives us to complete a task, so lack thereof would lead to the task not being completed. The cause behind lack of motivation is extrinsic motivation, meaning coming from an outside source. This is common among students in the form of teachers and parents. If the student themself does not want to complete their work, the motivation for them would come from their parents and teachers, which is not enough for them to complete their task.</span></p>
<p class="msg msg--highlight  align-center"><em><strong>Fear of failure and perfectionism </strong></em><span style="font-weight: 400;"><em>is another cause to procrastination.</em> </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">These examples go hand in hand since they are very similar in their root cause, which is a person’s work not being good enough. If someone is afraid of failing, then they will not be driven to complete their work since they don’t want it to be seen as mediocre. Similarly, if someone is a perfectionist, then they will want their work to be flawless. This will either cause the person to never start their task, or to never finish it, since it has to be perfect. </span></p>
<p class="msg msg--highlight  align-center"><em><strong>Negative emotions</strong><span style="font-weight: 400;"> are a large cause of procrastination, such as being overwhelmed or anxious about a task. </span></em></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">One becomes overwhelmed by a task when they think it is much too large, or when multiple smaller tasks pile up. This will cause a person to avoid their tasks and procrastinate them. Anxiety about a task is difficult to overcome because it creates a loop. Once a person becomes anxious about a task, they will avoid it, which will only amplify their anxiety about it, since it is not being completed. </span></p>
<p class="msg msg--highlight  align-center"><em><strong>Optimism</strong></em><span style="font-weight: 400;"><em>, however strange it sounds, contributes to procrastination as well.</em> </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Positive thinking, in terms of procrastination, refers to either the amount of time someone thinks a task will take, or one’s ability to complete it. This will lead them to believe that they won’t need to put much work into the task, which means they will wait to complete it. Because of this, when they actually do the task, it will become stressful when they realize they have not allowed themself enough time to do it well.</span></p>
<p class="msg msg--highlight align-center"><em><strong>Disconnect from the future self</strong><span style="font-weight: 400;">, or temporal disjunction, is another cause of procrastination, and also happens to be mine. </span></em></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">It is when one sees their future self as a completely different person. This leads them to think that the task they have at hand is not their problem, but one for their future self to take care of. It becomes a way for them to deflect their responsibilities onto “someone else” and not worry about completing them. Speaking from personal experience, this ends up being a large problem when the due date for a task comes around and there is little to no work shown for it.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">These are just a few of many causes of procrastination, and once you have identified why you procrastinate, you can then figure out how to stop. Here are some tips to help you get started:</span></p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Just start working. </strong><span style="font-weight: 400;">The hardest part of any task is getting started, and once you get that out of the way, you have a good foundation for quality work.</span></li>
</ul>
<ul>
<li><strong>Break it down. </strong><span style="font-weight: 400;">The larger a task is, the less you will want to do it. Breaking a larger task into smaller ones will be a big help in staying productive.</span></li>
</ul>
<ul>
<li><strong>Put aside possible distractions. </strong><span style="font-weight: 400;">Find yourself a quiet workspace where you can focus on your task. It’s not possible to eliminate every single distraction there may be, but putting away the ones you know will cause a problem will allow you to concentrate.</span></li>
</ul>
<ul>
<li><strong>Stay positive!</strong><span style="font-weight: 400;"> If you approach a task with a negative attitude, your work will not be at its best, and it will be harder for you to focus. If you stay positive while working, it will be much more enjoyable and the quality of your work will be better.</span></li>
</ul>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Procrastination is one of the biggest obstacles preventing us from reaching our full potential. Don’t let yourself be the one to stop you from making the world a better place.</span></p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>The Yemeni Crisis</title>
        <author>
            <name>Ishan Vepa</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://blog.thegenz.org/the-yemeni-crisis.html"/>
        <id>https://blog.thegenz.org/the-yemeni-crisis.html</id>
            <category term="#society"/>
            <category term="#globalconflict"/>
            <category term="#global"/>
            <category term="#environment"/>
            <category term="#crisis"/>
            <category term="#community"/>

        <updated>2020-07-30T18:19:22-04:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://blog.thegenz.org/media/posts/30/yemen_war.jpg" alt="Aftermath of Yemen Conflict" />
                    Yemen is currently caught in the worst humanitarian crisis of the 21st century with 24 million people or 80% of the population in need of humanitarian aid. The issue: The country is going through its second civil war which started in 2015 and over 100,000&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <img src="https://blog.thegenz.org/media/posts/30/yemen_war.jpg" alt="Aftermath of Yemen Conflict" />
                <p class="msg msg--highlight  align-center"><strong><em>Yemen is currently caught in the worst humanitarian crisis of the 21st century with 24 million people or 80% of the population in need of humanitarian aid. </em></strong></p>
<p><strong><i>The issue:</i></strong></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The country is going through its second civil war which started in 2015 and over 100,000 people have been killed by the conflict. The situation only gets worse every day. According to UNICEF, more than half of those in need of humanitarian aid are children and around 2 million children under the age of 5 are malnourished. Civilians are suffering the most due to the lack of essential items. Roads and buildings required for delivering food and water have been destroyed or taken over resulting in the price of food skyrocketing. Most cannot afford enough food for their families and have had to flee their homes to get away from conflict. Houthi rebels who are fighting the government have been accused of confiscating food, water, and other essential items from civilians.</span></p>
<p><em><strong>American involvement in Yemen: </strong></em></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Ever since the start of the war, the United States supported its ally Saudi Arabia who is fighting against Yemeni forces. The U.S has sold over 110 billion in arms to Saudi since 2009. Many have been critical of America’s involvement and claim that the conflict will end if the U.S. pulls out. However, the U.S. continues to show support of Saudi and sells arms to them. Saudi forces use weapons without consideration of civilian lives which the U.S. knows but does nothing. Saudi Arabia targets Yemeni infrastructure as a strategy to cripple Yemen from the inside by causing civil unrest and to weaken enemy forces but the conflict has been stretched for years and thousands of civilian lives have been taken. </span></p>
<p><strong><i>Covid-19 in Yemen:</i></strong></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The coronavirus has made things much worse than it already is in Yemen. Cases are spiking and most don’t have access to affordable healthcare which is crucial to stopping the spread of the virus. Most health workers are not receiving pay and basic sanitation supplies which is putting them at risk of getting the virus. They also get threatened and killed for doing their work causing many to flee in fear. Over 4 million people have been displaced and many of them live in areas with a high population density which further increases the danger of the situation. Many children could not afford school before the virus but now that schools have closed, 7.8 million children do not have access to education. There is a short supply of ventilators and test kits. Many are not aware of the dangers of the virus and its high contagiousness. The situation is getting worse every day and the UN has gone as far as airlifting testing kits to Yemen in hopes of slowing the spread.</span></p>
<p><strong><i>How you can help: </i></strong></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">One of the best ways you can help other than donating is to spread awareness about the issue. Not many people know about this and it doesn’t get much media attention even though millions of people are starving. Spreading awareness about this issue will allow it get more media attention and garner more donors. Another way to help is to sign petitions that demand change. For example, a petition on Change.org already has over 2.7 million signatures. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Here are some useful links to help :</span></p>
<ul>
<li style="font-weight: 400;">
<div class="js-petition-content">
<div class="sm-txt-c mtxxl xs-mtm xs-phs">
<p class="mtl mbxxxl xs-mts xs-mbxs type-break-word petition-title"><a href="https://tinyurl.com/y2olzqqk" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Stop the war and end the famine in Yemen, Change.org</a></p>
</div>
</div>
</li>
<li style="font-weight: 400;"><a href="https://tinyurl.com/yxotc3sg" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Send support to fight medical crisis in Yemin, Islamic Relief USA</a></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400;"><a href="https://tinyurl.com/y2p9ckpj" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Help save children in Yemen, savethechildren.org</a></li>
<li class="align-left" style="font-weight: 400;"><a href="https://tinyurl.com/y3d2gte3" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Donate to help save Yemeni lives, Doctors Without Borders</a></li>
</ul>
<hr>
<p class="align-center"><em>Citations</em></p>
<p>“What's Happening in Yemen? .” <i>BBC News</i>, BBC, 28 Mar. 2918, <a href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/newsround/38317367" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">www.bbc.co.uk/newsround/38317367</a>.</p>
<p>UNICEF. “Yemen Crisis.” <i>UNICEF</i>, 22 July 2020, <a href="http://www.unicef.org/emergencies/yemen-crisis" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">www.unicef.org/emergencies/yemen-crisis</a>.</p>
<p>Bazzi, Mohamad. “America Is Likely Complicit in War Crimes in Yemen. It's Time to Hold the US to Account | Mohamad Bazzi.” <i>The Guardian</i>, Guardian News and Media, 3 Oct. 2019, <a href="http://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/2019/oct/03/yemen-airstrikes-saudi-arabia-mbs-us" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/2019/oct/03/yemen-airstrikes-saudi-arabia-mbs-us</a>.</p>
<p>“Yemen: Displaced at Heightened Covid-19 Risk.” <i>Human Rights Watch</i>, 22 May 2020, <a href="http://www.hrw.org/news/2020/05/22/yemen-displaced-heightened-covid-19-risk" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">www.hrw.org/news/2020/05/22/yemen-displaced-heightened-covid-19-risk</a>.</p>
<p><br><br><br><br><br><br></p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Hedy Lamarr: More Than Just a Pretty Face</title>
        <author>
            <name>Ishan Vepa</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://blog.thegenz.org/hedy-lamarr-more-than-just-a-pretty-face.html"/>
        <id>https://blog.thegenz.org/hedy-lamarr-more-than-just-a-pretty-face.html</id>
            <category term="#womensrights"/>
            <category term="#womeninstem"/>
            <category term="#society"/>
            <category term="#science"/>
            <category term="#inequality"/>
            <category term="#community"/>

        <updated>2020-07-30T18:19:22-04:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://blog.thegenz.org/media/posts/29/Hedy-Lamarr-Science-Abigail-Mullins.jpg" alt="Hedy Lamar working on scientific experimentation." />
                    Can a woman be both smart and beautiful? The obvious answer is well, yes. Of course she can. However, society tends to split women between being smart and beautiful. There are women who are seen as beautiful, and there are women who are smart, although&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <img src="https://blog.thegenz.org/media/posts/29/Hedy-Lamarr-Science-Abigail-Mullins.jpg" alt="Hedy Lamar working on scientific experimentation." />
                <p class="msg msg--highlight align-center"><span style="font-weight: 400;"><strong><em>Can a woman be both smart and beautiful? The obvious answer is well, yes. Of course she can. However, society tends to split women between being smart and beautiful.</em></strong></span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">There are women who are seen as beautiful, and there are women who are smart, although in the past a lot less was seen of the latter. Take Hedy Lamarr. It is a name that evokes old Hollywood and great beauty. She was the most beautiful woman and a famous actress. She was also an inventor. Somehow, history tends to forget this last part.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Lamarr had from a young age had had a love of science, which had been influenced by her father. He talked to her about the inner workings of machines to the point that Lamarr at the age of 5 was able to take apart and reassemble a music box. Guided by her mother, Lamarr took on roles in movies and eventually married a munitions manufacturer, who often had guests over. Lamarr would listen in on their conversations regarding wartimes weapons. In 1937, she left her unhappy marriage with a husband who didn’t see her beyond a pretty doll and eventually ended up in London. Unfortunately, this would not be her first experience with being seen only as pretty.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">In London, she met the co-founder of MGM studios which eventually led to a career in Hollywood. Despite her newfound fame, Lamarr still found time for her inventive mind. In her trailer, she continued working on various projects. Howard Hughes encouraged her inventive mind, and would take her to airplane factories. She even designed airplane wings by taking inspiration from nature. She combined the design of the fastest fish’s fins and the fastest birds’ wings into one set of speedy airplane wings. “Genius” Hughes called her.  Her inventive side, though, was somewhat hidden from the public, and not because she didn’t want people to know.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Lamarr shared her passion of inventing with George Antheil, a pianist. Both were concerned by the looming war and wanted to contribute ideas to help. In order to help torpedoes resist interference from the enemy, they created a frequency-hopping system that prevented the signal from being jammed. The transmitter and receiver would jump frequencies together and the enemy would not be able to intercept the message with the signal constantly moving across frequencies. In August 1942, they received a patent and donated it to the US Navy. However, the US Navy rejected it, saying it was too cumbersome. Unfazed, Lamarr continued to show her support for the war and used her celebrity status to raise money for war bonds. She even became a US citizen in 1953.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">When Hedy Lamarr starred in a new movie, there were headlines raving about how beautiful she was and how greatly she performed. Her new invention? No big headline. Nothing. It is interesting to see what parts of her that society valued. Her beauty, definitely. Her acting, yes. Her scientific side? Nope. It was brushed aside. Why must society pick and choose which parts of people, especially women, to present to the world? Even today actresses are asked about what they wear or their makeup routine. Anything else is irrelevant.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">In the mid 1950s, the Navy did use her and Antheil’s concept on a buoy that was able to detect submarines and even used it during the Cuban Missile Crisis of 1962. With the patent expiring in 1958, neither Lamarr or Antheil ever received any money from their invention.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">As for Lamarr herself, she continued working as an actress until 1958, and even worked as a producer in 2 films. While her great beauty was praised by many, Lamarr did not find her outward appearance as the most important thing. “Any girl can look glamorous. All you have to do is look stupid,” she once said. Lamarr was aware of how society valued her beauty. In the 40s, her profile was most requested by plastic surgery patients. Could the same awe be said of her science side? No. Lamarr was in a way forced to hide that aspect about her because she couldn’t be recognized for being smart. Society only really valued beauty in women anyway. Even if she was smart, that wasn’t really important. It is unfortunate that society was, and still is, like that. Society should realize that beauty isn’t always about looking good. It is also about creativeness, kindness, what we can do for others, and so much more beyond physical attributes. Hedy Lamarr created the frequency-hopping system not for herself, but to help our country win the war.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">As the years went on, Lamarr never really spoke of her inventive nature. Why? Perhaps because she felt she wouldn’t have been taken seriously. After all, the reason she left her first husband was because he never treated her like an equal. It is unfortunate that she felt that she had to conform to society’s ideals and couldn’t share her inventive side. Society’s idea of her was that she was pretty and that was it. Even today women have to deal with society only thinking of them as being pretty or smart, never both. To the public, Hedy Lamarr was only beautiful, and some probably thought that because she was beautiful, she was dumb as well. If she was smart, she would’ve been ugly. Which is completely untrue.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">As time went on, society’s ideas of women lessened a bit. Women could get recognition for their brains even while being pretty. Long lost tapes from the 1990s tapes reveal a different side to Lamarr than the public had originally seen. She talked about her inventions, and said “The brains of people are more interesting than looks, I think.” She was beginning to be comfortable talking about her science side and know that she wouldn’t get ridiculed for it. Finally, in 1997, she began to receive credit for the work she had done. She was the first woman to receive the Invention Convention’s Bulbie Gnass Spirit of Achievement Award, which is the equivalent of an Oscar in the inventing world. The Electronic Frontier Foundation honored her and Antheil with the Pioneer Award. It took 50 years for her and Anthiel’s achievement to be recognized. Why did it have to take so long? Did society simply not want to recognize her efforts? We have to realize that people are more than just what they look like. The things they do, how they treat others are more important factors that define a person. Physical characteristics mean nothing and do not contribute to who a person is overall.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Lamarr passed away in 2000. However, her frequency-hopping system continues to live on. In fact, you most certainly have used it before, maybe even right now. Today, this technology is used in WiFi and Bluetooth communications. In 2014, she and Antheil were posthumously inducted into the Inventor’s Hall of Fame for their work.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">It is interesting how history has chosen what pieces of someone to remember. For Hedy Lamarr, history chose her beauty. Not her work as an inventor, which was ignored for years. It wasn’t until 50 years later after the invention of her and Antheil’s frequency-hopping system were they recognized for their work. Why was it forgotten? Perhaps because society values physical beauty more than anything else, especially concerning women. A woman cannot be both smart and pretty. But Hedy Lamarr defies that role. She was a brilliant inventor and a genius who also happened to look good. Her inventive mind is perhaps the most beautiful part about her.</span></p>
<hr>
<p class="align-center"><em><span style="font-weight: 400;">Citations</span></em></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Brancaccio, David, and Paulina Velasco. “The Story of Hedy Lamarr, the Hollywood Beauty Whose Invention Helped Enable Wi-Fi, GPS and Bluetooth.” </span><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">Marketplace</span></i><span style="font-weight: 400;">, 29 Apr. 2019, </span><a href="http://www.marketplace.org/2017/11/21/inventor-changed-our-world-and-also-happened-be-famous-hollywood-star/"><span style="font-weight: 400;">www.marketplace.org/2017/11/21/inventor-changed-our-world-and-also-happened-be-famous-hollywood-star/</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;">.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Cheslak, Colleen. “Hedy Lamarr.” </span><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">Hedy Lamarr</span></i><span style="font-weight: 400;">, National Women's History Museum, 30 Aug. 2018, </span><a href="http://www.womenshistory.org/students-and-educators/biographies/hedy-lamarr"><span style="font-weight: 400;">www.womenshistory.org/students-and-educators/biographies/hedy-lamarr</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;">.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Desta, Yohana. “How Inventive ‘Genius’ Hedy Lamarr Became a Hollywood Tragedy.” </span><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">Vanity Fair</span></i><span style="font-weight: 400;">, Vanity Fair, 25 May 2017, </span><a href="http://www.vanityfair.com/hollywood/2017/04/hedy-lamarr-documentary-clip"><span style="font-weight: 400;">www.vanityfair.com/hollywood/2017/04/hedy-lamarr-documentary-clip</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;">.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Field, Shivaune. “Hedy Lamarr: The Incredible Mind Behind Secure WiFi, GPS And Bluetooth.” </span><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">Forbes</span></i><span style="font-weight: 400;">, Forbes Magazine, 8 Mar. 2018, </span><a href="http://www.forbes.com/sites/shivaunefield/2018/02/28/hedy-lamarr-the-incredible-mind-behind-secure-wi-fi-gps-bluetooth/#66f66fba41b7"><span style="font-weight: 400;">www.forbes.com/sites/shivaunefield/2018/02/28/hedy-lamarr-the-incredible-mind-behind-secure-wi-fi-gps-bluetooth/#66f66fba41b7</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;">.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">George, Alice. “Thank This World War II-Era Film Star for Your Wi-Fi.” </span><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">Smithsonian.com</span></i><span style="font-weight: 400;">, Smithsonian Institution, 4 Apr. 2019, <a href="http://www.smithsonianmag.com/smithsonian-institution/thank-world-war-ii-era-film-star-your-wi-fi-180971584/">www.smithsonianmag.com/smithsonian-institution/thank-world-war-ii-era-film-star-your-wi-fi-180971584/</a>.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Long, Emily. “HEDY LAMARR, MARCH 2017 LAMP LUMINARY.” </span><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">The Lamp</span></i><span style="font-weight: 400;">, 14 </span><span style="font-weight: 400;">Mar. 2017, <a href="http://www.thelamp.org/hedy-lamarr/">www.thelamp.org/hedy-lamarr/</a>.</span></p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Lowering the Voting Age</title>
        <author>
            <name>Ishan Vepa</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://blog.thegenz.org/lowering-the-voting-age.html"/>
        <id>https://blog.thegenz.org/lowering-the-voting-age.html</id>
            <category term="#vote"/>
            <category term="#society"/>
            <category term="#rights"/>
            <category term="#generations"/>
            <category term="#community"/>

        <updated>2020-07-30T18:19:22-04:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://blog.thegenz.org/media/posts/28/1242731F-441C-41B7-8866-A44110881168-Ryan-Shankar.png" alt="Voting rights depiction." />
                    Voting age is a very controversial topic. History has seen the minimum age for voting change, from 21 to 18 during 1969. When 18 year-olds were being drafted into the military, but could not vote. Now something similar has occurred, with climate change and gun&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <img src="https://blog.thegenz.org/media/posts/28/1242731F-441C-41B7-8866-A44110881168-Ryan-Shankar.png" alt="Voting rights depiction." />
                <p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Voting age is a very controversial topic. History has seen the minimum age for voting change, from 21 to 18 during 1969. When 18 year-olds were being drafted into the military, but could not vote. Now something similar has occurred, with climate change and gun control. Now more than ever, guns are killing more students. In 46 weeks there has been over 45 school shootings killing at least one student. Still gun laws aren’t changing and many believe it's because students, the ones actually being affected by the shootings aren’t represented in politics. People are starting comparing this to when 18-year-olds couldn’t vote for the president that was drafting them into the military. Climate change is a problem that is not going to affect the current generation but the generation born after the 2000’s, so it doesn’t get much attention and priority from current voters. Because of 16 year-olds participation and involvement in these problems, national voting age should be reduced to 16.</span></p>
<p><strong><i>What Are Ages of Current Voters?</i></strong></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Currently the U.S has the lowest voter turnout of any developed nation. This greatly affects the U.S.A and can be seen in their voter demographics, most of the voters in the U.S are age 65 plus white, data provided from the U.S Census. The main problem with this demographic is that they don’t know much about current issues, such as climate change and gun violence because it won’t affect them as much as it affects minorities or people of younger ages. The current issue many have is that. Why should the kids of this generation stand on the side and watch while their future is being destroyed right in front of them, with the world's lack to address climate change? Many teens around the world, especially in the U.S are stepping up and organizing protests and coming together to try to stop this, like the Juliana Plaintiffs and the recent worldwide teen protest about climate change. The only thing is no leaders are listening because they don’t have to worry about teen voters, all they have to do is satisfy the older population who is clearly not worried about climate change. As seen from the recent election of leaders around the world who have been ignoring this issue. But one highly debated topic has been gun control. The countless protests that teens have done trying to stricten gun control laws have seemed to be ineffective. This goes back and relates to the fact that politicians don't have to address teens issues and concerns, because it won't affect their chances of being elected. They are better off not addressing gun control because the people who vote are not as concerned about guns or climate change. This is why U.S.A has to change its voting age, because for a country that boasts about having a democracy, clearly do not as not everyone's issues are being heard and attended to. </span></p>
<p><strong><i>Why Isn’t the Voting Age Being Changed?</i></strong></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;"> People believe that 16 year-olds are not mature enough to vote, or not involved as much as older people. People argue that 16 year-olds don’t care enough about politics. These were the same arguments people used when trying to justify why African Americans shouldn’t and women shouldn’t vote. They said that African Americans and women were not relevant and weren’t as smart as the current voter population, but when you look at it now it seems ridiculous. The same should be done with 16 year-olds, now more than ever. Because with technology they are more exposed current affairs and politics. This can be seen when you look at mock elections and voting events teens are participating more in these elections because they care about current affairs. Ayanna Pressley who presented a bill to lower voting age to the House said </span><span style="font-weight: 400;">“Some have questioned the maturity of our youth. I don’t,” the congresswoman told the House”, she went on to say “A sixteen-year-old in 2019 possesses a wisdom and a maturity that comes from 2019 challenges, hardships, and threats”. The bill she presented did not pass but did get the support of 125 House members. </span><span style="font-weight: 400;">Teen activism is rising, recently there have been many protests against the way the world is being run and this has been proving Pressley’s point of why teens should be allowed to vote. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The national voting age of the United States should be lowered to 16 because it allows a larger voting population of people who are interested in their future. Opening up voting to 16 will allow the country to have more creative solutions and gives the youth a chance to be heard. Many say that lowering the voting age will be unfavorable to the country but they are also the ones who make key decisions in the lives of the younger people and so far their decisions have negatively impacted the youth. The youth can't argue because their voice is not heard and lowering the voting age will allow them to be heard.</span></p>
<hr>
<p class="align-center"><em>Citations</em></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">“ACLU Letter Opposing H.R. 1 (For the People Act of 2019).” </span><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">American Civil Liberties Union</span></i><span style="font-weight: 400;">, https://www.aclu.org/aclu-letter-opposing-hr-1-people-act-2019.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Astor, Maggie. “16-Year-Olds Want a Vote. Fifty Years Ago, So Did 18-Year-Olds.” </span><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">The  New York Times</span></i><span style="font-weight: 400;">, The New York Times, 19 May 2019, https://www.nytimes.com/2019/05/19/us/politics/voting-age.html.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Cilluffo, Anthony, and Richard Fry. “Gen Z, Millennials and Gen X Outvoted Older Generations in 2018 Midterms.” </span><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">Pew Research Center</span></i><span style="font-weight: 400;">, Pew Research Center, 29 May 2019, https://www.pewresearch.org/fact-tank/2019/05/29/gen-z-millennials-and-gen-x-outvoted-older-generations-in-2018-midterms/.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Costly, Andrew. “Race and Voting - Constitutional Rights Foundation.” </span><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">Race and Voting - Constitutional Rights Foundation</span></i><span style="font-weight: 400;">, https://www.crf-usa.org/brown-v-board-50th-anniversary/race-and-voting.html.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">DeSilver, Drew. “U.S. Voter Turnout Trails Most Developed Countries.” </span><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">Pew Research Center</span></i><span style="font-weight: 400;">, Pew Research Center, 21 May 2018, https://www.pewresearch.org/fact-tank/2018/05/21/u-s-voter-turnout-trails-most-developed-countries/.</span></p>
<p><br><br></p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Should Children Play Video Games?</title>
        <author>
            <name>Ishan Vepa</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://blog.thegenz.org/should-children-play-video-games.html"/>
        <id>https://blog.thegenz.org/should-children-play-video-games.html</id>
            <category term="#youth"/>
            <category term="#videogames"/>
            <category term="#mentalhealth"/>

        <updated>2020-07-30T18:19:22-04:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://blog.thegenz.org/media/posts/27/video-game-game-controller-genz-Lauren-Scarpa.jpg" alt="White Xbox and Sony PS4 Controllers on Brown Surface, Video Game." />
                    Should children play video games? “They argue that violent video games may provide a safe outlet for angry feelings. This may actually reduce crime”(Newsela). Many experts claim that video games aren’t proven to lead to violent crimes in the future. They also have many studies&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <img src="https://blog.thegenz.org/media/posts/27/video-game-game-controller-genz-Lauren-Scarpa.jpg" alt="White Xbox and Sony PS4 Controllers on Brown Surface, Video Game." />
                <p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Should children play video games? “They argue that violent video games may provide a safe outlet for angry feelings.  This may actually reduce crime”(Newsela).  Many experts claim that video games aren’t proven to lead to violent crimes in the future.  They also have many studies showing that when video game sales increased the crime rate decreased.  Children should play video games, because they lower crime rates, they do not lead to violent crimes, and they help with their physical and mental health.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">There is no question that video games are proven to lower crime rates. In the article, “Shooters in the Dark”</span><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">, </span></i><span style="font-weight: 400;">“‘We found that higher rates of violent video game sales related to a decrease in crimes, and especially violent crimes’, said Dr. Ward, whose co-authors were A. Scott Cunningham of Baylor University and Benjamin Engelstätter of the Center for European Economic Research in Mannheim, Germany”(Benedict).  This shows that when more video games are sold, there is a decrease in crimes. But, is there much of a decrease in crimes?  Yes, actually.  One of the most significant pieces of evidence that supports this is,  “Issue Overview: Do Video Games Cause Violence?” by Newsela, “From 1994 to 2014, game sales increased by more than 200 percent.  During those same ten years, murders by youth acting on their own fell 76 percent and violent crime rates dropped 37 percent.” When the video games sales increased by 200 percent the violent crime rates dropped.</span><span style="font-weight: 400;">  </span><span style="font-weight: 400;">This further displays the fact that more video games sales leads to significantly less murders and violent crimes, especially on the youth’s behalf.  If violent video games lead to violent crimes, why exactly would crime rates lower, as more people bought video games?</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">It seems that video games are not proven to lead to violent crimes.  According to “Issue Overview: Do Video Games Cause Violence?”</span> <span style="font-weight: 400;">by Newsela, “Courts have said there is no clear link between video game violence and real-world violence.”  This reveals that even courts have found that video game violence is not linked to real world violence.  Another relevant piece of evidence that supports that video games do not lead to violent crimes is from the article “Do Games Like 'Grand Theft Auto V' Cause Real-World Violence?”</span> <span style="font-weight: 400;">by Erik Kain, “If there is a truly direct, causal link between games like Grand Theft Auto V and violent shootings, we will soon have 18 to 20 million killers on our hands, not to mention the countless millions who have been playing violent video games for years”.  This implies that there is no possible way that video games can lead to violence, because then we would have countless more criminals and violent people in the world.  The world is violent, but not violent enough to be because of video games.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">In general, video games help with the physical and mental health of children.  For instance, the article, “Game on! New Study Says Video Games Could Be Good for You?”</span> <span style="font-weight: 400;">by Newsela, states, “Gaming might burn more calories than just watching TV.  She believes it also may be that kids holding a controller are not as likely to pick a snack or a soda.”  This demonstrates that children who play video games have more physical health benefits than children who don’t.  When children are playing video games they are burning off more calories than just sitting in front of the TV, and these children are also less likely to eat a fattening snack or drink a soda full of sugar, because they won’t be eating for “fun”.  Video games do not only help children with their health physically, but also mentally.  As stated earlier, children who play video games are able to release some of their anger in a safe environment, which ultimately helps their mental health, plus video games also help children with decision making.  In the same article it also talks about this positive mental health factor.  It says that video games are an important tool for teaching children to make the right decision.  This affirms that video games can also help with the decision making part of mental health.  All in all, video games help children physically and mentally in more than one area.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Although some people believe that video games lead to more violence and violent crimes, this is not the case.  According to “Shooters in the Dark”</span> <span style="font-weight: 400;">by Carey Benedict, “The proliferation of violent video games has not coincided with spikes in youth violent crime. The number of violent youth offenders fell by more than half between 1994 and 2010, to 224 per 100,000 population, according to government statistics, while video game sales have more than doubled since 1996.”  If video games lead to violence, like some people argue, then when more video games were sold, certainly, more people would be committing crimes. The previous evidence clearly explains that this is simply not how it works.  Others also claim that when children play violent video games, they are more hostile and violent, nevertheless, “They argue that violent video games may provide a safe outlet for angry feelings</span><span style="font-weight: 400;">.” </span><span style="font-weight: 400;">(Newsela).  As you can see, video games actually cause children to be </span><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">less</span></i><span style="font-weight: 400;"> violent, since they are able to release some of their anger while playing these video games.  Not only are they able to release their anger, but it’s also in a safe way, where they are not hurting themselves or others.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Let’s come to an agreement, video games should be played by children  because they do not lead to violent crimes and they help with the physical and mental health of children.  When children play violent video games they burn more calories than just watching TV, and they can release some of their rage and hostility. But, most importantly, video games lead to significantly high percentages of less vicious crimes.  Without a doubt, the world could use less violence and hostility, and video games will help with that.  What can you do to help spread this message?  </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;"><em>Voice your position to professionals, such as child psychiatrists, on how beneficial video games are.</em></span></p>
<hr>
<p class="align-center"><em><span style="font-weight: 400;">Citations</span></em></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Carey, Benedict. “Shooting in the Dark.” </span><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">The New York Times</span></i><span style="font-weight: 400;">, The New York Times, 11 Feb. 2013, </span><a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2013/02/12/science/studying-the-ef"><span style="font-weight: 400;">www.nytimes.com/2013/02/12/science/studying-the-ef</span></a></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">“Essential Facts About Games and Violence.” </span><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">The Entertainment Software Association</span></i><span style="font-weight: 400;">,   </span><span style="font-weight: 400;">Entertainment Software Association, 20016, </span><a href="http://www.theesa.com/article/essential-facts-about-games-and-violence/."><span style="font-weight: 400;">www.theesa.com/article/essential-facts-about-games-and-violence/.</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;">  </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">“ Game on! New Study Says Video Games Could Be Good for You?” </span><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">Newsela- Game on! New </span></i><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">Study Says Video Games Could Be Good for You</span></i><span style="font-weight: 400;">, By Chicago Tribune, Adapted by Newsela Staff, 2 Apr. 20 ADAD, <a href="http://www.newsela.com/read/videogames-health/id/7123/">www.newsela.com/read/videogames-health/id/7123/</a>.</span><span style="font-weight: 400;">  </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">“Issue Overview: Do Video Games Cause Violence?” Newsela | Issue Overview: Do Video Games Cause </span><span style="font-weight: 400;">Violence?, Newsela, 27 Nov.  2016. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Kain, Erik. “Do Games Like 'Grand Theft Auto V' Cause Real-World Violence?” </span><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">Do Games Like </span></i><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">'Grand Theft Auto V' Cause Real-World Violence?</span></i><span style="font-weight: 400;">, Forbes Magazine, 18 Sept. 2013, 01:30PM, <a href="http://www.forbes.com/sites/erikkain/2013/09/18/do-games-like-grand-theft-auto-v-cause-real-world-violence/">www.forbes.com/sites/erikkain/2013/09/18/do-games-like-grand-theft-auto-v-cause-real-world-violence/</a>.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Mohammadi, Dara. “How Online Gamers Are Solving Science's Biggest Problems.” </span><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">How </span></i><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">Online Gamers Are Solving Science's Biggest Problems</span></i><span style="font-weight: 400;">, Guardian News and Media, 25 Jan. 2014, 14:05.</span></p>
<p> </p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;"> </span></p>
<p><br><br><br><br><br><br></p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>How Apple&#x27;s Strange Decisions will Ultimately Benefit the Environment</title>
        <author>
            <name>Ishan Vepa</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://blog.thegenz.org/how-apples-strange-decisions-will-ultimately-benefit-the-environment.html"/>
        <id>https://blog.thegenz.org/how-apples-strange-decisions-will-ultimately-benefit-the-environment.html</id>
            <category term="#tech"/>
            <category term="#infrastructure"/>
            <category term="#environment"/>
            <category term="#energy"/>

        <updated>2020-07-30T18:19:22-04:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://blog.thegenz.org/media/posts/26/Electronic_waste_at_Agbogbloshie_Ghana-Ahvan-Misra.jpg" alt="PCB and Electronic components in waste." />
                    It’s not surprising for Apple to remove certain features from their devices or charge a ridiculous price for their products. But in late June, 2020, Apple leaks have confirmed the upcoming iPhone 12 will not ship with a charging adapter or EarPods. This isn’t like&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <img src="https://blog.thegenz.org/media/posts/26/Electronic_waste_at_Agbogbloshie_Ghana-Ahvan-Misra.jpg" alt="PCB and Electronic components in waste." />
                <p class="align-center msg msg--highlight "><em><strong>It’s not surprising for Apple to remove certain features from their devices or charge a ridiculous price for their products. But in late June, 2020, Apple leaks have confirmed the upcoming iPhone 12 will not ship with a charging adapter or EarPods.</strong></em></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;"> This isn’t like the removal of the headphone jack from Apple devices in 2016--this is more controversial than that. Ultimately, this will provide a huge benefit for the environment, and there are reasons to support why this was the right decision.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Of course, coming from Apple, this decision was expected to happen sooner rather than later, as Apple have been striving to create a portless iPhone sometime in the future. This was just one step they needed to take in order to get closer to their goal, albeit controversial. The headphone jack wasn’t a big feature on their smartphones, so its removal from the iPhone 7 and all future iPhones became less of an issue when people were able to get an adapter to use their EarPods and/or get Apple’s AirPods for wireless Bluetooth connection. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">This time, Apple is removing a </span><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">necessary</span></i><span style="font-weight: 400;"> component of their smartphones. It is nearly impossible to consistently use and charge an iPhone with just a Lightning cable on a day-to-day basis (though USB-C is likely going to be on the iPhone 12), unless one has a USB wall outlet at home. That still doesn’t solve any problems, since those are a hassle to install manually.</span></p>
<p><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">So, the question is, why did Apple decide to remove a major accessory people are essentially required to use?</span></i></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Currently, with no speculation from Apple, the answer to this question is not certain. (The information was leaked by Ming-Chi Kuo, one of the most reliable and accurate sources for information about Apple’s future plans.) Essentially, with less accessories being produced and sold alongside the upcoming iPhones, there will be much less e-waste. According to Arun Maini from the YouTube channel “Mrwhosetheboss”, Apple has about 66% of all profits with only 20% of people in the world using iPhones. So, if only a small percentage of the human population are going to buy one of the new 2020 iPhones, is the reduction in e-waste worth the annoyance of having to find an older charging adapter or buy one separately?</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">On paper, it doesn’t look like a worthy trade-off. However, one thing needs to be considered: In the tech industry, specifically smartphones, Android manufacturers see Apple as a role model, and usually implement Apple’s “odd” decisions into their own devices. There are several examples of this, most notably the headphone jack’s removal from nearly every Android flagship. So, Android smartphone manufacturers like Samsung, OnePlus, Oppo, etc. are likely to follow Apple’s footsteps and remove the charging adapter from their smartphone boxes sometime in the future, thus reducing even more e-waste.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">On the other hand, people say the removal of these accessories from smartphone purchases will not have a worthy impact on the amount of e-waste, because most people don’t throw their chargers away in the first place. They also say Apple is being greedy and are only doing this to save money, as they likely will still charge full price for their upcoming iPhones even though it doesn’t have accessories. Tech reviewer Marques Brownlee released a YouTube video about the removal of these accessories and why Apple’s decisions were justified (and not an excuse for them to gain an even bigger profit). In the video, he said people who want/need the charger should be able to order the charger at a discount with their phone, since the charger Apple sells is a very basic 5 watt charger and people who already have a charger don’t need another, especially if it’s inferior to the one they already have. He also refers back to the CEO of Anker’s words by saying it will still save a significant amount of e-waste, at least enough that it will be a huge benefit for the environment. Brownlee’s ideas have a possibility of being implemented by Apple simply due to how beneficial it is for everyone buying a 2020 iPhone.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">After reading all of this, you may be wondering: </span><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">Why should I care? Why do I need to know about Apple’s decisions? </span></i><span style="font-weight: 400;">Well, you need to understand this: Apple’s decisions are going to affect </span><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">you</span></i><span style="font-weight: 400;">. You </span><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">will</span></i><span style="font-weight: 400;"> be affected by these decisions in the future because you are going to purchase a new smartphone. You may have to deal with the annoyance of using your old and worn out charging adapter, or simply not having any earbuds if you don’t already have a pair. But most importantly, you will understand how the decrease in e-waste throughout the world will be absolutely worth it.</span></p>
<hr>
<p class="align-center"><em>Citations</em></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Bohn, Dieter. “Apple Might Not Include a Charger with the iPhone 12. Good.” </span><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">The Verge</span></i><span style="font-weight: 400;">, The Verge, 30 June 2020, www.theverge.com/2020/6/30/21307463/apple-iphone-12-power-adapter-charger-rumor-usb-c.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Mayo, Benjamin. “Kuo: Apple Will Not Include Earbuds or Charger in iPhone 12 Box.” </span><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">9to5Mac</span></i><span style="font-weight: 400;">, 29 June 2020, 9to5mac.com/2020/06/28/iphone-12-no-earbuds-power-adapter/.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">“On the iPhone 12 With No Charger…” YouTube, uploaded by Marques Brownlee, 1 July 2020, https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=8IB7JcKJEeI</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">“The Apple Master Plan.” YouTube, uploaded by Mrwhosetheboss, 11 July 2020, https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=aYPaso1zHow</span></p>
<p><br><br></p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>The New Reality of Sports</title>
        <author>
            <name>Ishan Vepa</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://blog.thegenz.org/the-new-reality-of-sports.html"/>
        <id>https://blog.thegenz.org/the-new-reality-of-sports.html</id>
            <category term="#sportsnow"/>
            <category term="#sports"/>
            <category term="#society"/>
            <category term="#socialdistancing"/>
            <category term="#covid19"/>
            <category term="#coronavirus"/>
            <category term="#blacklivesmatter"/>
            <category term="#advocacy"/>

        <updated>2020-07-30T18:19:22-04:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://blog.thegenz.org/media/posts/25/pasted-image-0-GenerationZ-Chronicle.png" alt="Aston Villa Players Take a Knee in Support of Black Lives Matter Campaign" />
                    At the start of quarantine, the world was in an odd place. School closures, followed by stay-at-home orders, all ensued internationally throughout the months of March and April. “Six feet” became a common phrase, summer plans hindered, and most importantly, life for many became dull&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <img src="https://blog.thegenz.org/media/posts/25/pasted-image-0-GenerationZ-Chronicle.png" alt="Aston Villa Players Take a Knee in Support of Black Lives Matter Campaign" />
                <p class="msg msg--highlight "><span style="font-weight: 400;"><em><strong>At the start of quarantine, the world was in an odd place. School closures, followed by stay-at-home orders, all ensued internationally throughout the months of March and April. “Six feet” became a common phrase, summer plans hindered, and most importantly, life for many became dull and uneventful without the existence of televised sports. I fell into the latter. </strong></em> </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Fast forward to nearly a month, George Floyd is killed by a Minneapolis policeman. This sparks passionate anti-racism protests across the United States. Feuling these calls for action is the </span><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">Black Lives Matter</span></i><span style="font-weight: 400;"> movement. Voicing to put an end to racially targeted violence and white supremacy. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Now as nations begin to reopen, the pandemic’s pace is quickening worldwide, and the Black Lives Matter movement is continuing to gain traction, we see how these factors all intertwine with the return of sports. </span></p>
<p class="align-center"><strong><span style="text-decoration: underline;">NASCAR &amp; PGA Tour</span></strong></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The Professional Golfers Association Tour returned on June 11. NASCAR returned on May 17. Both including an abundance of testing and safety measures. Both had no spectators.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">A point speaking against systemic racism, for both sports, had been set.  Every morning of the PGA Tour officials dedicate the 8:46 am tee time to a minute of silence to “amplify the voices and efforts underway to end system issue of racial and social injustices impacting our country”. NASCAR driver Bubba Wallace raced a car with a </span><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">Black Lives Matter</span></i><span style="font-weight: 400;"> paint scheme. The hood and rear bumper presenting a painting of a black and white hand clasped with the saying “compassion, love, understanding.”  </span></p>
<p><strong>“Listening and learning. Educating ourselves. So people will look up what this hashtag means. And hopefully, get a better understanding.” Says Wallace, the first Black driver in the Cup Series since 1971.</strong></p>
<p class="align-center"><span style="text-decoration: underline;"><strong>Soccer</strong></span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Soccer was one of the first major sports to return since the coronavirus crisis. German Bundesliga became the first league to return on May, 16. Followed by Spain’s La Liga on June 11 and English Premier Leauge on June 17. All returning as a continuation of the season before the coronavirus.  Major League Soccer returned in North America as a new tournament cup-style competition on July 8. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">All returning leagues had no fans and social distancing among the bench players was enforced.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Watching top-level footballers play with almost complete silence rather than the passionate roar of the crowd is an odd adjustment for many, but it’s still soccer. </span></p>
<blockquote>
<p><strong>“It’s strange and unfamiliar, it makes your heart bleed,” Borussia Dortmund’s sporting director Micheal Zorc said after the first game of the Bundesliga kicked off.</strong></p>
</blockquote>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The </span><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">Black Lives Matter</span></i><span style="font-weight: 400;"> movements’ solidarity proves to not only be within the United States as its global implications are seen with the restart of these various soccer leagues. </span><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">Black Lives Matter</span></i><span style="font-weight: 400;"> support dominates the Premier League start, as all 20 teams wear “Black Lives Matter” on the backs of their shirts, replacing their names, for the first 12 matches. Even more powerful of an image, at the start of each match, following the first whistle, all players on the field simultaneously take a knee to send a clear message that the league stands as one in the fight against racism and inequality. This powerful sentiment doesn’t stop within England. Support for BLM is also seen within Germany’s Bundesliga. </span></p>
<p class="align-center"><span style="text-decoration: underline;"><strong>Basketball </strong></span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The National Basketball Association is set to return on July 30. All games will be played at the ESPN Wide World of Sports complex in Orlando, Florida.</span><strong> </strong></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Similar to soccer, fans will not be allowed to attend any of the games and social distancing rules will be strict. A 113-page health-and-safety document details everything from proper ways to disinfect the basketballs used in individual workouts to the protocol set once teams arrive in Orlando.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Many players in the NBA have been vocal about the importance of racial equality and social justice being a central part of the NBA and WNBA’s return. The National Basketball Players Association is planning to paint “Black Lives Matter” on the court inside both sidelines of all three Orlando arenas. President of the NBA Player’s Union, Chris Paul, told ESPN that the league and union were collaborating to allow players to replace the names with personalized messages linked to social justice on the backs of their jersey’s. </span></p>
<p class="align-center"><strong><span style="text-decoration: underline;">Takeaway</span></strong></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">With the new protocol concerning the coronavirus being implemented with the return of sports, it is proven that they are not looking the same way they did before the pandemic. Yes, they’re back but adjustments have been made to harmonize with the state of the world. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Similarly, the sports world’s involvement and connection to social change are just as significant. As a viewer and supporter of these powerful sports teams and leagues, I have their attention and respect. Not only for me but for millions of other individuals like me, these athletes are role models. The usage of this power that athletes and sports organizations have on society is meaningful and necessary.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;"> Especially in these times of confusion and adversity. Now we are understanding that sports are more than just entertainment. Sports leagues, teams, and athletes have platforms with the power to invoke positive change and discussion. All things considered, I believe this is why something as simple as the replacement of an athlete’s name to the phrase “Black Lives Matter” onto their jerseys, speaks volumes. And can later pave the way for deeper underlying issues, for example, the lack of black coaching or directors in many sports leagues.</span></p>
<hr>
<p class="align-center"><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">Citations</span></i></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Creditor, Avi. “Details of Premier League's Return Come Further Into Focus.” </span><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">Sports Illustrated</span></i><span style="font-weight: 400;">, 4 June 2020, </span><a href="http://www.si.com/soccer/2020/06/04/premier-league-return-fixtures-substitute-rules-details"><span style="font-weight: 400;">www.si.com/soccer/2020/06/04/premier-league-return-fixtures-substitute-rules-details</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;"> </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Blumenthal, E., 2020. NBA Restart: Everything You Need To Know About Basketball's 2020 Return. CNET. Available at: </span><a href="https://www.cnet.com/news/nba-restart-everything-you-need-to-know-about-basketballs-2020-return/"><span style="font-weight: 400;">https://www.cnet.com/news/nba-restart-everything-you-need-to-know-about-basketballs-2020-return/</span></a></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Games, &amp;., League, N., Sports, O., BB, R., FB, R., Olympics, S. and Games, X., 2020. Sources: NBA Plans 'Black Lives Matter' On Courts. ESPN.com. Available at: </span><a href="https://www.espn.com/nba/story/_/id/29384944/nba-plans-paint-black-lives-matter-courts-orlando"><span style="font-weight: 400;">https://www.espn.com/nba/story/_/id/29384944/nba-plans-paint-black-lives-matter-courts-orlando</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;"> </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Golf Channel. 2020. After Moment Of Silence, PGA Tour Knows It Can't Stay Silent On Race. Available at: </span><a href="https://www.golfchannel.com/news/after-moment-silence-pga-tour-knows-it-cant-stay-silent-race"><span style="font-weight: 400;">https://www.golfchannel.com/news/after-moment-silence-pga-tour-knows-it-cant-stay-silent-race</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;"> </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Amir Vera and Steve Almasy, C., 2020. NASCAR's Bubba Wallace Will Have Black Lives Matter Paint Scheme On Car At Martinsville Speedway Race. CNN. Available at: </span><a href="https://www.cnn.com/2020/06/09/us/bubba-wallace-confederate-flag-trnd/index.html"><span style="font-weight: 400;">https://www.cnn.com/2020/06/09/us/bubba-wallace-confederate-flag-trnd/index.html</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;"> </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">ESPN.com. 2020. Sources: NBA Plans 'Black Lives Matter' On Courts. [online] Available at: </span><a href="https://www.espn.com/nba/story/_/id/29384944/nba-plans-paint-black-lives-matter-courts-orland"><span style="font-weight: 400;">https://www.espn.com/nba/story/_/id/29384944/nba-plans-paint-black-lives-matter-courts-orland</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;"> </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Wbur.org. 2020. Athletes Take A Leading Role In Black Lives Matter Protests. Available at: </span><a href="https://www.wbur.org/onlyagame/2020/06/05/black-lives-matter-protests-ken-shropshire"><span style="font-weight: 400;">https://www.wbur.org/onlyagame/2020/06/05/black-lives-matter-protests-ken-shropshire</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;"> </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Liew, J., 2020. Black Lives Matter Has Exposed Sport's Underlying Failure To Deal With Racism | Jonathan Liew. the Guardian. Available at: </span><a href="https://www.theguardian.com/sport/2020/jun/13/black-lives-matter-sports-underlying-failure-racism"><span style="font-weight: 400;">https://www.theguardian.com/sport/2020/jun/13/black-lives-matter-sports-underlying-failure-racism</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;"> </span></p>
<p><br><br><br><br><br><br><br><br><br><br></p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Mental Health: Stigmatized</title>
        <author>
            <name>Ishan Vepa</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://blog.thegenz.org/mental-health-stigmatized.html"/>
        <id>https://blog.thegenz.org/mental-health-stigmatized.html</id>
            <category term="#youth"/>
            <category term="#society"/>
            <category term="#mentalhealth"/>
            <category term="#health"/>
            <category term="#advocacy"/>

        <updated>2020-07-30T18:19:22-04:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://blog.thegenz.org/media/posts/24/Mental-Health-Rohan-Thapliyal.jpg" alt="Graphic of various mental conditions." />
                    The topic of mental health in today's society has been stigmatized for decades: no one is open to talk about it. You or someone you know may have a mental disorder, and the person affected might not even know due to how the media has&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <img src="https://blog.thegenz.org/media/posts/24/Mental-Health-Rohan-Thapliyal.jpg" alt="Graphic of various mental conditions." />
                <p class="align-center msg msg--highlight "><em><strong>The topic of mental health in today's society has been stigmatized for decades: no one is open to talk about it.</strong></em></p>
<hr>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">You or someone you know may have a mental disorder, and the person affected might not even know due to how the media has portrayed mental health. The news has cast a shadow over mental health, speaking of crimes committed and murders caused by mental illnesses, but the truth of the matter is that 50 percent of all people on Earth will be diagnosed with a mental illness/disorder in their lifetimes, not including the millions of non-documented cases or the millions of people not actually aware that they may actually have a mental disorder at all. These kinds of diseases plague our day to day lives, and most people never even notice them.</span></p>
<p><strong>What is Mental Health?</strong></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The Centers for Disease Control describes mental health like this: “Our emotional, psychological, and social wellbeing.” If that sounds like a very large portion of our lives, that’s because it is. Our mental health is everything that goes on in our minds, whether it be our daily emotions or a deep-rooted state of depression. Our minds are what keep us conscious and alive, so it is important to address mental illnesses no matter how hard it may be to speak about the topic.</span></p>
<p><strong>Depression and Anxiety.</strong></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Perhaps one of our most stigmatized mental disorders, depression is a disorder that millions of people must endure every year. Anxiety, on the other hand, has improved in how it has been addressed in the general public, now it being fairly easy to self-diagnose and is easy to receive treatment for. These two may seem very different, but they are deeply intertwined with each other. Almost half of those affected by depression also are also diagnosed with an anxiety disorder as stated by The Anxiety and Depression Association of America. </span></p>
<p><strong>Warning Factors of Mental Disorders.</strong></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Here are some causes of mental disorders. Keep in mind if you fall into one of these categories, it just means you have a higher probability of being affected by a mental illness, not that you are.</span></p>
<ul>
<li style="font-weight: 400;"><span style="font-weight: 400;">Trauma from previous events, possibly of abuse</span></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400;"><span style="font-weight: 400;">Family members being affected</span></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400;"><span style="font-weight: 400;">Experience with serious medical conditions</span></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400;"><span style="font-weight: 400;">The feeling of loneliness, even if not alone</span></li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Symptoms.</strong></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Here are a few common symptoms of mental illnesses. If you notice that you fit into one or more of these, please contact your healthcare provider to get diagnosed and treated. Remember, mental health isn’t a joke, mental illnesses can very easily cause death.</span></p>
<ul>
<li style="font-weight: 400;"><span style="font-weight: 400;">Lack of the ability to concentrate</span></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400;"><span style="font-weight: 400;">Extreme feelings of guilt, anger, sadness, etc.</span></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400;"><span style="font-weight: 400;">Suicidal thinking</span></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400;"><span style="font-weight: 400;">Changes in eating habits</span></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400;"><span style="font-weight: 400;">Low energy</span></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400;"><span style="font-weight: 400;">Large mood-swings</span></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400;"><span style="font-weight: 400;">Trouble relating to people</span></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400;"><span style="font-weight: 400;">Constant paranoia </span></li>
</ul>
<p><strong>In Conclusion...</strong></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">If you notice that someone you know may have a mental disorder based upon the warning signs and symptoms described above, don’t hesitate to speak with them about it. If they don’t, it’s better safe than sorry. If they do, you may have saved a life. Also, take a look at the sources listed below for more information on depression, anxiety, and mental health in general.</span></p>
<ul>
<li style="font-weight: 400;"><a href="https://adaa.org/about-adaa/press-room/facts-statistics"><span style="font-weight: 400;">Adaa.org</span></a></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400;"><a href="https://www.cdc.gov/mentalhealth/learn/index.htm"><span style="font-weight: 400;">cdc.gov</span></a></li>
</ul>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>The fight to END the Global Water Crisis</title>
        <author>
            <name>Ishan Vepa</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://blog.thegenz.org/the-fight-to-end-the-global-water-crisis.html"/>
        <id>https://blog.thegenz.org/the-fight-to-end-the-global-water-crisis.html</id>
            <category term="#science"/>
            <category term="#environment"/>
            <category term="#energy"/>
            <category term="#climate"/>

        <updated>2020-07-30T18:19:22-04:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://blog.thegenz.org/media/posts/23/Kid_enjoying_with_clean_water-Tia-Guay.jpg" alt="Kid enjoying access to water." />
                    Millions of people in Africa and all over the world do not have access to clean, safe, drinking water. They have to walk up to 3 miles just to drink water that is contaminated with animal feces, bugs, dirt, and much more. What is the&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <img src="https://blog.thegenz.org/media/posts/23/Kid_enjoying_with_clean_water-Tia-Guay.jpg" alt="Kid enjoying access to water." />
                <p class="msg msg--highlight "><em><span style="font-weight: 400;"><strong>Millions of people in Africa and all over the world do not have access to clean, safe, drinking water. They have to walk up to 3 miles just to drink water that is contaminated with animal feces, bugs, dirt, and much more.</strong> </span></em></p>
<hr>
<p><strong><i>What is the Global Water Crisis:</i></strong></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Did you know that 663 million people on this planet lack access to safe drinking water? This number is growing as water becomes more scarce around the world. Many people know that there is a shortage of water in places like Africa. However, they do not understand the effects of the Global Water Crisis and the extent of how bad it actually is. You might be wondering...well how is dirty water really that bad? The water that people in Africa have to drink is not only filled with dirt and other natural products, but it contains a lot of bacteria. This bacteria causes many different waterborne illnesses. Every 21 Seconds, a child dies from a water-related illness. In Africa, the most common type of illness is HIV and AIDS. This disease is spread through dirty water and is passed around the area.</span></p>
<p><strong><i>What are the Effects of Not Having Clean Water:</i></strong></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Aside from getting many different waterborne diseases like HIV/AIDS, there are many effects. For instance, many kids have to miss school to help their families get water. As previously stated, the average distance that many families walk to get water is 3.75 miles. This takes a long time, and in many families, the kids and the women are the ones that have to take this long journey. When a 5-gallon jerrycan gets filled with water, it weighs about 44 pounds. Women and kids have to carry that jerrycan back and forth from the muddy lake water. The effects of drinking contaminated water not only hurt your health, but it also affects your lifestyle and mental well-being. Kids are not able to play or talk to other kids because they are too busy getting water for their family and friends. </span></p>
<p><strong><i>How Can You Help:</i></strong></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">There are many ways to help this cause and END the Global Water Crisis. One of the best ways to help is to spread awareness. By spreading awareness, more people will know about the cause and feel more inclined to donate! You can spread awareness by posting on social media explaining what the problem is and how they can help. You can also share about the Global Water Crisis with friends and family members and convince them to donate. Another good way to help this issue is to set up an online fundraising page where people can donate. You can share this with people on social media or let them know by talking about it in person. Especially, in today’s world, everything is digital. Setting up an online platform makes it easy for people to donate! The last and one of the most effective ways to help END the Global Water Crisis is to host a fundraiser at your school, church, or another organization in your community. A fundraiser is one of the best ways to help this issue because it brings awareness and forces people to donate. Also, a fundraiser is super fun! They can range anywhere from a pasta dinner to a football game, it’s up to you! The most important thing is that you take action on this cause and do your part to put the global water crisis into the</span></p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Water Conservation and What We Can Do to Help</title>
        <author>
            <name>Ishan Vepa</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://blog.thegenz.org/water-conservation-and-what-we-can-do-to-help.html"/>
        <id>https://blog.thegenz.org/water-conservation-and-what-we-can-do-to-help.html</id>
            <category term="#science"/>
            <category term="#infrastructure"/>
            <category term="#environment"/>

        <updated>2020-07-30T18:19:22-04:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://blog.thegenz.org/media/posts/22/waterpic-Anika-Mathur.jpeg" alt="Aerial Photo of Water Waves" />
                    Water is an important and necessary part of everyday life. 60% of the human body is made up of water and 71% of the Earth’s surface consists of water as well, according to the USGS. With such an important resource, it is surprising that many&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <img src="https://blog.thegenz.org/media/posts/22/waterpic-Anika-Mathur.jpeg" alt="Aerial Photo of Water Waves" />
                <p class="msg msg--highlight  align-center"><strong>Water is an important and necessary part of everyday life. 60% of the human body is made up of water and 71% of the Earth’s surface consists of water as well, according to the USGS. With such an important resource, it is surprising that many people do not know that fresh water is not a renewable source.</strong></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">You may be thinking, ‘How can water not be renewable? After all, the water cycle is a repeated process, so therefore water must be a renewable resource.’ Even though there is a water cycle, the use of fresh water should be considered a nonrenewable resource. Even though so much of the Earth’s surface is made up of water, only 3% is fresh water, according to National Geographic. And of that 3%, only 1% can be used as drinking water (the other 2% is frozen) according to Sorcatic.org. The rest is saltwater, which can’t be used in our daily life. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Saltwater can be purified into freshwater, however, it does take energy. One way is through a process called reverse osmosis. This process takes saltwater and forces it through a permeable membrane, which removes the larger particles of unwanted material and leaves behind clean water. However, this process does take energy, as stated previously, which means that the process can’t be used as evidence for freshwater being renewable.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Some areas don’t even have access to freshwater locally, so it takes a lot of energy to get it to them. Many places around the world are not near freshwater naturally, which would mean that water would have to be transported there, which contributes to the increasing usage of energy throughout the world.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">When reading these statistics, you may wonder why you should worry about it. It’s not like what you do has any control over how much water is available in the world, right? Well, you do have a lot of control over how you use your water. Americans use around 80 to 100 gallons of water a day (USGS). Imagine the amount of water you can save once you become aware of the number of gallons you use daily! Here are some tips on how you can save water in your day to day life right now!</span></p>
<ul>
<li style="font-weight: 400;"><strong>Taking shorter showers: </strong><span style="font-weight: 400;">Did you know that a 20-minute shower uses around 50 gallons (the Sacramento Bees)? Instead of taking a long shower, try to shorten the amount of time you are showering for!</span></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400;"><strong>Turn off the water when brushing:</strong><span style="font-weight: 400;"> While you are brushing your teeth, you don’t need to have the faucet running. This eliminates the wastage of water when you aren’t even using it! This tip saves around 4 gallons of water each time you brush your teeth (the San Diego Union-Tribune)!</span></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400;"><strong>Don’t use your toilet to throw away tissues: </strong><span style="font-weight: 400;">Using the toilet to throw away tissues and other types of garbage wastes around 5 to 7 gallons of water (the City of Santa Cruz). Instead, use a trash can, which does not need water to function!</span></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400;"><strong>Use your laundry machine when full:</strong><span style="font-weight: 400;"> These appliances use a ton of water! The laundry machine uses 23 gallons, according to the water footprint calculator. By using them when they are full, you are saving water by not using the machines in excess.</span></li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">There are also other ways you can save water! One way freshwater is lost is through runoff. Runoff harms the environment by increasing the amount of pollution in water systems (and therefore decreasing the amount of fresh water available). Runoff carries what is on the road while it is raining, for example, fertilizers and litter. It then carries these things into the sewer drains and other large bodies of water. The following ideas are ways you can prevent runoff and that you may need an adult before doing:</span></p>
<ul>
<li style="font-weight: 400;"><strong>Rain Garden: </strong><span style="font-weight: 400;">A rain garden is part of a landscape and is put in areas where water accumulates. This helps prevent runoff (when rainwater goes into sewer drains), helping the environment.</span></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400;"><strong>Green Roof:</strong><span style="font-weight: 400;"> A green roof is when the roof of a building is covered with plants. This helps collect rainwater that usually accumulates on the roofs of buildings.</span></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400;"><strong>Permeable Pavement: </strong><span style="font-weight: 400;">Permeable pavement is a type of pavement that absorbs rainwater, instead of allowing it to go into the sewer drains. This also helps prevent runoff.</span></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400;"><strong>Rain Barrel: </strong><span style="font-weight: 400;">A rain barrel helps collect rainwater, which allows you to use it for other uses, such as watering gardens!</span></li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">If you and the people around you use these tips to conserve the fresh water on Earth, you would be saving an abundance of water. This would help save the amount of water that is left for future generations too!</span></p>
<p><br><br><br></p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
</feed>
