<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <title>The Generation Z Blog</title>
    <link href="https://blog.thegenz.org/feed.xml" rel="self" />
    <link href="https://blog.thegenz.org" />
    <updated>1969-12-31T19:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <author>
        <name>Ishan Vepa</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://blog.thegenz.org</id>

    <entry>
        <title>Should Schools Reopen</title>
        <author>
            <name>Ishan Vepa</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://blog.thegenz.org/should-schools-reopen.html"/>
        <id>https://blog.thegenz.org/should-schools-reopen.html</id>
            <category term="#education"/>
            <category term="#covid19"/>
            <category term="#coronavirus"/>

        <updated>2020-09-25T17:33:40-04:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://blog.thegenz.org/media/posts/50/24F482A3-B132-49A9-87F2-B516DFFC1C78-Ryan-Shankar.jpeg" alt="Covid-19 classroom integration." />
                    With summer ending schools have started to re-open, but is that the right move many wonder. I strongly believe that reopening schools is the worst thing that could happen currently. Because there is still a raging pandemic which the world, let alone the U.S has&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <img src="https://blog.thegenz.org/media/posts/50/24F482A3-B132-49A9-87F2-B516DFFC1C78-Ryan-Shankar.jpeg" alt="Covid-19 classroom integration." />
                <p class="align-center msg msg--highlight "><em><strong>With summer ending schools have started to re-open, but is that the right move many wonder. I strongly believe that reopening schools is the worst thing that could happen currently. Because there is still a raging pandemic which the world, let alone the U.S has an answer for. </strong></em></p>
<p class="align-center"><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">What effect has schools reopening had on students</span></i></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;"> </span><span style="font-weight: 400;">Schools reopening have put many students at risk of catching the virus. In the last two weeks of July over 97,000 covid cases were students, schools were not even open. If the virus is spreading this fast for students when out of school, I don't want to imagine how bad it will be when all schools reopen. But many schools have set up an online option that will provide distance learning to students which will reduce a good chunk of those potential cases but not enough. Many of the schools in the Southern states are reopening and those states have seen a surge in cases. Georgia has had over 40,000 new cases ever since schools opened. Their cases per day went from 2,000 a day to 4,000 a day. If all states reopened schools, their cases would obviously rise and call for the entire state to be shut down again. That's why I believe that online school, until the amount of cases decreases massively, is how schools should be reopening. </span></p>
<p class="align-center"><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">Why do students and parents not want online school?</span></i></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Many students dislike online learning, because it is easier for many to learn in person. I can agree with this because when schools did close in the spring it was harder keeping a routine and learning new concepts from home. I feel like even though it is harder to learn from home it will be beneficial to the country as there the amount of cases that could happen would be prevented. Many believe that saving lives is worth doing online school, no matter how hard it may be for some students. A major flaw with online education is not everyone has access to it. Many organizations are trying like internet providers are trying to help students who don't have access by providing WiFi and other technology they need. Also it is a lot harder for younger students to learn from a at home setting as they have shorter attention spans and need more help learning topics. But teachers and parents are trying their best to help them. Schools have served as a daycare for many parents and with online school that would not be possible, not every parent can work from home and their child would have to be sent to a daycare which will cost them extra. The government is trying to provide financial support but I fear that it will not be enough to help these families who are struggling during these times. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Overall schools reopening wouldn’t help anybody as after a week or two they would have to close again because of the virus. If a state decides to let schools open for in person learning there should be some requirements, such as less students, masks, social distancing and daily cleaning of the school. Sadly that's not what we have seen in Georgia and many other states that have reopened schools, as many students aren't wearing masks or social distancing. CNN reported on this issue but schools in Georgia have not changed anything. One school even suspended the student who took the photo exposing the school. I don’t think any public place such as schools can open safely without there being an outbreak and for those reasons, I believe schools shouldn’t have in person learning until numbers are under control.</span></p>
<hr>
<p class="align-center"><em>Citations</em></p>
<p>Turner, Cory. “At Least 97,000 Children Tested Positive For Coronavirus In Last 2 Weeks Of July.” <i>NPR</i>, NPR, 11 Aug. 2020, <a href="http://www.npr.org/sections/coronavirus-live-updates/2020/08/11/900861372/at-least-97-000-children-tested-positive-for-coronavirus-in-last-2-weeks-of-july">www.npr.org/sections/coronavirus-live-updates/2020/08/11/900861372/at-least-97-000-children-tested-positive-for-coronavirus-in-last-2-weeks-of-july</a>.</p>
<p>Peiser, Jaclyn. “A Georgia District Returned to School Last Week. More than 900 Students and Staff Are Now Quarantined.” <i>The Washington Post</i>, WP Company, 12 Aug. 2020, <a href="http://www.washingtonpost.com/nation/2020/08/12/school-coronavirus-outbreak-georgia-quarantine/">www.washingtonpost.com/nation/2020/08/12/school-coronavirus-outbreak-georgia-quarantine/</a>.</p>
<p>Andone, Dakin. “Georgia School Seen in Photo of a Crowded Hallway Will Briefly Move to Online Learning after Reporting 9 Cases of Covid-19.” <i>CNN</i>, Cable News Network, 10 Aug. 2020, <a href="http://www.cnn.com/2020/08/09/us/north-paulding-high-school-covid-19-cases/index.html">www.cnn.com/2020/08/09/us/north-paulding-high-school-covid-19-cases/index.html</a>.</p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Google’s COVID-19 Alert</span></p>
<p> </p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Our Unconscious Biases: The Hidden Racial Prejudice Within us All</title>
        <author>
            <name>Ishan Vepa</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://blog.thegenz.org/our-unconscious-biases-the-hidden-racial-prejudice-within-us-all.html"/>
        <id>https://blog.thegenz.org/our-unconscious-biases-the-hidden-racial-prejudice-within-us-all.html</id>
            <category term="#society"/>
            <category term="#inequality"/>
            <category term="#generations"/>
            <category term="#gap"/>
            <category term="#community"/>
            <category term="#blacklivesmatter"/>

        <updated>2020-09-25T17:33:40-04:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://blog.thegenz.org/media/posts/48/unconscious-bias-pic-Generation-Z-Media.png" alt="Unconscious Biases in the Workplace graphic." />
                    “Are Emily and Greg More Employable Than Lakisha and Jamal?” The American Economic Institute conducted this study in order to understand labor market discrimination. Fictitious resumes were sent to over 1300 employment ads in Boston and Chicago newspapers. The resumes were randomly assigned either a&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <img src="https://blog.thegenz.org/media/posts/48/unconscious-bias-pic-Generation-Z-Media.png" alt="Unconscious Biases in the Workplace graphic." />
                <p class="msg msg--highlight  align-center"><em><strong>“Are Emily and Greg More Employable Than Lakisha and Jamal?” </strong></em></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The American Economic Institute conducted this study in order to understand labor market discrimination. Fictitious resumes were sent to over 1300 employment ads in Boston and Chicago newspapers. The resumes were randomly assigned either a white-sounding name (Emily Walsh or Greg Baker) or an African American sounding name (Lakisha Washington or Jamal Jones). The researches also varied the quality of the resumes, giving two higher quality and two-lower-quality resumes to each employer for a total of nearly 5000 resumes covering a vast array of jobs within the fields of sales and administrative support and customer services.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Researchers found that white-sounding names had a 9.65% chance of receiving a callback, whereas African American sounding names had a 6.45% chance. Regarding quality, higher-quality resumes did receive more callbacks, as expected, but for African Americans, the difference was only a 0.51% improvement. A number that researchers deemed statistically insignificant, essentially meaning that African American applicants experienced no gain from a higher quality resume.   </span><span style="font-weight: 400;">                     </span></p>
<figure class="align-center"><span style="font-weight: 400;">                                                                            </span>                                                                                                <img loading="lazy"  src="https://miro.medium.com/max/900/1*R1j1tQkSR8mdQls7G3sjZQ.jpeg" data-is-external-image="true"  alt="Are Emily and Greg more Employable than Lakisha and Jamal? | by Brooke C |  Medium" width="415" height="509"></figure>
<p> </p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The researchers were in fact able to conclude that the employers were being discriminatory towards the African Americans. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">This experiment is just one application of our implicit, unconscious racial biases creating unfair hurdles and impeding access to opportunity. Something that every American has. Racial biases are something that I, a person of color, am not free of.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Why use the word biases, rather than just plain and simple, racism? </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The word racism has a severe negative connotation that many view as negative thoughts, negative feelings, and hatred towards a group of people. Since the passing of legislation during the civil rights era making this immoral and illegal, racism has become more subtle. These negative feelings embedded within a race are still there but many aren’t aware of them. And rather than hatred, it’s more like avoidance and discomfort. That’s where the use of the words “unconscious, implicit, racial biases” comes from.</span></p>
<p class="align-center"><strong>Biases at Work</strong></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">John Dovidio, professor of psychology and public health at Yale University, further explores this. “Most of us want to be good people. Prejudice is bad and when we think about it, we always do the right thing. But if something is unconscious, you don’t know you have it. It’s that simple. They’re like having habits of mind that you’ve grown up with” he says in an interview with the American Psychological Association</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Many agree that we cannot get rid of this inherent bias in our brains. On the contrary, it’s something we manage. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">But the </span><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">Are Emily and Greg More Employable Than Lakisha and Jamal experiment </span></i><span style="font-weight: 400;">has proved that these subtle biases are having greater adverse effects when being put into application. This is evident not only in the labor market but within critical life domains such as housing, education, health, and criminal justice. Our implicit biases present themselves in the form of microaggressions (indirect, subtle, or even unintentional acts of discrimination against members of a marginalized group), stereotyping, avoidance, or in the worst-case scenario, through our decision making, for example with police. All creating barriers that impede opportunity. Essentially, making the need to manage our biases on an individual level all the more vital and urgent. </span></p>
<p class="align-center"><strong>How can we manage our racial biases?</strong></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">One important strategy to understand our biases is the involvement of racial and ethnic diversity in conversations and discussions. Like mentioned before, racism has shifted from hatred to now avoidance, discomfort, and bias. The problem with avoiding a group of people is that allows you to maintain the stereotypes that you have of that group. Assumptions and expectations about the roles they should play all lead to unfair judgments. Reversely, if you continue to interact with those members you no longer think about them as members of a group. You think about them as individuals. </span></p>
<p><strong>“You haven’t really gotten rid of the implicit bias, but you’ve now been able to fine-tune and dial-up a broader array of repertoire of being able to interact with people and understand them,” says Divido.</strong></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">More importantly, dealing with bias is a personal operation. Situations, mostly vulnerable, stress ones, around us affect when our racial biases come into play. In situations where we feel threatened or fearful we are more likely to act on our biases. Jenifer Eberhardt, professor of psychology at Stanford University, explains that “by interrogating ourselves and slowing ourselves down... just being aware when we’re beginning to make stereotypic associations.” This allows you to move your thinking from the primitive, reactive parts of the brain to the more reflective levels.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Black people convicted of capital offenses facing the death penalty at higher rates than white people. Teachers quick to see “patterns” of bad behavior in black children. Police officers shooting unarmed black men. All are outcomes of our biases that not only explore the nature of America but are ideas that Eberhardt has studied. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Eberhardt agrees that increased diversity in neighborhoods, workplaces, and schools is vital. But the implementation of anti-bias training in many institutions is where we can begin to deal with our bias in the workplace. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">One example of this is within the Oakland Police Department. By changing its foot pursuit policy, rather than chase a suspect into a blind alley, officers are encouraged to call for backup, set a perimeter, and make a plan. This gives officers more distance on the situation, therefore, allowing them to take hold of their decision making. This is where Eberhardt’s idea of “interrogating ourselves and slowing ourselves down” comes into play. Even without knowing the roots of the behavior, as a result, the change in policy positively affected officer injuries and officer-involved shootings. Oakland used to have eight to nine officer-involved shootings every single year, after changing policy, they had eight officer-involved shootings across five years.  </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The glimpses of the anti-bias training being introduced within the workforce are proving to be effective. But it doesn’t stop there. Imagine if these techniques were enforced within our education or criminal justice systems. Eberhardt agrees with the ending of her book, </span><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">Biased: Uncovering the Hidden Prejudice That Shapes What We See, Think, and Do</span></i><span style="font-weight: 400;"> “There is hope in the sheer act of reflection. This is where the power lies and how the process starts.”</span></p>
<p class="align-center"><strong>As for all of us, whether at work or not, think twice before making an association or acting upon a stereotype considering now we know its impacts in creating and reinforcing racialized barriers to opportunity.</strong></p>
<hr>
<p class="align-center"><em><span style="font-weight: 400;">Citations</span></em></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Bertrand, M., and Mullainathan, S., 2020. </span><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">Are Emily And Greg More Employable Than Lakisha And Jamal? A Field Experiment On Labor Market Discrimination</span></i><span style="font-weight: 400;">. Uh.edu. </span><a href="https://www.uh.edu/~adkugler/Bertrand&amp;Mullainathan.pdf"><span style="font-weight: 400;">https://www.uh.edu/~adkugler/Bertrand&amp;Mullainathan.pdf</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;"> </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Chang, A., 2020. </span><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">Can We Overcome Racial Bias? 'Biased' Author Says To Start By Acknowledging It</span></i><span style="font-weight: 400;">.  Npr.org. </span><a href="https://www.npr.org/2019/03/28/705113639/can-we-overcome-racial-bias-biased-author-says-to-start-by-acknowledging-it"><span style="font-weight: 400;">https://www.npr.org/2019/03/28/705113639/can-we-overcome-racial-bias-biased-author-says-to-start-by-acknowledging-it</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;"> </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Hamilton, A., 2020. </span><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">Speaking Of Psychology: Understanding Your Racial Biases</span></i><span style="font-weight: 400;">. Apa.org.</span><a href="https://www.apa.org/research/action/speaking-of-psychology/understanding-biases"><span style="font-weight: 400;">https://www.apa.org/research/action/speaking-of-psychology/understanding-biases</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;">  </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Racial Equity Tools.org. 2020. </span><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">Communicating • Racial Equity Tools</span></i><span style="font-weight: 400;">. Available at: </span><a href="https://www.racialequitytools.org/act/communicating/implicit-bias"><span style="font-weight: 400;">https://www.racialequitytools.org/act/communicating/implicit-bias</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;"> </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Kirwan Institute.osu.edu. 2020. </span><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">Understanding Implicit Bias</span></i><span style="font-weight: 400;">. Available at: </span><a href="http://kirwaninstitute.osu.edu/research/understanding-implicit-bias/"><span style="font-weight: 400;">http://kirwaninstitute.osu.edu/research/understanding-implicit-bias/</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;"> </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Starr, D., 2020. Meet The Psychologist Exploring Unconscious Bias—And Its Tragic Consequences For Society. Science | AAAS. </span><a href="https://www.sciencemag.org/news/2020/03/meet-psychologist-exploring-unconscious-bias-and-its-tragic-consequences-society"><span style="font-weight: 400;">https://www.sciencemag.org/news/2020/03/meet-psychologist-exploring-unconscious-bias-and-its-tragic-consequences-society</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;"> </span></p>
<p><br><br><br><br><br><br><br><br><br><br><br><br><br><br></p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>The Woman Behind NASA&#x27;s Headquarters</title>
        <author>
            <name>Ishan Vepa</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://blog.thegenz.org/the-woman-behind-nasas-headquarters.html"/>
        <id>https://blog.thegenz.org/the-woman-behind-nasas-headquarters.html</id>
            <category term="#science"/>

        <updated>2020-09-25T17:33:40-04:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://blog.thegenz.org/media/posts/47/Mary-Jackson-Abigail-Mullins.jpg" alt="Depiction of Mary Jackson, Aeronautical Engineer" />
                    It has taken Mary Jackson many years to become a familiar name. Even though Jackson was NASA’s first African American female engineer, she was relatively unknown until the book Hidden Figures: The American Dream and the Untold Story of the Black Women Who Helped Win&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <img src="https://blog.thegenz.org/media/posts/47/Mary-Jackson-Abigail-Mullins.jpg" alt="Depiction of Mary Jackson, Aeronautical Engineer" />
                <p><span style="font-weight: 400;">It has taken Mary Jackson many years to become a familiar name. Even though Jackson was NASA’s first African American female engineer, she was relatively unknown until the book </span><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">Hidden Figures: The American Dream and the Untold Story of the Black Women Who Helped Win the Space Race</span></i><span style="font-weight: 400;"> was released in 2016 and a movie of same name came out later that year. Her name may sound especially familiar now as recently, NASA has renamed its Headquarters in Washington DC after her. This honor is well deserved after years of being an unknown “hidden figure.”</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Born in Hampton, Virginia in 1921, Mary Winston graduated from George P. Phenix Training School in 1937 with high honors before receiving a dual bachelor’s degree in math and physical sciences from Hampton Institute (now Hampton University) 5 years later. Before her work at NASA, she had a variety of other jobs. She was a math teacher in Maryland for a year, she was a bookkeeper at her alma mater, she was a mother to her children after marrying Levi Jackson, and she worked as a US Army secretary in the now decommissioned Fort Monroe military base. Finally, in 1951, she began working for the National Advisory Committee on Aeronautics, a predecessor of what would become NASA.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Initially, she started as a research mathematician as one of the “human computers” in the West Area Computing Unit, which worked to provide data that helped the US space program become more successful. Her supervisor was fellow “Hidden Figure” Dorothy Vaugan. In 1953 she moved to the Compressibility Research division of NACA where she conducted experiments with a supersonic pressure tunnel.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Since it was the 1950s, Jackson faced discrimination as segregation was still legal in her Virginia workplace. Her West Area Computing Unit primarily consisted of African American women. While whites got to go to the cafeteria and order and eat their food from there, blacks had to ask an attendant for their food and had to sit at their desks, which Jackson considered an “indignity.” Bathrooms were also segregated. Fed up with the mistreatment, Jackson considered resigning, but Kazimierz Czarnecki, an engineer, encouraged her to stay and work for him. She agreed, and he told her to take engineering classes so she could have a better chance of being promoted to an engineer.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Not all was smooth sailing. Jackson had to get permission to attend the all white Hampton High School for engineering classes, which she eventually did get. She would go on to complete all of her courses. Finally, in 1958, her work was finally recognized as she was promoted to aeronautical engineer for the newly created NASA. She was the first and only black female engineer in an otherwise male-dominated field at the time. She worked with wind tunnels and analyzed data that came from experiments. She also authored/co-authored 12 papers over the course of her career as an engineer.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Despite her success as an engineer, Jackson was never offered management positions as she was still being discriminated against for her race and gender. Sick of this, in 1979 she took a demotion and worked as a Federal Women’s Program Manager. The work she did, however, was still extremely important. She was able to help women and minorities advance their careers at NASA. As she once did herself, she encouraged them to take extra classes so they were more likely to receive a promotion. She eventually retired in 1985 and passed away 20 years later.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Mary Jackson used her position to help the next generation of women to pursue careers in STEM by enabling them to become scientists, engineers, and mathematicians. Without her efforts, many women may have felt discouraged that they couldn’t pursue a career they wanted. It is because of her work that more women felt that they could work at places such as NASA. By breaking boundaries herself, she could also be a source of inspiration for others and prove that anybody could do what she did, regardless of their gender or race.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">NASA’s headquarters isn’t the only place to be renamed after this amazing woman. It was announced in 2018 that Jackson Elementary in Salt Lake City, Utah was renamed Mary W. Jackson Elementary School in her honor. Even though it took over 50 years to receive credit for the work she has done, it is good to see that her, and even Katherine Johnso and Dorothy Vaugan, finally receive some attention and praise that is well deserved. Even though there are plenty more women who have yet to be recognized, it’s good to see Mary Johnson finally be celebrated and honored for what she has accomplished.</span></p>
<hr>
<p class="align-center"><em><span style="font-weight: 400;">Citations</span></em></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The Editors of Encyclopedia Britannica. “Mary Jackson.” </span><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">Encyclopædia Britannica</span></i><span style="font-weight: 400;">, Encyclopædia Britannica, Inc., 9 Apr. 2020, www.britannica.com/biography/Mary-Jackson-mathematician-and-engineer.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Explained Desk. “Mary Jackson: NASA's First African American Female Aeronautical Engineer.” </span><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">The Indian Express</span></i><span style="font-weight: 400;">, 26 June 2020, indianexpress.com/article/explained/mary-jackson-nasa-6477210/.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">“Jackson, Mary.” </span><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">Encyclopædia Britannica</span></i><span style="font-weight: 400;">, Encyclopædia Britannica, www.britannica.com/biography/Mary-Jackson-mathematician-and-engineer/images-videos#/media/1/2091689/238758.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Potter, Sean, et al. “NASA Names Headquarters After 'Hidden Figure' Mary W. Jackson.” </span><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">NASA</span></i><span style="font-weight: 400;">, NASA, 24 June 2020, www.nasa.gov/press-release/nasa-names-headquarters-after-hidden-figure-mary-w-jackson.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Timmons, Greg. “Mary Jackson.” </span><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">Biography.com</span></i><span style="font-weight: 400;">, A&amp;E Networks Television, 6 Dec. 2016, </span><a href="http://www.biography.com/scientist/mary-winston-jackson"><span style="font-weight: 400;">www.biography.com/scientist/mary-winston-jackson</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;">.</span></p>
<p><br><br></p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Cut Down Deforestation</title>
        <author>
            <name>Ishan Vepa</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://blog.thegenz.org/cut-down-deforestation.html"/>
        <id>https://blog.thegenz.org/cut-down-deforestation.html</id>
            <category term="#science"/>
            <category term="#environment"/>
            <category term="#energy"/>
            <category term="#climate"/>

        <updated>2020-09-25T17:33:40-04:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://blog.thegenz.org/media/posts/46/Deforestation-Article-Photo-Alyson-Torino.jpg" alt="Deforestation present in a woodland." />
                    Let’s talk about how deforestation usually begins: forest degradation. Trees are one of the world’s most valuable resources. They are a plentiful resource that is very versatile in terms of its possible usage. They can be used for their wood, for their fruit, and for&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <img src="https://blog.thegenz.org/media/posts/46/Deforestation-Article-Photo-Alyson-Torino.jpg" alt="Deforestation present in a woodland." />
                <p class="msg msg--highlight "><strong><em>Let’s talk about how deforestation usually begins: forest degradation.</em></strong></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Trees are one of the world’s most valuable resources. They are a plentiful resource that is very versatile in terms of its possible usage. They can be used for their wood, for their fruit, and for their oxygen. We also use trees for construction, manufacturing, and fuel. However, those trees also serve a purpose besides what we use them for: they are home to other plants and animals, yet we cut them down without regard for that. Deforestation has an impact not only on us, but also on the plants and animals that live, or used to live, in those forests that have been cleared. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Forest degradation, according to the World Wildlife Fund (WWF), is when a forest has been cut down enough to still exist, but has undergone too much damage to function as normal. It is most commonly caused by illegal logging. Once one company starts to cut, it will be followed by others, quickly changing from forest degradation to deforestation. This may not seem like a very pressing issue at first, but the scale at which it is occurring is startling. According to National Geographic, between 1600 and 1870, half of Eastern North America’s forests were cut down. Additionally, 2,000 years ago, Europe was 80% forested, which has dropped to an alarming 34% today, on top of China being only 20% forested. This pushes most, if not all, of the wildlife in these areas out of their normal environments, causing endangerment to multiple species of plants and animals. The WWF says that we are losing forests at a rate of 27 soccer fields per minute, but how are we clearing these forests so fast? One lovely little technique that is being used is called slash and burn.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">You can probably guess what slash and burn is based off of the name. The trees in the desired area are cut down, and then burned into ash. The areas where this technique is used are usually tropical forests and are turned into agricultural areas, since the ash acts as a good fertilizer. However, this land is only fertile for a few years, leaving an open and dry environment where a moist and sheltered one used to be. If the deforestation wasn’t already bad enough, this makes the land vulnerable to erosion and wildfires. The remaining wildlife is once again put at risk due to these new conditions, adding more and more consequences to deforestation. There is still one more thing that I haven’t discussed that trees are notorious for: oxygen.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Trees are not the largest producers of oxygen. That title goes to all of the microscopic phytoplankton in the ocean and other bodies of water. However, every densely populated area on Earth, and by that I mean populated by both plants and animals, has an equal exchange of oxygen and carbon dioxide. In simpler terms, the so-called “Lungs of Earth” Amazon Rainforest uses up all of the oxygen it produces, leaving the other forests and phytoplankton of the world to produce the oxygen that will be used in their area. This makes the trees that we have left very important because oxygen is necessary for us to survive, and if we keep cutting them down at the current rate, the levels of oxygen and carbon dioxide in the atmosphere will become imbalanced. This leads to the much larger problem of global warming, but that is an issue for an entirely different article to cover.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">In order to help with this cause, you can buy products that have been approved by the Forest Stewardship Council (FSC). This organization ensures that the product was made with trees that were harvested within local and international laws. You can also donate to foundations like the Rainforest Alliance, who help save ecosystems at risk and fight climate change. While we are the ones who caused all of these damages with deforestation, we can also be the ones to solve it.</span></p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Why Schools should Switch Times?</title>
        <author>
            <name>Ishan Vepa</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://blog.thegenz.org/why-schools-should-switch-times.html"/>
        <id>https://blog.thegenz.org/why-schools-should-switch-times.html</id>
            <category term="#infrastructure"/>
            <category term="#education"/>

        <updated>2020-09-25T17:33:40-04:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://blog.thegenz.org/media/posts/45/pexels-dids-2675050.jpg" alt="Photo of Empty Class Room" />
                    It’s around 6:00 am in the morning and your alarm goes off. You groan and dreadingly press snooze. Ten minutes later, you force yourself to get out of bed. You get ready as if you are a zombie, but quickly at the same time because&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <img src="https://blog.thegenz.org/media/posts/45/pexels-dids-2675050.jpg" alt="Photo of Empty Class Room" />
                <p><span style="font-weight: 400;">It’s around 6:00 am in the morning and your alarm goes off. You groan and dreadingly press snooze. Ten minutes later, you force yourself to get out of bed. You get ready as if you are a zombie, but quickly at the same time because you can't be late for school. You skip breakfast, because your exhaustion makes the sound of food disgusting. You go to school, and run on little sleep even though you have two tests, and one is during first period. How can you perform well in school under these conditions?</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The</span><span style="font-weight: 400;"> times of high school and elementary schools need to be switched because of student's natural sleep cycles, the fact that high school students perform better in school at later times, and elementary school children will only need care in the afternoon, instead of in the morning and afternoon, in order to benefit students so they can be healthier, perform better at school, and put less stress on themselves and their parents.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The most sensible reason to switch the schedules of elementary schools and high schools, is because of the fact that high schoolers perform better later in the day. A research team that conducted a three year long study of eight different high schools that switched to later times, determined that there were, “Significant increases in grade point average in </span><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">all</span></i><span style="font-weight: 400;"> 1st-period core courses for </span><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">all</span></i><span style="font-weight: 400;"> semesters in </span><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">all </span></i><span style="font-weight: 400;">grades in Jackson Hole High School in Wyoming, with a start time of 8:55 a.m.” This data is from Phi Delta Kappan (The professional journal for educators), and it demonstrates how making high school start later can improve grades in all first period classes. Schools want their students to perform well, but students simply cannot when they wake up so early.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">If high school and elementary school start times switch, younger children will only require afternoon daycare. According to the article </span><span style="font-weight: 400;">"What Is the Advantage of Having School Start Early?", “</span><span style="font-weight: 400;">There are specific advantages for parents if younger grades have early start times. Starting school early may eliminate the need for morning childcare if parents are able to drop off their kids before work.” If children are not in need of childcare parents save money, and stress levels decrease regarding their let’s face it, very stressful children.  Plus, having your child only attend daycare in one part of the day is just easier for both the parents and the child.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">On the other hand, switching the times of high school and elementary school, will cause high school to end later. According to classroom.synonym.com, “school administrators cited extracurricular activities as a major reason why high school campuses would rather start earlier in the day.”</span> <span style="font-weight: 400;">Although this may be sensible at first glance, also consider that if high school students wake up later, they can go to sleep later, ultimately giving them the same amount of time to participate in clubs and sports.</span> <span style="font-weight: 400;">Also, in the study from Phi Delta Kappan that was previously mentioned, they discovered a common worry that they never had difficulty with was “Participation in after-school activities may decline.”  This exhibits how high schools can have later start times as well as participation in sports and clubs.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The final reason why high school and elementary schools should switch schedules, is because of student’s natural sleep cycles. The article,  “Elementary and High School Should Switch Times”, states, “Younger children tend to naturally wake up earlier than teenagers and adults, and they are able to have more energy early in the morning”. Then why wouldn't young kids start school earliest, if they’re already awake and have energy? Plus, teens cannot get a good amount of sleep when school starts so early. According to Phi Delta Kappan</span><span style="font-weight: 400;">, “Teens need about 9.25 hours of sleep each night, a difficult amount to obtain when the brain doesn’t enter sleep mode until about 10:45 p.m. and when students must awaken early for a school day that begins before 8:30 a.m.”  These facts clearly illustrate how it is physically impossible for a high school student to get 9 hours of sleep when they are falling asleep at 11, and waking up at around 6 for school.  The article also briefly mentions how teens’ brains remain in sleep mode until about 8 am. This means that even if teens are awake before eight, they are not really awake.  Schools need to stop encouraging sleep deprivation, for the health of their students.  </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;"> </span><span style="font-weight: 400;">In conclusion, high school and elementary schools should switch schedules because high school students do not perform well early in the morning, elementary school children would only need afternoon daycare, and high schoolers cannot get enough sleep for school.</span></p>
<p><strong> </strong><span style="font-weight: 400;">If you think about it, when was the last time you got 8 to 9 hours of sleep before school, besides in elementary school?</span></p>
<hr>
<p class="align-center"><em>Citations</em></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Anderson, Marie. "What Is the Advantage of Having School Start Early?" Synonym, https://classroom.synonym.com/advantage-having-school-start-early-4526.html. Accessed 09 July 2020.  </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Campbell, Leah. “Research Shows Early School Start Times Are Bad for Kids’ Health.” </span><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">Healthline</span></i><span style="font-weight: 400;">, 13 Aug. 2018, www.healthline.com/health-news/early-school-start-times-bad-for-kids-health#1. Accessed 09 July 2020.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Wahlstrom, Kyla L. “Later Start Time for Teens Improves Grades, Mood, and Safety.” </span><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">Kappanonline.org</span></i><span style="font-weight: 400;">, Phi Delta Kappa International, Dec. 2016/Jan. 2017, www.kappanonline.org/later-start-time-for-teens/. </span></p>
<p> </p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>A Social Study of Racism in Latin America</title>
        <author>
            <name>Ishan Vepa</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://blog.thegenz.org/a-social-study-of-racism-in-latin-america.html"/>
        <id>https://blog.thegenz.org/a-social-study-of-racism-in-latin-america.html</id>
            <category term="#generations"/>
            <category term="#community"/>

        <updated>2020-09-25T17:33:40-04:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://blog.thegenz.org/media/posts/44/Latin_America_Flag_Proposal-800x445.png" alt="The Persisting Impact of Racial Construction in Latin America" />
                    This summer has seen a lot more political and economic tension than ever before in most of our lifetimes. Racism has always been a point of discussion in the United States, especially in a post-Civil Rights Movement era. However, growing up in South Florida has&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <img src="https://blog.thegenz.org/media/posts/44/Latin_America_Flag_Proposal-800x445.png" alt="The Persisting Impact of Racial Construction in Latin America" />
                <p><span style="font-weight: 400;">This summer has seen a lot more political and economic tension than ever before in most of our lifetimes. Racism has always been a point of discussion in the United States, especially in a post-Civil Rights Movement era. However, growing up in South Florida has always gotten me to wonder how racism is handled in other parts of the world, specifically in Latin America.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Perhaps we should start with some history for context. In the early 16th century, the conquistadors landed in the Americas, following Columbus. Their expeditions were pure conquest -- finding land and resources for Spain. Their foreign germs murdered 90% of the native populations and what was left were either chased off, converted to Christianity, enslaved by the Spanish, or a combination of any of these. This could be where racism in Latin America truly started, but there is a key difference: the Spanish conquered for the sake of conquering. The argument could be made that there was hardly real racial motivation for colonizing the Americas, but the argument can be made for the opposite. However, by 1502, African slaves were already in the Caribbean. This is, arguably, where the true racism began in colonial Latin America.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">While indigenous people were enslaved due to conquest, African slaves were a part of the Trans-Atlantic trade system -- also famously called the Colombian Exchange -- and so now the conquistadors found themselves with a question: What will the social hierarchy be? You have ethnocentric Europeans with two different kinds of enslaved peoples. The </span><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">casta </span></i><span style="font-weight: 400;">system that the Spanish developed was as follows, roughly: with the </span><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">peninsulares </span></i><span style="font-weight: 400;">at the top (white Europeans from the Iberian peninsula), </span><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">creoles</span></i><span style="font-weight: 400;"> just under (white Europeans born in the Americas), mestizos and mulattos, followed by indigenous people, and then black slaves all the way at the bottom -- because to the white conquistador, enslaved Africans were lesser than everyone. This was due to a combination of the notion of blood purity and racial segregation. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">This system of both political, economic, and social hierarchy is most probably the reason for modern-day racism in Latin America. Unlike in the United States, racism in Latin America is based on social and economic class. This may sound similar to racism in the U.S., but in Latin America: if you’re poor, then you’re black. In the United States, racism is often the opposite: if you’re black, then you must be poor. According to an article from the American Quarterly, “</span><span style="font-weight: 400;">As early as 1944, Alejandro Lipschutz, a Chilean anthropologist, coined the idea of Latin America as a ‘pigmentocracy’ -- where the region’s social hierarchies are ethnic or color-based. However, that idea was largely ignored until recently, when research using new census data on racial identification began to document racial inequalities. These studies generally show that Afro-descendant and Indigenous people occupy the lowest rungs on the income, educational and occupational ladders across Latin America.”</span><span style="font-weight: 400;"> But because Latin America as a whole is not the wealthiest of continents, funding and money are often pushed towards other projects. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The social aspect of it is also a factor because while in the United States, “negro” is compared to the n-word, but in Latin America, it is used a fond version of “homie” for people with darker skin. To us in the U.S., this appears to be racist. But in Latin America, oftentimes it’s not used as such. Its connotations depend entirely on the context. “Negrita(/o)” is used as a fond pet name for friends or family with dark skin, even if they’re not black. At the same time, it can be used as a slur as bad as the n-word when thrown around with hate behind it. </span></p>
<p class="align-left"><em><span style="font-weight: 400;">Because of all of this, racism is often overlooked. </span></em></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">However, now this poses the question: how does this racism manifest itself in immigrants who come to the United States? It’s quite an interesting phenomena because here, Hispanics are no longer the majority; they’re the minority. Here in the U.S., they are often greeted with racism towards them, so why are some Hispanics still racist towards other minorities? By all logic, they shouldn’t. They’re on the same level as them; they’re all facing the same racism and oppression. So, why?  </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The answer is very complicated. For one, there is the notion of a sort of “protection.” Latinos are often encouraged to either marry people who are lighter skin than them or marry white people. Marrying lighter skin people has the connotations that you marry rich and that you’re gaining more “protection” from racism. It’s a practice of erasing culture and heritage for the sake of wanting -- what some would call -- a better life. This is the same reason why some Hispanics parents refuse to teach Spanish to their kids -- so that those kids don’t get picked on or have to experience racism like their parents did. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">There is also, however, a paradoxical feeling of superiority that leads to racism towards other minorities. This is mainly rooted in stereotypes portrayed in the United States that Hispanics families sometimes believe, such as how black people are called “thugs.” This reinforces the classist racism of Latin America, so the line between “poor therefore black” and “black therefore poor” is extremely blurred.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">So hopefully this has provided some insight on how racism manifests itself in different parts of the world, but also how it manifests itself when it is in the United States.</span></p>
<hr>
<p class="align-center"><em>Citations</em></p>
<p>“Science and Its Times: Understanding the Social Significance of Scientific Discovery. . Encyclopedia.com. 11 Aug. 2020 .” <em>Encyclopedia.com</em>, Encyclopedia.com, 3 Sept. 2020,</p>
<p><a href="http://www.encyclopedia.com/science/encyclopedias-almanacs-transcripts-and-maps/impact-european-">www.encyclopedia.com/science/encyclopedias-almanacs-transcripts-and-maps/impact-european-</a> diseases-native-americans.</p>
<p><em>Study.com</em>, study.com/academy/lesson/the-spanish-casta-system-definition-significance.html.</p>
<p>“Las Castas – Spanish Racial Classifications.” <em>Native Heritage Project</em>, 15 June 2013, nativeheritageproject.com/2013/06/15/las-castas-spanish-racial-classifications/.</p>
<p>Edward Telles and Liza Steele | February 21, 2012. “Racism in Latin America - Racial Identification Latin American Countries.” <em>Americas Quarterly</em>, <a href="http://www.americasquarterly.org/article/the-effects-of-skin-color-in-the-americas/">www.americasquarterly.org/article/the-effects-of-skin-color-in-the-americas/.</a></p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Inequality is NOT a Political Debate</title>
        <author>
            <name>Ishan Vepa</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://blog.thegenz.org/inequality-is-not-a-political-debate.html"/>
        <id>https://blog.thegenz.org/inequality-is-not-a-political-debate.html</id>
            <category term="#society"/>
            <category term="#rights"/>
            <category term="#political"/>
            <category term="#mlk"/>
            <category term="#inequality"/>
            <category term="#generations"/>
            <category term="#community"/>
            <category term="#blacklivesmatter"/>
            <category term="#BLM"/>

        <updated>2020-09-25T17:33:40-04:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://blog.thegenz.org/media/posts/43/blm-wm2020-protesters-500x442-01-Tia-Guay.jpg" alt="Black Lives Matter Protest." />
                    I Look To The Day When People Will Not Be Judged By The Color of Their Skin, But By The Content of Their Character" - Martin Luther King Jr. Equality has always been an issue for the human race. People are judged for their skin&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <img src="https://blog.thegenz.org/media/posts/43/blm-wm2020-protesters-500x442-01-Tia-Guay.jpg" alt="Black Lives Matter Protest." />
                <blockquote>
<p><i>I Look To The Day When People Will Not Be Judged By The Color of Their Skin, But By The Content of Their Character"</i></p>
<p><strong><i> - Martin Luther King Jr.</i></strong></p>
</blockquote>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Equality has always been an issue for the human race. People are judged for their skin color, gender, sexuality, social status, ethnicity, wealth, and much more. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The groups of people that fall on the “wrong side” of these topics, are considered a minority. Why, you ask? The answer is not simple. In fact, people have been asking this question for centuries. To be honest, there should not be an answer to this question. Actually, there should not even be a question at all. Everyone in the world should be treated equally. Wait…but then why is equality so controversial? </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The issue of equality among different groups of people, especially over the last few months, has become a hot topic of debate among politicians. There are associations with different political parties on certain topics. For instance, in the recent Black Lives Matter protests it is believed that most of the people advocating for the cause are Democrats. Of course, this is just a stereotype. Why should it matter what political party you are when it comes to equal rights of African Americans? </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The truth is…it shouldn’t. Some people are afraid to speak up about what they truly believe because they do not want to “get political.” However, the way I see it, the issue of Equality is not controversial. There should be no “Republicans vs. Democrats” when fighting for Equality. As a country, we need to unite together and combat these social issues together as one. With that being said, I decided to start this blog because I wanted to “break the barrier” about the controversial topics that I will be blogging about. In fact, nothing I will be posting is “controversial” or “political.” It is simply just the facts. On the other hand, I will be sharing my own personal beliefs on each of the topics. Although, my personal values will be reflected, none of my posts will highlight politics. As I previously stated, the issue of equality and the social injustices around the world do not exhibit a specific political party. So…how can you create social change without getting “political?” </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">For starters, do not make assumptions about different people’s political affiliation based on their stance in a social issue. By becoming more aware of your own personal views towards other people, you can become a better citizen and have your opinions be more respected by other people. Above all, demonstrate your beliefs clearly. State the problem that you want to be solved, and come up with a solution. I hope this helps to clear up some of the controversy that surrounds Equality!</span></p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Is Voting Important?</title>
        <author>
            <name>Ishan Vepa</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://blog.thegenz.org/is-voting-important.html"/>
        <id>https://blog.thegenz.org/is-voting-important.html</id>
            <category term="#vote"/>
            <category term="#society"/>
            <category term="#political"/>

        <updated>2020-09-25T17:33:40-04:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://blog.thegenz.org/media/posts/42/element5-digital-ls8Kc0P9hAA-unsplash.jpg" alt="&quot;I Voted&quot; emblems." />
                    Voting is a very crucial component of determining what can and can’t happen in your life. When people hear about voting, most people think, “Eh, I’m just one person, what can I do alone?”, when they should be thinking “The fact that I’m one more&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <img src="https://blog.thegenz.org/media/posts/42/element5-digital-ls8Kc0P9hAA-unsplash.jpg" alt="&quot;I Voted&quot; emblems." />
                <p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Voting is a very crucial component of determining what can and can’t happen in your life. When people hear about voting, most people think, “Eh, I’m just one person, what can I do alone?”, when they should be thinking “The fact that I’m one more person means that I can change what laws there are and things like who’ll be in office”. Voting is an individual act, but it’s also one of the most powerful things we can do, something that we get to decide without others forcing us to do what they want, and if need be, others don’t even get to know who/what you voted for if you don’t want them knowing.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">In places like Australia, you will get fined if you don’t vote unless you have a valid reason not to. Every time you don’t vote, your fines get higher and higher to a point where you will end up being arrested, and I think this is actually a very good thing. What Australia is doing is forcing its people to use their voice, not deprive it, not hide it, but do what they think will be best for their future and others as well. Even if you don’t want to vote, you will and you will end up having to think about what you can do with your vote and who deserves it.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Many people know the power of voting, don’t vote, and then get angry when a law gets either passed or denied and/or when someone they didn’t want gets into office. America should make compulsory voting legal in the US because this would not only benefit the country as a whole with many new voters, but this would also make it so that politicians are forced to also address poorer communities and areas that have problems that are ignored. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">An instance in which voting could’ve changed something so dramatic in the USA was when Donald Trump got elected. Out of the entire population, only 58.1% of the eligible voting population voted. Now just think about the other 41.9%, if they voted, Trump could’ve still won, or he could’ve lost. The fact that millions of Americans never voted though, means we’ll never know, and that many didn’t use their voice. Even if you’re doubtful about whether you’re doing the right thing or not, if you can, vote, at least you did something instead of nothing, and you could also learn from it for the better good.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">People need to know that even as an individual person with just one vote, they are still incredibly powerful, and can do a lot. They’re not the only ones who think the way they do, and if people vote, they might feel like an individual who isn’t doing anything, but so are many millions just like them who took the initiative to vote. </span></p>
<p class="align-center"><span style="font-weight: 400;">Voting can change so many things in a country, especially in places like America, where we have a Democratic Republic, a Constitution, and the Bill of Rights to protect our voices and our freedoms. Fighting for them and voting will keep them in place, change them, and with many new things being introduced, make a better tomorrow.</span></p>
<hr>
<p class="align-center"><em><span style="font-weight: 400;">Citations</span></em></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Bureau, US Census. “Voting in America: A Look at the 2016 Presidential Election.” </span><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">The United States Census Bureau</span></i><span style="font-weight: 400;">, 10 May 2017, www.census.gov/newsroom/blogs/random-samplings/2017/05/voting_in_america.html.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">“Compulsory Voting.” </span><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">International IDEA</span></i><span style="font-weight: 400;">, 2020, www.idea.int/data-tools/data/voter-turnout/compulsory-voting.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">“Failure to Vote.” </span><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">Western Australian Electoral Commission</span></i><span style="font-weight: 400;">, www.elections.wa.gov.au/vote/failure-vote.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">“Library Guides: Post-Election 2016 Recap &amp; Resources: Voter Turnout.” </span><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">Voter Turnout - Post-Election 2016 Recap &amp; Resources - Library Guides at Penn State University</span></i><span style="font-weight: 400;">, 14 Aug. 2020, guides.libraries.psu.edu/post-election-2016/voter-turnout.</span></p>
<p dir="ltr"><span style="font-weight: 400;">National Geographic Society. “Why Voting Is Important.” </span><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">National Geographic Society</span></i><span style="font-weight: 400;">, 17 Mar. 2020, www.nationalgeographic.org/article/why-voting-important/.</span></p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Energy Vampires and their Impact on Biodiversity</title>
        <author>
            <name>Ishan Vepa</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://blog.thegenz.org/energy-vampires-and-their-impact-on-biodiversity.html"/>
        <id>https://blog.thegenz.org/energy-vampires-and-their-impact-on-biodiversity.html</id>
            <category term="#tech"/>
            <category term="#energy"/>

        <updated>2020-09-25T17:33:40-04:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://blog.thegenz.org/media/posts/41/plug-socket-electric-electricity-energy-power-cord-outlet-hand.jpg" alt="Lightning Cable, Battery Charger, Cable, Iphone, Load, Socket" />
                    Our planet is undergoing a massive wave of extinction. Most of it is because of our doing. In order to help fix the problems that we are creating, increasing biodiversity will be a huge factor. What is biodiversity? It is the size of each population&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <img src="https://blog.thegenz.org/media/posts/41/plug-socket-electric-electricity-energy-power-cord-outlet-hand.jpg" alt="Lightning Cable, Battery Charger, Cable, Iphone, Load, Socket" />
                <p class="msg msg--highlight  align-center"><strong><em>Our planet is undergoing a massive wave of extinction. Most of it is because of our doing. In order to help fix the problems that we are creating, increasing biodiversity will be a huge factor. </em></strong></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">What is biodiversity? It is the size of each population of each species on Earth. The higher amount of diversity in an ecosystem, the more biodiversity there is in an area. This also helps the food web, since more animals would have more food sources, increasing the population number.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">There are many ways that you can help the environment. One way is by reducing Vampire Power Drains around your household. Vampire power drains are when power is being used by objects that are plugged in, even when they are not being used. These objects include the TV, lamps and even the charger to the phone (regardless if you still have your phone plugged in).</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">This method of helping biodiversity because it not only helps the environment, but it also helps your electricity bill (more on that later). Also, it is easy to do and not time consuming. It does not take much energy to unplug the things around you when you don't use them. Plus, there is no time limit to do it in, as it does not require many lifestyle changes. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">There is no time frame, so if you think about the choices you are making, this method works well. Even if you forget to do this once or twice, you can always do this method without prior commitments.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">As I said in the beginning, this method helps both you and the environment. The small amount of energy that is being used every time you keep a plug into an outlet without using it costs you some money. Over time the amount of money adds up, saving you a ton! In America, $3 billion could be saved each year just from Vampire Energy! This also equates to a small amount of carbon dioxide in the atmosphere. It also adds up to be a lot of carbon dioxide in the atmosphere.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The carbon dioxide helps warm the atmosphere (also called global warming), which warms the oceans. This kills many organisms that need a specific temperature to survive. The carbon dioxide is absorbed into the oceans, making them acidic, which kills even more organisms. Trying to lessen the amount of carbon dioxide would help this problem. Your electricity bill would also be helped, as the small amount of money saved each time you don't use the energy adds up. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">There are many different problems that vampire energy solves. For example the 25% of energy use is from the things that are plugged in, even when they are not used. Most electronics are kept in a standby mode, which allows you to use them quickly. These things suck the energy from your house, causing you to lose money. The United States consumes 26% of the world's energy! And 5% of that huge amount is JUST from the vampire energy. The huge amount could be reduced from unplugging the things you don't use!</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Being mindful of vampire energy can help both your daily life and the environment. It saves you money and it helps decrease the amount of carbon dioxide in the atmosphere. In your daily life, keep a lookout for these vampire energy drains! Your bank account and the environment will thank you!</span></p>
<hr>
<p class="align-center"><span style="font-weight: 400;"><em>Citations</em></span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;"><br></span><a href="https://www.khanacademy.org/computer-programming/link_redirector?url=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.energy.gov%2Fenergysaver%2Farticles%2Fenergy-vampires-are-attacking-your-home-here-s-how-stop-them"><span style="font-weight: 400;">“Energy Vampires Are Attacking Your Home – Here's How to Stop Them.” Energy.gov, </span></a><a href="http://www.energy.gov/energysaver/articles/energy-vampires-are-attacking-your-home-here-s-how-stop-them"><span style="font-weight: 400;">www.energy.gov/energysaver/articles/energy-vampires-are-attacking-your-home-here-s-how-stop-them</span></a><a href="https://www.khanacademy.org/computer-programming/link_redirector?url=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.energy.gov%2Fenergysaver%2Farticles%2Fenergy-vampires-are-attacking-your-home-here-s-how-stop-them"><span style="font-weight: 400;">.</span></a></p>
<p><a href="https://www.khanacademy.org/computer-programming/link_redirector?url=https%3A%2F%2Felectronics.howstuffworks.com%2Feveryday-tech%2Fvampire-power.htm"><span style="font-weight: 400;">Lamb, Robert. “How Vampire Power Works.” HowStuffWorks, HowStuffWorks, 4 June 2008, electronics.howstuffworks.com/everyday-tech/vampire-power1.htm.</span></a></p>
<p><a href="https://www.khanacademy.org/computer-programming/link_redirector?url=https%3A%2F%2Fmedium.com%2F%40heoegema%2Fcoding-for-absolute-beginners-choose-your-own-adventure-tutorial-3613182c6097"><span style="font-weight: 400;">Oegema, Holly. “Coding For Absolute Beginners: Choose Your Own Adventure Tutorial.” Medium, Medium, 2 Dec. 2017, medium.com/@heoegema/coding-for-absolute-beginners-choose-your-own-adventure-tutorial-3613182c6097.</span></a></p>
<p><a href="https://www.khanacademy.org/computer-programming/link_redirector?url=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.youtube.com%2Fwatch%3Fv%3DjgjQJdsySrM"><span style="font-weight: 400;">sfdungeon. “RACING EXTINCTION.” YouTube, YouTube, 30 June 2017, www.youtube.com/watch?v=jgjQJdsySrM.</span></a></p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Puppets No Longer: The Hypocrisy of Political Parties</title>
        <author>
            <name>Ishan Vepa</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://blog.thegenz.org/puppets-no-longer-the-hypocrisy-of-political-parties.html"/>
        <id>https://blog.thegenz.org/puppets-no-longer-the-hypocrisy-of-political-parties.html</id>
            <category term="#political"/>
            <category term="#oped"/>

        <updated>2020-09-25T17:33:40-04:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://blog.thegenz.org/media/posts/40/partisan_voters-2e3fb6e73c661b938f4003c9fc8669e7be01010e-s800-c85.jpg" alt="Rivaling political parties." />
                    Hypocrisy: a feigning to be what one is not or to believe what one does not: behavior that contradicts what one claims to believe or feel (Merriam Webster) In the political climate that is the United States of America, we are no strangers to political&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <img src="https://blog.thegenz.org/media/posts/40/partisan_voters-2e3fb6e73c661b938f4003c9fc8669e7be01010e-s800-c85.jpg" alt="Rivaling political parties." />
                <p class="post__lead dropcap"><span style="font-weight: 400;">Hypocrisy: </span><span style="font-weight: 400;">a feigning to be what one is not or to believe what one does not: behavior that contradicts what one claims to believe or feel (Merriam Webster)</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">In the political climate that is the United States of America, we are no strangers to political parties (nominally the two major ones; Republicans and Democrats) being quite divisive on an array of issues. Ranging from gun control to welfare to immigration to mask-wearing to you name it. Often we find if Republicans believe one thing, Democrats are inclined to believe the opposite, and vice versa. While most can not see it at face value, this is very much a dangerous thing as this can cause political parties to contradict themselves in what they say and do and be hypocritical in what they believe in order to be divisive, because divisiveness is what keeps party loyalty and gets the votes. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">It is important to note that it is quite easy for these divisive political ideologies to infect the minds of the people. We live in a world where it seems you have to choose a side because Republicans and Democrats are “sworn enemies” on every issue. We are told to pick a side and if we do not pick a side and believe in everything that side believes in, we are automatically traitors to the political party we align ourselves with and to America as a whole. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Generalizations can help and can hurt. We should never generalize a person or a group of people based on any factor, we should always hear out. For example, just because someone is a registered Republican that does not mean they are not for more gun control or a Democrat could be pro-life. However, certain generalizations must be concluded about these political parties and their ideologies as it points out their hypocritical nature. It is this hypocritical nature that is derived from the fact that these political parties must be “sworn enemies” and divisive on every issue, even at the expense of compromising and contradicting themselves and being hypocritical. This is all done in order to get the vote, to make Americans choose a side lest they be traitors to party and to America itself. It is this hypocritical, divisive mindset that is tearing America apart and harming more than helping. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">And no better an example to discuss this is the abortion debate.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">As a pro-life American whose pro-lifeness is hinged on my relationship with Christ (I am a Christian), I will point out the hypocrisy of the Republican party first when it comes to this debate. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Typically, Republican ideology tilts towards the pro-life side of this debate. They argue for the sanctity of life and how life in the womb matters and must be preserved. They argue it is murderous and vile. Yet, the same party that argues for the sanctity of life has a leader that wants to build a wall to keep life out. They argue for the sanctity of life in the womb, only as long as that womb or person is a U.S. citizen. Who cares about the people trying to find safety and life from drug cartels or violence or to just have a better life than the one they came from? The only precious life is the one within the borders of the U.S. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Being pro-life means being pro-immigrant lives, pro-black lives, pro-”anything that is a human life”. Anyways, let us move on…. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Before I discuss the Democratic view, I would like to point out a stat I read from a New York Times article where it was found that “</span><span style="font-weight: 400;"> black women continue to have the highest abortion rate at 27.1 per 1,000 women compared with 10 per 1,000 for white women, </span><a href="https://ajph.aphapublications.org/doi/10.2105/AJPH.2017.304042"><span style="font-weight: 400;">according to a study</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;"> published in the American Journal of Public Health.” (Eligon) As to why this is? Another quote from the same article gives some insight, “</span><span style="font-weight: 400;">In many black communities, the abortion debate is inextricably tied to race in ways that white communities seldom confront. Social and economic disparities that are particularly challenging to African-Americans, from mass incarceration to maternal and infant mortality, are crucial parts of that discussion,” (Eligon). </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Democrats tend to be pro-choice in the abortion debate, meaning they tend to advocate for abortion and the right to have one. As well, it is typically Democrats who are more progressive in their thinking and they spearhead social justice movements in our democracy, especially when it comes to race. However, there is an issue. The same party that spearheads social justice for black Americans also advocates for a practice that affects black women at a rate of almost 3 to 1. In the same breath, they advocate for ways to end systemic racism but also advocate for a practice that feeds off of systemic racism and is killing the future black leaders of American more than the white ones. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">These political parties are willing to contradict themselves in what they say and believe and be hypocritical in order to appear divisive. They claim and appear to be the protectors of “life and justice”, but contradict themselves and are another thing entirely. This is all done to be divisive, to get the vote, and make Americans pick a side and believe everything that side believes, lest they be traitors to party and to country.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">I say these things not out of hate nor anger, but out of love for country and love for every human in and outside this country. As a Christ-follower, it is my humble belief that I put Christ first in my life and in doing so I show love to as many people as possible. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">We as Americans are being politically divided, and it is doing a lot more harm than good. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">We as American people must be able to think as individuals and come up with opinions that are based on facts and our love and care for other humans, not based on political allegiance. And in doing so we must reach a place where we do not hate each other for our opinions. A Republican should be able to believe in gun control, a Democrat should be able to be pro-life, and both not be hated for it. People should be able to make opinions on issues based on facts and love for one another and not based on whether they say Biden or Trump 2020 and not have to be hated for it.  And in making these opinions, we must reach a place where we can discuss such opinions in a loving, caring, gentle, respectful manner in where we can make compromises that help as many people as possible. Where we can disagree with one another, but still have a respectful conversation about our disagreement. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Our goal should be able to come up with opinions on issues as individuals who care for and love their country and care for and love people as a whole, to make opinions while considering the facts and how this may positively or negatively affect people in real life, to respectfully and gently discuss our opinions and try to come up with solutions and compromises that help as many people as possible, and to not be puppets for these political machines any longer.</span></p>
<hr>
<p class="align-center"><em>Citations</em></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Eligon, John. “When ‘Black Lives Matter’ Is Invoked in the Abortion Debate.” The New York Times, 6 July. 2019, </span><a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2019/07/06/us/black-abortion-missouri.html"><span style="font-weight: 400;">https://www.nytimes.com/2019/07/06/us/black-abortion-missouri.html</span></a></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Merriam Webster. “Definition of Hypocrisy.” </span><a href="https://www.merriam-webster.com/dictionary/hypocrisy"><span style="font-weight: 400;">https://www.merriam-webster.com/dictionary/hypocrisy</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;">. Accessed August 15, 2020</span></p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
</feed>
