<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <title>The Generation Z Blog</title>
    <link href="https://blog.thegenz.org/feed.xml" rel="self" />
    <link href="https://blog.thegenz.org" />
    <updated>2020-11-18T10:34:40-05:00</updated>
    <author>
        <name>Ishan Vepa</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://blog.thegenz.org</id>

    <entry>
        <title>Are Sports More Harmful or Helpful for Kids?</title>
        <author>
            <name>Ishan Vepa</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://blog.thegenz.org/are-sports-more-harmful-or-helpful-for-kids.html"/>
        <id>https://blog.thegenz.org/are-sports-more-harmful-or-helpful-for-kids.html</id>
            <category term="#youth"/>
            <category term="#sports"/>
            <category term="#society"/>

        <updated>2020-11-18T10:34:40-05:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://blog.thegenz.org/media/posts/55/socc-2.png" alt="" />
                     Are sports more harmful or helpful for kids? Sports are more helpful than harmful for kids. Sports are a helpful thing in a child’s life because kids who play sports are more confident, they perform better academically, and get more exercise than the average&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <img src="https://blog.thegenz.org/media/posts/55/socc-2.png" alt="" />
                <p class="msg msg--highlight  align-center"><span style="font-weight: 400;"> </span><em><strong>Are sports more harmful or helpful for kids? Sports are more helpful than harmful for kids. Sports are a helpful thing in a child’s life because kids who play sports are more confident, they perform better academically, and get more exercise than the average non playing sports child. </strong></em></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Sports are helpful for children because kids who play sports have more confidence than those who don’t. Most sports jocks tend to be on the more confident side, but according to the news video, “Kids and Sports”, sports give all kids confidence even if they are not playing for a team or with other kids at all. he video also says that minimal confidence is beneficial to a child. As displayed by facts in the video everyone is more confident if or when they play a sport.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Another way sports are helpful for kids is because kids tend to do better academically when they play a sport. In the news video “Sports: How much is too much?”, the coach of the basketball team says that the kids with overwhelming schedules do better academically, than the ones who have nothing to do. The coach also proves that his statement is correct by saying that when the sports season ends grades drop because the athletes seem to lose focus on their sport and their schoolwork. Sports don’t just help athletes in regular school but in college, because being good at a sport can get you a scholarship to a college, especially if you have good grades too.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The last way that sports are helpful for kids is because they help kids get more exercise. Exercise is good for staying healthy and burning calories, most of us know that, but did you know sports help kids prevent a terrible disease. In the article “What in the Name of High School Football?” by Hank Hill, it states, “The single greatest factor in preventing the nation’s number one killer - heart disease - is regular and vigorous exercise”. Children who play sports definitely get regular and vigorous exercise. So just by playing sports children can stay away from the nation’s number one killer. You wouldn’t want to hand your kid to a killer, would you? </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">In conclusion sports are without a doubt more helpful to kids than harmful. Sports help children socially, academically, and physically. Simply by just playing even one sport children will have more confidence, better grades, and stay away from a killer. If you are wondering whether to put your child on a sports team, if they want to do it, let them. Yes, they can get hurt, but it’s not definite, and it’s probably better than heart disease.</span></p>
<hr>
<p class="align-center"><em>Citations</em></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">CBS and Katie Couric, directors. </span><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">Notebook: Kids And Sports (CBS News)</span></i><span style="font-weight: 400;">, CBS News, 7 Jan. 2008, www.youtube.com/watch?v=CV-WqlorsBM.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Gray, Walt and KCRA News, directors. </span><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">Sports: How Much Is Too Much?</span></i><span style="font-weight: 400;">, KCRA News, 15 Feb. 2011, www.youtube.com/watch?v=vrP68OD355w.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Hill, Hank. “What in the Name of High School Football?” </span><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">Images.pcmac.org</span></i><span style="font-weight: 400;">, Scholastic Inc., images.pcmac.org/SiSFiles/Schools/GA/CatoosaCounty/HeritageMiddle/Uploads/DocumentsCategories/Documents/sports%20articles.pdf.</span></p>
<p> </p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Tap Water Versus Plastic Bottles</title>
        <author>
            <name>Ishan Vepa</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://blog.thegenz.org/tap-water-versus-plastic-bottles.html"/>
        <id>https://blog.thegenz.org/tap-water-versus-plastic-bottles.html</id>
            <category term="#society"/>
            <category term="#lifestyle"/>
            <category term="#infrastructure"/>
            <category term="#environment"/>

        <updated>2020-10-31T17:50:30-04:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://blog.thegenz.org/media/posts/54/plasticwaterbottle-Anika-Mathur.jpg" alt="Plastic Water Bottles" />
                    During the school year, what do you usually use? Do you grab a plastic bottle of water? If so, then you may not know the benefits of using tap water instead of bottled water! Why have bottled water when you could get tap water? Well,&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <img src="https://blog.thegenz.org/media/posts/54/plasticwaterbottle-Anika-Mathur.jpg" alt="Plastic Water Bottles" />
                <p class="msg msg--highlight  align-center"><em><strong>During the school year, what do you usually use? Do you grab a plastic bottle of water? If so, then you may not know the benefits of using tap water instead of bottled water!</strong></em></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Why have bottled water when you could get tap water? Well, tap water is free and much more cost-effective than buying plastic water bottles. If you use tap water, instead of plastic bottled water, you would also be decreasing the amount of waste you use daily. Why waste your money and pollute your world by using plastic water bottles, when you could get tap water? </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Water bottles would cost you a lot of money if you continuously buy them. Tap water is much better to use in daily life since it saves you money. In fact, according to Business Insider, water bottles cost 2000 times more than regular tap water. In 2012, around $11.8 billion were spent by Americans on water bottles, reported by the BMC. Imagine the amount of savings that everyone could have if they used tap water instead of bottled water! Americans are spending so much on bottled water that a gallon of bottled water is twice the price of gasoline. When there is a more cost-effective solution than continuously buying bottled water, why should we continue to waste our money?</span></p>
<p class="msg msg--highlight  align-center"><em><strong>Do you throw out your water bottles after drinking them? Well, since you do, tap water is better than bottled water because water bottles create a lot of waste! </strong></em></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">According to The World Counts, every second 1,500 plastic bottles are being thrown into the ocean or in landfills. Obviously, this is a lot of waste, especially when most people can easily use tap water from their own home! Only 1 in 5 plastic bottles are recycled as well. The other 4 are usually thrown away, or they are littered.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Some may claim that bottled water has a different taste than regular tap water. What if I told you there isn’t any difference? You might have heard that bottled water is cleaner and healthier than tap water, but this is a huge lie! In reality, tap water is as good as bottled water! The World Counts reported that most bottled water is just tap water! Although critics say that there is a huge difference between tap and bottled water, blind tests state that tap water and bottled water taste the same, according to psych central. This imaginary difference between bottled and tap water is one that is costing Americans a lot of money and increasing the amount of waste created!</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">As you can see, tap water is just as good as bottled water, if not, even better! Bottled water is a waste of money, creates too much waste and it has no difference than tap water!  Now that you are informed, try to take steps to drink tap water instead of reaching for a bottle of water. Doing this can help the environment and your wallet!</span></p>
<p><br><br><br></p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Sleep it Off</title>
        <author>
            <name>Ishan Vepa</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://blog.thegenz.org/sleep-it-off.html"/>
        <id>https://blog.thegenz.org/sleep-it-off.html</id>
            <category term="#society"/>
            <category term="#lifestyle"/>
            <category term="#community"/>

        <updated>2020-10-27T10:27:02-04:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://blog.thegenz.org/media/posts/53/sleep-Ekansh-Kushwaha.jpg" alt="8 Ways to Sleep Like a Pro Athlete." />
                    According to NDTV, 1 in every 5 people don't get enough sleep every night. Many people like to squeeze out a few more extra hours in their day, whether it be for work or recreation, but they sacrifice the wrong thing to do it. Instead&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <img src="https://blog.thegenz.org/media/posts/53/sleep-Ekansh-Kushwaha.jpg" alt="8 Ways to Sleep Like a Pro Athlete." />
                <p class="msg msg--highlight "><em><strong>According to NDTV, 1 in every 5 people don't get enough sleep every night.</strong></em></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Many people like to squeeze out a few more extra hours in their day, whether it be for work or recreation, but they sacrifice the wrong thing to do it. Instead of trying to forsake their sleep people should work more efficiently or decide to do it at the later date. Getting enough sleep is especially important during this pandemic as sleeping is the one time when our body can dedicate all resources to fight any germs and diseases that might have infected us.</span></p>
<p class="msg msg--highlight "><em><strong>Sleep is essential for the physical upkeep of the body, but it also helps maintain cognitive skills, such as attention, learning, memory, and emotional regulation.</strong></em></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">According to Erica Jansen, sleep touches almost every aspect of health as it can affect anything from our physical and mental condition the next day to reduce the risk factor of and developing immunity against various diseases and viruses. You might have noticed that one day if you hardly got any sleep, the next day you feel sluggish, moody, and tired. On the other hand, if you got the proper amount of sleep on another day then the day after that you probably felt refreshed, energetic, and maybe even cheerful. All that change came simply from how much sleep you got! Furthermore, according to the CDC, not getting enough sleep can increase one's chances of getting type 2 diabetes, cardiovascular disease, and obesity. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Getting more sleep can also drastically improve your performance at getting work done. According to an article written by Ana Sandoiu, not only does sleeping help us learn new things faster, but it also helps to increase the neuroplasticity of our brains. Neuroplasticity is the brain's ability to rewire itself and create new connections between neurons. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Furthermore, sleep can help one be more emotionally stable and reduce their risk of developing a mental health condition. People who don’t get enough sleep will be more prone to getting anxiety and depression which in itself could lead to further sleepless nights. Sleep also helps us to perceive reality correctly. Research suggests that if one doesn't sleep for 3 or more nights they will have perceptual distortions, hallucinations, and delusions. When scientists reviewed their research they were also able to find out that poor sleep, or insomnia, preceded the development of bipolar disorder and schizophrenia. Insomnia also increased the chances of one to commit suicide. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Now that you have made it this far you are probably wondering if there are any tips as to how to get more/better sleep. One of the best ways that I have found to improve one's sleep cycle is a form of cognitive-behavioral therapy for treating insomnia (CBT-I). To test its effects, Professor Freeman and a few of his colleagues randomly chose 3,755 students with insomnia from 26 different colleges and made them receive either CBT-I or usual care. After some testing, Freeman found that students who received the CBT-I treatment had a more significant improvement in sleep cycles than the students who received the usual care. Not only did the student who received CBT-I have better sleep, but they also experienced less paranoia and fewer hallucinations. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">When you begin the therapy you first learn about what exactly sleep is and how to change your sleep-related behaviors and thought processes. Then you learn about sleep hygiene which involves things such as limiting naps and not using electronics 30 minutes before or during bedtime. Next, you are taught three behavioral techniques: Sleep restriction, stimulus control, and relaxation. Finally, you learn about a few cognitive techniques, some of which include belief restructuring, mindfulness, imagery, and paradoxical intention. Of course, this is a brief overview of CBT-I but if you think this might help you then I recommend searching about it and understanding it more in-depth. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Sleep is a very important factor in maintaining our health and living a happy and fulfilling life. We should try to do our best to get enough sleep in the day otherwise your life might start going downhill before you even realize it. While you might think that you are fine if you get a mere 1 hour of sleep or simply not sleeping at all, you are not. Lack of sleep takes its toll both mentally and physically. </span></p>
<hr>
<p class="align-center"><em><span style="font-weight: 400;">Citations</span></em></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Jansen, Erica. “Sleep 101: Why Sleep Is So Important to Your Health: The Pursuit: University of Michigan School of Public Health: Adolescent Health: Child Health: Chronic Disease: Epidemic: Mental Health: Obesity.” The Pursuit | University of Michigan School of Public Health | Adolescent Health | Child Health | Chronic Disease | Epidemic | Mental Health | Obesity, 2 Mar. 2020, sph.umich.edu/pursuit/2020posts/why-sleep-is-so-important-to-your-health.html#:~:text=Sleep%20is%20essential%20to%20every,touches%20every%20aspect%20of%20health.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Kingsland, James. “Mental Health: What Role Does Sleep Play?” Edited by Hannah Flynn, Medical News Today, MediLexicon International, 4 Aug. 2020, www.medicalnewstoday.com/articles/sleep-and-mental-health#How-does-CBT-for-insomnia-work?</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Sandoiu , Ana. “The Neuroscience of Sleep.” Edited by Jessica Beake, Medical News Today, MediLexicon International, 6 Aug. 2020, www.medicalnewstoday.com/articles/what-happens-in-the-brain-when-you-sleep#The-neurons-that-make-us-forget-dreams.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Perez, Cassandra. “20 Percent People Sleep Deprived Globally: Survey.” Sleep Review, 16 Mar. 2020, www.sleepreviewmag.com/curated/20-percent-people-sleep-deprived-globally-survey/.</span></p>
<p> </p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Put your Parties on Hold</title>
        <author>
            <name>Ishan Vepa</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://blog.thegenz.org/put-your-parties-on-hold.html"/>
        <id>https://blog.thegenz.org/put-your-parties-on-hold.html</id>
            <category term="#society"/>
            <category term="#socialmedia"/>
            <category term="#popculture"/>
            <category term="#global"/>
            <category term="#covid19"/>
            <category term="#coronavirus"/>

        <updated>2020-10-05T07:34:54-04:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://blog.thegenz.org/media/posts/52/7-1-1024x512-Rohan-Thapliyal.jpg" alt="Social Media of People hosting parties." />
                     In case you’ve been under a rock for the past few months, we are in the middle of a global pandemic. There is a disease plaguing the world, infecting and killing, with no cure as of yet. Nearly the entire world is under quarantine&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <img src="https://blog.thegenz.org/media/posts/52/7-1-1024x512-Rohan-Thapliyal.jpg" alt="Social Media of People hosting parties." />
                <p><span style="font-weight: 400;"> </span><span style="font-weight: 400;">In case you’ve been under a rock for the past few months, we are in the middle of a global pandemic. There is a disease plaguing the world, infecting and killing, with no cure as of yet. Nearly the entire world is under quarantine as to lower the haste of Covid-19’s spread and try to allow hospitals to treat patients at a speed at which they can handle. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">In all of this, you’d think this would be a time where people would put down their pitchforks and listen to the people that know what’s best for them. You’d think that there would finally be an event where the whole world could agree to put their gatherings on hold and follow social distancing, not for themselves, but for the innocent people they could spread the disease to whom very well could be at risk of death if they caught such a disease. You’d think these things, but it apparently isn’t the case.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;"> </span><span style="font-weight: 400;">As an example, social media influencer Jake Paul has thrown a party as of recently. A party. Right now. In the middle of a pandemic. You hopefully can see how such a thing is a problem in today’s life as, even if there were precautions made, germs were definitely spread as well as the potential spread of disease. Though, saying precautions were made would be a complete and utter overstatement, as Jake did nothing of the sort. No distancing, no masks, and dozens of party-goers in extremely close proximity to each other. As icing on the cake, there apparently is a possibility that one of the party attendees was infected during the time the party took place. After hearing such news, Jake Paul was barely fazed, saying he wasn’t worried.</span><span style="font-weight: 400;"> He then said in an interview that he will not promise to stop partying, as “Our leadership has failed us” being his only defense against his actions.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;"> </span><span style="font-weight: 400;">As for what we can do to combat this stupidity and recklessness is pretty much nothing. All we can do is take precautions, not for us, but for those innocent people. Use Jake Paul as an example of what not to do. We are still in a pandemic, and we can do better than this.</span></p>
<p dir="ltr"> </p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>E-Waste: The Consequences of Material Extraction</title>
        <author>
            <name>Ishan Vepa</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://blog.thegenz.org/e-waste-the-consequences-of-material-extraction.html"/>
        <id>https://blog.thegenz.org/e-waste-the-consequences-of-material-extraction.html</id>
            <category term="#tech"/>
            <category term="#environment"/>

        <updated>2020-10-01T17:44:12-04:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://blog.thegenz.org/media/posts/51/e_waste.jpg" alt="E-waste consolidation." />
                    The United States produces 6.9 million tons of electronic waste each year and only 12% of it gets recycled according to the EPA. The rate of electronics being produced is five times faster than the growth of the human population itself. All of this electronic&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <img src="https://blog.thegenz.org/media/posts/51/e_waste.jpg" alt="E-waste consolidation." />
                <p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The United States produces 6.9 million tons of electronic waste each year and only 12% of it gets recycled according to the EPA. The rate of electronics being produced is five times faster than the growth of the human population itself. All of this electronic waste or e-waste, is made of valuable metals and toxic substances, 50 - 70 % of which is transported to foreign countries, where it accumulates developing into a hazard for the surrounding environment. </span></p>
<p class="align-center msg msg--highlight "><em><strong>But creating massive amounts of electronics requires large amounts of materials that are causing problems in many third-world countries.</strong></em></p>
<p><strong><i>The conflict in DRC:</i></strong></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;"> </span><span style="font-weight: 400;">The Democratic Republic has been a hotspot of conflict for many years and is currently going through a civil war fueled by the mining of metals. Both sides depend on the metals to finance operations causing a conflict which has taken the lives of 5.4 million people since 1998. These metals are then bought by foreign countries to produce electronics. Robert Hormats, who served as the Under Secretary of State for Economic Growth, Energy, and the Environment said that the consequences of mineral mining are “one of the most significant moral issues of our time”. </span></p>
<p><strong><i>Environmental impact: </i></strong></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;"> </span><span style="font-weight: 400;">Mining for metals is extremely detrimental to the surrounding environment. It contaminates nearby water sources with different types of toxic metals and acids which kills wildlife. A large amount of waste is also produced through the mining process which ends up in the ground or at waste sites. Approximately 80 tons of waste is produced from mining one ounce of gold. The mining of rare Earth elements also requires miners to separate it from radioactive elements. Managing the radioactive waste is also a problem and many are exposed to radiation in the process. One of the largest e-waste dumps in the world is the city of Guiyu in China, where e-waste from all over the world is transported for burning or recycling. The burning of plastics has resulted in 80 % of Guiyu’s children to have high amounts of lead in their blood. Nearby water sources also test high for industrial solvents and metals.</span></p>
<p><strong><i>What you can do to help: </i></strong></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;"> </span><span style="font-weight: 400;">One of the best ways that you can help slow down the amount of e-waste produced is by lengthening the time you buy devices. Instead of buying the newest phone and chucking the old one every time your brand comes out with a new version, buy a new phone every two or three versions as most phones work fine for more than 3 or 4 years. This is the same with laptops and TVs which can also last very long before needing a replacement. Most cell carriers have deals where you can trade in a phone and it counts towards your purchase of a newer version which is also a great way to reduce the amount of e-waste you produce. The safest way to dispose of electronics is to check for nearby recycling centers for electronics. They can manage the waste and recover metals and parts that can be recycled before getting rid of the waste.</span></p>
<hr>
<p class="align-center"><em><span style="font-weight: 400;">Citations</span></em></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;"> </span><span style="font-weight: 400;">“Where’s The Harm – From Materials Extraction?” </span><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">Electronics Take Back Coalition</span></i><span style="font-weight: 400;">, </span><a href="http://www.electronicstakeback.com/toxics-in-electronics/wheres-the-harm-extraction/"><span style="font-weight: 400;">www.electronicstakeback.com/toxics-in-electronics/wheres-the-harm-extraction/</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;">.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Banco, Erin. “Is Your Cell Phone Fueling Civil War in Congo?” </span><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">The Atlantic</span></i><span style="font-weight: 400;">, Atlantic Media Company, 10 July 2011, </span><a href="http://www.theatlantic.com/international/archive/2011/07/is-your-cell-phone-fueling-civil-war-in-congo/241663/"><span style="font-weight: 400;">www.theatlantic.com/international/archive/2011/07/is-your-cell-phone-fueling-civil-war-in-congo/241663/</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;">.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Pinghui, Zhuang. “China's Notorious e-Waste Dumping Ground Cleaner but Poorer.” </span><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">South China Morning Post</span></i><span style="font-weight: 400;">, 22 Sept. 2017, </span><a href="http://www.scmp.com/news/china/society/article/2112226/chinas-most-notorious-e-waste-dumping-ground-now-cleaner-poorer"><span style="font-weight: 400;">www.scmp.com/news/china/society/article/2112226/chinas-most-notorious-e-waste-dumping-ground-now-cleaner-poorer</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;">.</span></p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Should Schools Reopen</title>
        <author>
            <name>Ishan Vepa</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://blog.thegenz.org/should-schools-reopen.html"/>
        <id>https://blog.thegenz.org/should-schools-reopen.html</id>
            <category term="#education"/>
            <category term="#covid19"/>
            <category term="#coronavirus"/>

        <updated>2020-09-25T17:33:29-04:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://blog.thegenz.org/media/posts/50/24F482A3-B132-49A9-87F2-B516DFFC1C78-Ryan-Shankar.jpeg" alt="Covid-19 classroom integration." />
                    With summer ending schools have started to re-open, but is that the right move many wonder. I strongly believe that reopening schools is the worst thing that could happen currently. Because there is still a raging pandemic which the world, let alone the U.S has&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <img src="https://blog.thegenz.org/media/posts/50/24F482A3-B132-49A9-87F2-B516DFFC1C78-Ryan-Shankar.jpeg" alt="Covid-19 classroom integration." />
                <p class="align-center msg msg--highlight "><em><strong>With summer ending schools have started to re-open, but is that the right move many wonder. I strongly believe that reopening schools is the worst thing that could happen currently. Because there is still a raging pandemic which the world, let alone the U.S has an answer for. </strong></em></p>
<p class="align-center"><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">What effect has schools reopening had on students</span></i></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;"> </span><span style="font-weight: 400;">Schools reopening have put many students at risk of catching the virus. In the last two weeks of July over 97,000 covid cases were students, schools were not even open. If the virus is spreading this fast for students when out of school, I don't want to imagine how bad it will be when all schools reopen. But many schools have set up an online option that will provide distance learning to students which will reduce a good chunk of those potential cases but not enough. Many of the schools in the Southern states are reopening and those states have seen a surge in cases. Georgia has had over 40,000 new cases ever since schools opened. Their cases per day went from 2,000 a day to 4,000 a day. If all states reopened schools, their cases would obviously rise and call for the entire state to be shut down again. That's why I believe that online school, until the amount of cases decreases massively, is how schools should be reopening. </span></p>
<p class="align-center"><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">Why do students and parents not want online school?</span></i></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Many students dislike online learning, because it is easier for many to learn in person. I can agree with this because when schools did close in the spring it was harder keeping a routine and learning new concepts from home. I feel like even though it is harder to learn from home it will be beneficial to the country as there the amount of cases that could happen would be prevented. Many believe that saving lives is worth doing online school, no matter how hard it may be for some students. A major flaw with online education is not everyone has access to it. Many organizations are trying like internet providers are trying to help students who don't have access by providing WiFi and other technology they need. Also it is a lot harder for younger students to learn from a at home setting as they have shorter attention spans and need more help learning topics. But teachers and parents are trying their best to help them. Schools have served as a daycare for many parents and with online school that would not be possible, not every parent can work from home and their child would have to be sent to a daycare which will cost them extra. The government is trying to provide financial support but I fear that it will not be enough to help these families who are struggling during these times. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Overall schools reopening wouldn’t help anybody as after a week or two they would have to close again because of the virus. If a state decides to let schools open for in person learning there should be some requirements, such as less students, masks, social distancing and daily cleaning of the school. Sadly that's not what we have seen in Georgia and many other states that have reopened schools, as many students aren't wearing masks or social distancing. CNN reported on this issue but schools in Georgia have not changed anything. One school even suspended the student who took the photo exposing the school. I don’t think any public place such as schools can open safely without there being an outbreak and for those reasons, I believe schools shouldn’t have in person learning until numbers are under control.</span></p>
<hr>
<p class="align-center"><em>Citations</em></p>
<p>Turner, Cory. “At Least 97,000 Children Tested Positive For Coronavirus In Last 2 Weeks Of July.” <i>NPR</i>, NPR, 11 Aug. 2020, <a href="http://www.npr.org/sections/coronavirus-live-updates/2020/08/11/900861372/at-least-97-000-children-tested-positive-for-coronavirus-in-last-2-weeks-of-july">www.npr.org/sections/coronavirus-live-updates/2020/08/11/900861372/at-least-97-000-children-tested-positive-for-coronavirus-in-last-2-weeks-of-july</a>.</p>
<p>Peiser, Jaclyn. “A Georgia District Returned to School Last Week. More than 900 Students and Staff Are Now Quarantined.” <i>The Washington Post</i>, WP Company, 12 Aug. 2020, <a href="http://www.washingtonpost.com/nation/2020/08/12/school-coronavirus-outbreak-georgia-quarantine/">www.washingtonpost.com/nation/2020/08/12/school-coronavirus-outbreak-georgia-quarantine/</a>.</p>
<p>Andone, Dakin. “Georgia School Seen in Photo of a Crowded Hallway Will Briefly Move to Online Learning after Reporting 9 Cases of Covid-19.” <i>CNN</i>, Cable News Network, 10 Aug. 2020, <a href="http://www.cnn.com/2020/08/09/us/north-paulding-high-school-covid-19-cases/index.html">www.cnn.com/2020/08/09/us/north-paulding-high-school-covid-19-cases/index.html</a>.</p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Google’s COVID-19 Alert</span></p>
<p> </p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Our Unconscious Biases: The Hidden Racial Prejudice Within us All</title>
        <author>
            <name>Ishan Vepa</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://blog.thegenz.org/our-unconscious-biases-the-hidden-racial-prejudice-within-us-all.html"/>
        <id>https://blog.thegenz.org/our-unconscious-biases-the-hidden-racial-prejudice-within-us-all.html</id>
            <category term="#society"/>
            <category term="#inequality"/>
            <category term="#generations"/>
            <category term="#gap"/>
            <category term="#community"/>
            <category term="#blacklivesmatter"/>

        <updated>2020-09-16T16:25:18-04:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://blog.thegenz.org/media/posts/48/unconscious-bias-pic-Generation-Z-Media.png" alt="Unconscious Biases in the Workplace graphic." />
                    “Are Emily and Greg More Employable Than Lakisha and Jamal?” The American Economic Institute conducted this study in order to understand labor market discrimination. Fictitious resumes were sent to over 1300 employment ads in Boston and Chicago newspapers. The resumes were randomly assigned either a&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <img src="https://blog.thegenz.org/media/posts/48/unconscious-bias-pic-Generation-Z-Media.png" alt="Unconscious Biases in the Workplace graphic." />
                <p class="msg msg--highlight  align-center"><em><strong>“Are Emily and Greg More Employable Than Lakisha and Jamal?” </strong></em></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The American Economic Institute conducted this study in order to understand labor market discrimination. Fictitious resumes were sent to over 1300 employment ads in Boston and Chicago newspapers. The resumes were randomly assigned either a white-sounding name (Emily Walsh or Greg Baker) or an African American sounding name (Lakisha Washington or Jamal Jones). The researches also varied the quality of the resumes, giving two higher quality and two-lower-quality resumes to each employer for a total of nearly 5000 resumes covering a vast array of jobs within the fields of sales and administrative support and customer services.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Researchers found that white-sounding names had a 9.65% chance of receiving a callback, whereas African American sounding names had a 6.45% chance. Regarding quality, higher-quality resumes did receive more callbacks, as expected, but for African Americans, the difference was only a 0.51% improvement. A number that researchers deemed statistically insignificant, essentially meaning that African American applicants experienced no gain from a higher quality resume.   </span><span style="font-weight: 400;">                     </span></p>
<figure class="align-center"><span style="font-weight: 400;">                                                                            </span>                                                                                                <img loading="lazy"  src="https://miro.medium.com/max/900/1*R1j1tQkSR8mdQls7G3sjZQ.jpeg" data-is-external-image="true"  alt="Are Emily and Greg more Employable than Lakisha and Jamal? | by Brooke C |  Medium" width="415" height="509"></figure>
<p> </p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The researchers were in fact able to conclude that the employers were being discriminatory towards the African Americans. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">This experiment is just one application of our implicit, unconscious racial biases creating unfair hurdles and impeding access to opportunity. Something that every American has. Racial biases are something that I, a person of color, am not free of.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Why use the word biases, rather than just plain and simple, racism? </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The word racism has a severe negative connotation that many view as negative thoughts, negative feelings, and hatred towards a group of people. Since the passing of legislation during the civil rights era making this immoral and illegal, racism has become more subtle. These negative feelings embedded within a race are still there but many aren’t aware of them. And rather than hatred, it’s more like avoidance and discomfort. That’s where the use of the words “unconscious, implicit, racial biases” comes from.</span></p>
<p class="align-center"><strong>Biases at Work</strong></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">John Dovidio, professor of psychology and public health at Yale University, further explores this. “Most of us want to be good people. Prejudice is bad and when we think about it, we always do the right thing. But if something is unconscious, you don’t know you have it. It’s that simple. They’re like having habits of mind that you’ve grown up with” he says in an interview with the American Psychological Association</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Many agree that we cannot get rid of this inherent bias in our brains. On the contrary, it’s something we manage. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">But the </span><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">Are Emily and Greg More Employable Than Lakisha and Jamal experiment </span></i><span style="font-weight: 400;">has proved that these subtle biases are having greater adverse effects when being put into application. This is evident not only in the labor market but within critical life domains such as housing, education, health, and criminal justice. Our implicit biases present themselves in the form of microaggressions (indirect, subtle, or even unintentional acts of discrimination against members of a marginalized group), stereotyping, avoidance, or in the worst-case scenario, through our decision making, for example with police. All creating barriers that impede opportunity. Essentially, making the need to manage our biases on an individual level all the more vital and urgent. </span></p>
<p class="align-center"><strong>How can we manage our racial biases?</strong></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">One important strategy to understand our biases is the involvement of racial and ethnic diversity in conversations and discussions. Like mentioned before, racism has shifted from hatred to now avoidance, discomfort, and bias. The problem with avoiding a group of people is that allows you to maintain the stereotypes that you have of that group. Assumptions and expectations about the roles they should play all lead to unfair judgments. Reversely, if you continue to interact with those members you no longer think about them as members of a group. You think about them as individuals. </span></p>
<p><strong>“You haven’t really gotten rid of the implicit bias, but you’ve now been able to fine-tune and dial-up a broader array of repertoire of being able to interact with people and understand them,” says Divido.</strong></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">More importantly, dealing with bias is a personal operation. Situations, mostly vulnerable, stress ones, around us affect when our racial biases come into play. In situations where we feel threatened or fearful we are more likely to act on our biases. Jenifer Eberhardt, professor of psychology at Stanford University, explains that “by interrogating ourselves and slowing ourselves down... just being aware when we’re beginning to make stereotypic associations.” This allows you to move your thinking from the primitive, reactive parts of the brain to the more reflective levels.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Black people convicted of capital offenses facing the death penalty at higher rates than white people. Teachers quick to see “patterns” of bad behavior in black children. Police officers shooting unarmed black men. All are outcomes of our biases that not only explore the nature of America but are ideas that Eberhardt has studied. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Eberhardt agrees that increased diversity in neighborhoods, workplaces, and schools is vital. But the implementation of anti-bias training in many institutions is where we can begin to deal with our bias in the workplace. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">One example of this is within the Oakland Police Department. By changing its foot pursuit policy, rather than chase a suspect into a blind alley, officers are encouraged to call for backup, set a perimeter, and make a plan. This gives officers more distance on the situation, therefore, allowing them to take hold of their decision making. This is where Eberhardt’s idea of “interrogating ourselves and slowing ourselves down” comes into play. Even without knowing the roots of the behavior, as a result, the change in policy positively affected officer injuries and officer-involved shootings. Oakland used to have eight to nine officer-involved shootings every single year, after changing policy, they had eight officer-involved shootings across five years.  </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The glimpses of the anti-bias training being introduced within the workforce are proving to be effective. But it doesn’t stop there. Imagine if these techniques were enforced within our education or criminal justice systems. Eberhardt agrees with the ending of her book, </span><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">Biased: Uncovering the Hidden Prejudice That Shapes What We See, Think, and Do</span></i><span style="font-weight: 400;"> “There is hope in the sheer act of reflection. This is where the power lies and how the process starts.”</span></p>
<p class="align-center"><strong>As for all of us, whether at work or not, think twice before making an association or acting upon a stereotype considering now we know its impacts in creating and reinforcing racialized barriers to opportunity.</strong></p>
<hr>
<p class="align-center"><em><span style="font-weight: 400;">Citations</span></em></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Bertrand, M., and Mullainathan, S., 2020. </span><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">Are Emily And Greg More Employable Than Lakisha And Jamal? A Field Experiment On Labor Market Discrimination</span></i><span style="font-weight: 400;">. Uh.edu. </span><a href="https://www.uh.edu/~adkugler/Bertrand&amp;Mullainathan.pdf"><span style="font-weight: 400;">https://www.uh.edu/~adkugler/Bertrand&amp;Mullainathan.pdf</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;"> </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Chang, A., 2020. </span><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">Can We Overcome Racial Bias? 'Biased' Author Says To Start By Acknowledging It</span></i><span style="font-weight: 400;">.  Npr.org. </span><a href="https://www.npr.org/2019/03/28/705113639/can-we-overcome-racial-bias-biased-author-says-to-start-by-acknowledging-it"><span style="font-weight: 400;">https://www.npr.org/2019/03/28/705113639/can-we-overcome-racial-bias-biased-author-says-to-start-by-acknowledging-it</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;"> </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Hamilton, A., 2020. </span><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">Speaking Of Psychology: Understanding Your Racial Biases</span></i><span style="font-weight: 400;">. Apa.org.</span><a href="https://www.apa.org/research/action/speaking-of-psychology/understanding-biases"><span style="font-weight: 400;">https://www.apa.org/research/action/speaking-of-psychology/understanding-biases</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;">  </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Racial Equity Tools.org. 2020. </span><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">Communicating • Racial Equity Tools</span></i><span style="font-weight: 400;">. Available at: </span><a href="https://www.racialequitytools.org/act/communicating/implicit-bias"><span style="font-weight: 400;">https://www.racialequitytools.org/act/communicating/implicit-bias</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;"> </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Kirwan Institute.osu.edu. 2020. </span><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">Understanding Implicit Bias</span></i><span style="font-weight: 400;">. Available at: </span><a href="http://kirwaninstitute.osu.edu/research/understanding-implicit-bias/"><span style="font-weight: 400;">http://kirwaninstitute.osu.edu/research/understanding-implicit-bias/</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;"> </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Starr, D., 2020. Meet The Psychologist Exploring Unconscious Bias—And Its Tragic Consequences For Society. Science | AAAS. </span><a href="https://www.sciencemag.org/news/2020/03/meet-psychologist-exploring-unconscious-bias-and-its-tragic-consequences-society"><span style="font-weight: 400;">https://www.sciencemag.org/news/2020/03/meet-psychologist-exploring-unconscious-bias-and-its-tragic-consequences-society</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;"> </span></p>
<p><br><br><br><br><br><br><br><br><br><br><br><br><br><br></p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>The Woman Behind NASA&#x27;s Headquarters</title>
        <author>
            <name>Ishan Vepa</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://blog.thegenz.org/the-woman-behind-nasas-headquarters.html"/>
        <id>https://blog.thegenz.org/the-woman-behind-nasas-headquarters.html</id>
            <category term="#science"/>

        <updated>2020-09-15T15:52:02-04:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://blog.thegenz.org/media/posts/47/Mary-Jackson-Abigail-Mullins.jpg" alt="Depiction of Mary Jackson, Aeronautical Engineer" />
                    It has taken Mary Jackson many years to become a familiar name. Even though Jackson was NASA’s first African American female engineer, she was relatively unknown until the book Hidden Figures: The American Dream and the Untold Story of the Black Women Who Helped Win&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <img src="https://blog.thegenz.org/media/posts/47/Mary-Jackson-Abigail-Mullins.jpg" alt="Depiction of Mary Jackson, Aeronautical Engineer" />
                <p><span style="font-weight: 400;">It has taken Mary Jackson many years to become a familiar name. Even though Jackson was NASA’s first African American female engineer, she was relatively unknown until the book </span><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">Hidden Figures: The American Dream and the Untold Story of the Black Women Who Helped Win the Space Race</span></i><span style="font-weight: 400;"> was released in 2016 and a movie of same name came out later that year. Her name may sound especially familiar now as recently, NASA has renamed its Headquarters in Washington DC after her. This honor is well deserved after years of being an unknown “hidden figure.”</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Born in Hampton, Virginia in 1921, Mary Winston graduated from George P. Phenix Training School in 1937 with high honors before receiving a dual bachelor’s degree in math and physical sciences from Hampton Institute (now Hampton University) 5 years later. Before her work at NASA, she had a variety of other jobs. She was a math teacher in Maryland for a year, she was a bookkeeper at her alma mater, she was a mother to her children after marrying Levi Jackson, and she worked as a US Army secretary in the now decommissioned Fort Monroe military base. Finally, in 1951, she began working for the National Advisory Committee on Aeronautics, a predecessor of what would become NASA.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Initially, she started as a research mathematician as one of the “human computers” in the West Area Computing Unit, which worked to provide data that helped the US space program become more successful. Her supervisor was fellow “Hidden Figure” Dorothy Vaugan. In 1953 she moved to the Compressibility Research division of NACA where she conducted experiments with a supersonic pressure tunnel.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Since it was the 1950s, Jackson faced discrimination as segregation was still legal in her Virginia workplace. Her West Area Computing Unit primarily consisted of African American women. While whites got to go to the cafeteria and order and eat their food from there, blacks had to ask an attendant for their food and had to sit at their desks, which Jackson considered an “indignity.” Bathrooms were also segregated. Fed up with the mistreatment, Jackson considered resigning, but Kazimierz Czarnecki, an engineer, encouraged her to stay and work for him. She agreed, and he told her to take engineering classes so she could have a better chance of being promoted to an engineer.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Not all was smooth sailing. Jackson had to get permission to attend the all white Hampton High School for engineering classes, which she eventually did get. She would go on to complete all of her courses. Finally, in 1958, her work was finally recognized as she was promoted to aeronautical engineer for the newly created NASA. She was the first and only black female engineer in an otherwise male-dominated field at the time. She worked with wind tunnels and analyzed data that came from experiments. She also authored/co-authored 12 papers over the course of her career as an engineer.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Despite her success as an engineer, Jackson was never offered management positions as she was still being discriminated against for her race and gender. Sick of this, in 1979 she took a demotion and worked as a Federal Women’s Program Manager. The work she did, however, was still extremely important. She was able to help women and minorities advance their careers at NASA. As she once did herself, she encouraged them to take extra classes so they were more likely to receive a promotion. She eventually retired in 1985 and passed away 20 years later.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Mary Jackson used her position to help the next generation of women to pursue careers in STEM by enabling them to become scientists, engineers, and mathematicians. Without her efforts, many women may have felt discouraged that they couldn’t pursue a career they wanted. It is because of her work that more women felt that they could work at places such as NASA. By breaking boundaries herself, she could also be a source of inspiration for others and prove that anybody could do what she did, regardless of their gender or race.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">NASA’s headquarters isn’t the only place to be renamed after this amazing woman. It was announced in 2018 that Jackson Elementary in Salt Lake City, Utah was renamed Mary W. Jackson Elementary School in her honor. Even though it took over 50 years to receive credit for the work she has done, it is good to see that her, and even Katherine Johnso and Dorothy Vaugan, finally receive some attention and praise that is well deserved. Even though there are plenty more women who have yet to be recognized, it’s good to see Mary Johnson finally be celebrated and honored for what she has accomplished.</span></p>
<hr>
<p class="align-center"><em><span style="font-weight: 400;">Citations</span></em></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The Editors of Encyclopedia Britannica. “Mary Jackson.” </span><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">Encyclopædia Britannica</span></i><span style="font-weight: 400;">, Encyclopædia Britannica, Inc., 9 Apr. 2020, www.britannica.com/biography/Mary-Jackson-mathematician-and-engineer.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Explained Desk. “Mary Jackson: NASA's First African American Female Aeronautical Engineer.” </span><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">The Indian Express</span></i><span style="font-weight: 400;">, 26 June 2020, indianexpress.com/article/explained/mary-jackson-nasa-6477210/.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">“Jackson, Mary.” </span><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">Encyclopædia Britannica</span></i><span style="font-weight: 400;">, Encyclopædia Britannica, www.britannica.com/biography/Mary-Jackson-mathematician-and-engineer/images-videos#/media/1/2091689/238758.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Potter, Sean, et al. “NASA Names Headquarters After 'Hidden Figure' Mary W. Jackson.” </span><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">NASA</span></i><span style="font-weight: 400;">, NASA, 24 June 2020, www.nasa.gov/press-release/nasa-names-headquarters-after-hidden-figure-mary-w-jackson.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Timmons, Greg. “Mary Jackson.” </span><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">Biography.com</span></i><span style="font-weight: 400;">, A&amp;E Networks Television, 6 Dec. 2016, </span><a href="http://www.biography.com/scientist/mary-winston-jackson"><span style="font-weight: 400;">www.biography.com/scientist/mary-winston-jackson</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;">.</span></p>
<p><br><br></p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Cut Down Deforestation</title>
        <author>
            <name>Ishan Vepa</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://blog.thegenz.org/cut-down-deforestation.html"/>
        <id>https://blog.thegenz.org/cut-down-deforestation.html</id>
            <category term="#science"/>
            <category term="#environment"/>
            <category term="#energy"/>
            <category term="#climate"/>

        <updated>2020-09-15T17:41:51-04:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://blog.thegenz.org/media/posts/46/Deforestation-Article-Photo-Alyson-Torino.jpg" alt="Deforestation present in a woodland." />
                    Let’s talk about how deforestation usually begins: forest degradation. Trees are one of the world’s most valuable resources. They are a plentiful resource that is very versatile in terms of its possible usage. They can be used for their wood, for their fruit, and for&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <img src="https://blog.thegenz.org/media/posts/46/Deforestation-Article-Photo-Alyson-Torino.jpg" alt="Deforestation present in a woodland." />
                <p class="msg msg--highlight "><strong><em>Let’s talk about how deforestation usually begins: forest degradation.</em></strong></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Trees are one of the world’s most valuable resources. They are a plentiful resource that is very versatile in terms of its possible usage. They can be used for their wood, for their fruit, and for their oxygen. We also use trees for construction, manufacturing, and fuel. However, those trees also serve a purpose besides what we use them for: they are home to other plants and animals, yet we cut them down without regard for that. Deforestation has an impact not only on us, but also on the plants and animals that live, or used to live, in those forests that have been cleared. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Forest degradation, according to the World Wildlife Fund (WWF), is when a forest has been cut down enough to still exist, but has undergone too much damage to function as normal. It is most commonly caused by illegal logging. Once one company starts to cut, it will be followed by others, quickly changing from forest degradation to deforestation. This may not seem like a very pressing issue at first, but the scale at which it is occurring is startling. According to National Geographic, between 1600 and 1870, half of Eastern North America’s forests were cut down. Additionally, 2,000 years ago, Europe was 80% forested, which has dropped to an alarming 34% today, on top of China being only 20% forested. This pushes most, if not all, of the wildlife in these areas out of their normal environments, causing endangerment to multiple species of plants and animals. The WWF says that we are losing forests at a rate of 27 soccer fields per minute, but how are we clearing these forests so fast? One lovely little technique that is being used is called slash and burn.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">You can probably guess what slash and burn is based off of the name. The trees in the desired area are cut down, and then burned into ash. The areas where this technique is used are usually tropical forests and are turned into agricultural areas, since the ash acts as a good fertilizer. However, this land is only fertile for a few years, leaving an open and dry environment where a moist and sheltered one used to be. If the deforestation wasn’t already bad enough, this makes the land vulnerable to erosion and wildfires. The remaining wildlife is once again put at risk due to these new conditions, adding more and more consequences to deforestation. There is still one more thing that I haven’t discussed that trees are notorious for: oxygen.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Trees are not the largest producers of oxygen. That title goes to all of the microscopic phytoplankton in the ocean and other bodies of water. However, every densely populated area on Earth, and by that I mean populated by both plants and animals, has an equal exchange of oxygen and carbon dioxide. In simpler terms, the so-called “Lungs of Earth” Amazon Rainforest uses up all of the oxygen it produces, leaving the other forests and phytoplankton of the world to produce the oxygen that will be used in their area. This makes the trees that we have left very important because oxygen is necessary for us to survive, and if we keep cutting them down at the current rate, the levels of oxygen and carbon dioxide in the atmosphere will become imbalanced. This leads to the much larger problem of global warming, but that is an issue for an entirely different article to cover.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">In order to help with this cause, you can buy products that have been approved by the Forest Stewardship Council (FSC). This organization ensures that the product was made with trees that were harvested within local and international laws. You can also donate to foundations like the Rainforest Alliance, who help save ecosystems at risk and fight climate change. While we are the ones who caused all of these damages with deforestation, we can also be the ones to solve it.</span></p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Why Schools should Switch Times?</title>
        <author>
            <name>Ishan Vepa</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://blog.thegenz.org/why-schools-should-switch-times.html"/>
        <id>https://blog.thegenz.org/why-schools-should-switch-times.html</id>
            <category term="#infrastructure"/>
            <category term="#education"/>

        <updated>2020-09-14T18:27:36-04:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://blog.thegenz.org/media/posts/45/pexels-dids-2675050.jpg" alt="Photo of Empty Class Room" />
                    It’s around 6:00 am in the morning and your alarm goes off. You groan and dreadingly press snooze. Ten minutes later, you force yourself to get out of bed. You get ready as if you are a zombie, but quickly at the same time because&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <img src="https://blog.thegenz.org/media/posts/45/pexels-dids-2675050.jpg" alt="Photo of Empty Class Room" />
                <p><span style="font-weight: 400;">It’s around 6:00 am in the morning and your alarm goes off. You groan and dreadingly press snooze. Ten minutes later, you force yourself to get out of bed. You get ready as if you are a zombie, but quickly at the same time because you can't be late for school. You skip breakfast, because your exhaustion makes the sound of food disgusting. You go to school, and run on little sleep even though you have two tests, and one is during first period. How can you perform well in school under these conditions?</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The</span><span style="font-weight: 400;"> times of high school and elementary schools need to be switched because of student's natural sleep cycles, the fact that high school students perform better in school at later times, and elementary school children will only need care in the afternoon, instead of in the morning and afternoon, in order to benefit students so they can be healthier, perform better at school, and put less stress on themselves and their parents.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The most sensible reason to switch the schedules of elementary schools and high schools, is because of the fact that high schoolers perform better later in the day. A research team that conducted a three year long study of eight different high schools that switched to later times, determined that there were, “Significant increases in grade point average in </span><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">all</span></i><span style="font-weight: 400;"> 1st-period core courses for </span><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">all</span></i><span style="font-weight: 400;"> semesters in </span><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">all </span></i><span style="font-weight: 400;">grades in Jackson Hole High School in Wyoming, with a start time of 8:55 a.m.” This data is from Phi Delta Kappan (The professional journal for educators), and it demonstrates how making high school start later can improve grades in all first period classes. Schools want their students to perform well, but students simply cannot when they wake up so early.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">If high school and elementary school start times switch, younger children will only require afternoon daycare. According to the article </span><span style="font-weight: 400;">"What Is the Advantage of Having School Start Early?", “</span><span style="font-weight: 400;">There are specific advantages for parents if younger grades have early start times. Starting school early may eliminate the need for morning childcare if parents are able to drop off their kids before work.” If children are not in need of childcare parents save money, and stress levels decrease regarding their let’s face it, very stressful children.  Plus, having your child only attend daycare in one part of the day is just easier for both the parents and the child.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">On the other hand, switching the times of high school and elementary school, will cause high school to end later. According to classroom.synonym.com, “school administrators cited extracurricular activities as a major reason why high school campuses would rather start earlier in the day.”</span> <span style="font-weight: 400;">Although this may be sensible at first glance, also consider that if high school students wake up later, they can go to sleep later, ultimately giving them the same amount of time to participate in clubs and sports.</span> <span style="font-weight: 400;">Also, in the study from Phi Delta Kappan that was previously mentioned, they discovered a common worry that they never had difficulty with was “Participation in after-school activities may decline.”  This exhibits how high schools can have later start times as well as participation in sports and clubs.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The final reason why high school and elementary schools should switch schedules, is because of student’s natural sleep cycles. The article,  “Elementary and High School Should Switch Times”, states, “Younger children tend to naturally wake up earlier than teenagers and adults, and they are able to have more energy early in the morning”. Then why wouldn't young kids start school earliest, if they’re already awake and have energy? Plus, teens cannot get a good amount of sleep when school starts so early. According to Phi Delta Kappan</span><span style="font-weight: 400;">, “Teens need about 9.25 hours of sleep each night, a difficult amount to obtain when the brain doesn’t enter sleep mode until about 10:45 p.m. and when students must awaken early for a school day that begins before 8:30 a.m.”  These facts clearly illustrate how it is physically impossible for a high school student to get 9 hours of sleep when they are falling asleep at 11, and waking up at around 6 for school.  The article also briefly mentions how teens’ brains remain in sleep mode until about 8 am. This means that even if teens are awake before eight, they are not really awake.  Schools need to stop encouraging sleep deprivation, for the health of their students.  </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;"> </span><span style="font-weight: 400;">In conclusion, high school and elementary schools should switch schedules because high school students do not perform well early in the morning, elementary school children would only need afternoon daycare, and high schoolers cannot get enough sleep for school.</span></p>
<p><strong> </strong><span style="font-weight: 400;">If you think about it, when was the last time you got 8 to 9 hours of sleep before school, besides in elementary school?</span></p>
<hr>
<p class="align-center"><em>Citations</em></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Anderson, Marie. "What Is the Advantage of Having School Start Early?" Synonym, https://classroom.synonym.com/advantage-having-school-start-early-4526.html. Accessed 09 July 2020.  </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Campbell, Leah. “Research Shows Early School Start Times Are Bad for Kids’ Health.” </span><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">Healthline</span></i><span style="font-weight: 400;">, 13 Aug. 2018, www.healthline.com/health-news/early-school-start-times-bad-for-kids-health#1. Accessed 09 July 2020.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Wahlstrom, Kyla L. “Later Start Time for Teens Improves Grades, Mood, and Safety.” </span><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">Kappanonline.org</span></i><span style="font-weight: 400;">, Phi Delta Kappa International, Dec. 2016/Jan. 2017, www.kappanonline.org/later-start-time-for-teens/. </span></p>
<p> </p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
</feed>
